{"forumData":[{"question":"where can we view our final marks","answers":[{"text":"get a transcript via myunsw","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will we be receiving feedback from our exams and assignments i can see the assignment marks in webcms but feedback would be good and as far as i can tell we haven't received our specific exam mark let alone any feedback from it. thanks","answers":[{"text":"you can see the marking output from your assignments by going to the assignment x submission page and clicking collect submission. no doubt this will trigger a rash of complaints along the lines of i deserved more marks . you should be able to work out your scaled exam mark from finalmark - labs quizzes assign1 assign2 blogging note that exam marks were heavily scaled up ... can't fail too many even if they deserve it because they failed to demonstrate programming competence or knowledge of computer systems.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi is it normal for us to be unable to view our assignment 1 marks still thanks","answers":[{"text":"yet another comp1521 stuff-up ... now fixed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"most likely tomorrow or by 8th dec","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have received an le for final mark. but i have finished all the course work and done the exams. i would like to have my marks rechecked.","answers":[{"text":"everyone has le. wait until dec 8th or so","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi if we still don't have our assignment marks yet should we email our tutor or wait a few more days","answers":[{"text":"wait ... all of your tutors have gone away for summer so they won't be marking them. the plan is to finish comp1521 off by late next week.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i still have not got my grade for assignment 1 and assignment 2. it is showing n/a in my grades web page. anyone has the same case","answers":[{"text":"hi try clicking the arrow box next to n/a on your sturec for assignment 2 if it has been marked you will be able to see a mark on the submission collection.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i find it. it is so great.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"everyone is in the same boat. don't expect to see any marks before november 20.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"given it is now approaching 11 weeks since the first assignment was submitted and 6 weeks since the second i can't see how this can be deemed acceptable.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i agree this is well bellow the acceptable standard it shows a failure of not just planning but of the course management and those responsible for checking courses are running properly and intervene when nessesary.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"actually the 2nd assignment for some is out. i have mine it depends on whether the tutors have marked it or not. since the tutors also have exams you might be lucky to get ur ass2 mark.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi will the mark of le eventually change to something else and around what time would that happen if it does thanks.","answers":[{"text":"it will change to a proper mark/grade a couple of days after we submit the marks to unsw. i'm expecting this to happen around december 3 or 4.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was unable to attend the final due to medical reasons. will the supplementary be of equal difficulty to the standard final or do they increase the difficulty due to the extra time those who take the supplementary exam have","answers":[{"text":"alright thank you.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's impossible to make something of equal difficulty but there's no intention to make it harder.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"or easier.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"could you tell me how i can query my lab results because when i query the results on the web page it is still blank.thank you","answers":[{"text":"once the exam in my pg course is over i'll be working full-time on the marking backlog.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if i pass 7/10 test in the q3 do i get some of the mark of it thanks","answers":[{"text":"it said on the exam that you could get partial marks for programming questions. i think it said the same thing in the 17s2 sample exam. read it again.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when do we have the supplementary exam timetable","answers":[{"text":"supps will be in december ... around the 9th but they're only available for people who did not sit the exam today and have a good reason for not doing so.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but outline says there are other ways which can gain the chance for supplementary exam","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes yes ... there's the close to pass and so on clause ... it's still around december 9 and i won't know who's eligible for at least two weeks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if i my final mark is in the range 47 finalmark lt 50 or 20 exammark lt 24 and finalmark 50 when can i take the supplementary exam","answers":[{"text":"or less precisely sometime around december 9","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"december 9","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there. may i ask what is the command if we want to use qtspim in the exam is it qtspim main.s or qtspim exe.s","answers":[{"text":"$ qtspim after that load exe.s to qtspim.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks a lot jiaxuan","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are we allowed to create files to test out theory questions in final exam","answers":[{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we use man 7 ascii in writing section","answers":[{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run check command i got following error and i can not fighre out why running 'make' ... just in case you haven't make nothing to be done for all'. ok couldn't make q2 q2 is not executable can i get some idea why that happen thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"i have the same problem and i do not know how to fix it. please if you fixed that share it here. thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no idea. trying to infer from the very limited info you sent i'd be guessing that you're in a directory that contains a directory called q2 but if that were the case the check script should have complained about not finding a tests directory ... unless there was a tests directory ... impossible to work out without seeing your complete environment.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi jas i have also tried the lab5 autotest for isk.s it also does not work. i wonder if because the test root has been changed and we are not able to use these autotest anymore thank you in advance","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"this has happened many times for different questions z5200681 vx4 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/prac_exams/week11/04/q2$ ls -alh total 56k drwx------ 3 z5200681 z5200681 4.0k nov 4 02 19 . drwxr-x--- 4 z5200681 z5200681 4.0k nov 4 01 38 .. -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 206 oct 23 2017 makefile -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 2.3k nov 4 02 19 students.c -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 296 oct 25 2017 students.h -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 6.4k nov 4 02 19 students.o -rwxr-x--- 1 z5200681 z5200681 12k nov 4 02 19 stu -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 662 oct 25 2017 stu.c -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 4.5k nov 4 02 10 stu.o drwxr-x--- 2 z5200681 z5200681 4.0k oct 11 22 07 tests z5200681 vx4 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/prac_exams/week11/04/q2$ check q2 running 'make' ... just in case you haven't make stu' is up to date. ok couldn't make q2 q2 is not executable z5200681 vx4 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/prac_exams/week11/04/q2$","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"happens for q2 in practice exam 5 also. z5200681 vx4 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/prac_exams/week11/05/q2$ ls -alh total 60k drwx------ 3 z5200681 z5200681 4.0k nov 4 03 19 . drwxr-x--- 4 z5200681 z5200681 4.0k nov 4 02 42 .. -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 290 oct 26 2017 makefile -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 2.1k nov 4 03 19 students.c -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 303 oct 26 2017 students.h -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 2.4k nov 4 03 19 students.o -rwxr-x--- 1 z5200681 z5200681 7.8k nov 4 03 19 mkstu -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 596 oct 26 2017 mkstu.c -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 1.4k nov 4 03 19 mkstu.o -rwxr-x--- 1 z5200681 z5200681 7.8k nov 4 03 19 stu -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 593 oct 26 2017 stu.c -rw-r----- 1 z5200681 z5200681 1.5k nov 4 03 16 stu.o drwxr-x--- 2 z5200681 z5200681 4.0k nov 4 03 19 tests z5200681 vx4 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/prac_exams/week11/05/q2$ check q2 running 'make' ... just in case you haven't make nothing to be done for all'. ok couldn't make q2 q2 is not executable z5200681 vx4 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/prac_exams/week11/05/q2$","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"hi there if 0x2710 is 10000 in decimal wouldn't that imply it's in index 1 of the process address space since every page is 8kb big","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are there files for the sample exam","answers":[{"text":"no. take the solutions remove the relevant bits and try to re-create them.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"deleted","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"and are we allowed to use the terminal while answering questions 4 to 12 cheers harold","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is that outlined somewhere in the exam spec and given that s the case how do we use submit","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"obviously there will also be check and submit","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i m sorry but i am strugglingto find where a distinction has been made between materials accessible for questions1-3 and 4-12 in the exam information. if you could please point me in the right direction to find such a distinction in the exam specification it would be greatly appreciated. regards harold","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"how do we access check and submit without the terminal or do you mean we can't use the specific terminal application on the cse computers but we get the exam environment shell","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"when did i say that you would not have a terminal the setup is the same as what you had in the week 11 lab.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry when harold asked are we allowed to use the terminal while answering questions 4 to 12 and you said no i interpreted that as us not being able to use the terminal.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey sir why 100000 cannoy be presented by either binary system or hexdecimal system thanks","answers":[{"text":"is it because it is a 16 bit sting instead of 32 bit sting which we usually use","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the above answers would make sense if the context was 16-bit ints whose maximum value is 65535 . the question clearly says that we're dealing with 16-bit quantities ... give a representation for each of the following decimal values in 16-bit twos-complement bit-strings","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"exit or _exit what is the main difference between exit and _exit and when do we use them","answers":[{"text":"void exit int status terminates current process triggers any functions registered as lt large gt atexit lt /large gt flushes stdio buffers closes open lt large gt file lt /large gt 's then behaves like lt large gt _exit lt /large gt this is from lec slides","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi the autotest for previous lab and and every prac exam q2 does not work now. is there any way that we can access the autotest or can it be fixed thank you in advanceeeeee","answers":[{"text":"i assume you mean that check has stopped working. the check script is nothing magical. it ssimply runs all of the tests in the relevant tests directory. you can run individual tests via e.g. sh tests/1.sh in the directory where the appropriate code and the tests are located.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we use 'man 2' to search for functions during the exam thanks","answers":[{"text":"yes you can access man pages. most things you'd want to find for this course would be in man 2 3 and 7","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will the solutions for practice exams be uploaded thanks.","answers":[{"text":"no","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are the correct answers to the quizzes available anywhere","answers":[{"text":"q1 d b c c q2 e b b e q3 b b b a q4 b b d b q5 c a d c q6 b d c b","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is wsn security gonna be assessed","answers":[{"text":"no","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i've heard a lot of people had trouble with mips in the practice exam and still aren't confident programming in it so i made a bunch of practice exercises for people to use to make sure they get some practice doing a variety of programming tasks in mips. many of them are similar to exercises you may have done in comp1511. you can access the page here http //z5214348.web.cse.unsw.edu.au/prac/ notes all of the mips exercises i've made available have 10 autotests you can run using check similar to how we do for lab exercises and have starting code usually just a main function skeleton or a simple loop to iterate through an array and print out values . i also made a simple utility to run mips code called 'run' which is included in the 'code.zip' in each practice exercise- it's just a basic c program which will either run '1521 spim -file lt file gt ' if on a cse machine or 'spim -file lt file gt ' if on your home computer assuming it can find the executable . also it will default to running exe.s or main.s files if it can find them in the current directory or you can pass in a mips file as the first argument ./run lt mips file gt . i hope that some of you find these exercises useful. i'll be posting more up as the week goes by - it takes me a while to sort out the autotests. if there is a high demand for them then i'll also post sample solutions for all of the exercises i can. kind regards and happy studying callum avery","answers":[{"text":"hi when i try to run the check main.s command for the question it tell me bash check command not found so can i have some idea about how can i run the test check main.s bash check command not found thank you in advance","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the check tool is a tool which is in the cs1521/bin. in order to use this you need to be running a 1521 subshell run '1521' by itself in a cse environment shell and then the 'check' command should work .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hey sorry i'm getting a slightly different problem. usage /home/cs1521/bin/check q1 q2 q3 not sure how to fix this. thanks for such a great resource","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"dw i fixed it. i needed to use the check.old command","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"excellent work i thoroughly endorse these.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"qtspim error attempt to execute non-instruction at address i am only getting this issue on the cse computers. the way i use qtspim is type 'qtspim' in command line wait for it to open up file gt load file. i get this issue no matter which mips file i am using. even for code that is correct i know it's correct because when i run the tests i pass all of them . what's even more strange is that qtspim works fine on my own computer. if i load the same file the same way qtspim works properly and does not show me this error. why doesn't it work on the cse computers also i tried looking for the instruction at the address shown but it's no where to be found on the page. anyone know why this may be happening","answers":[{"text":"have you tried single-stepping the code to find out where it jumps to 0x004005a8","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi john thank you for replying. yes it just shows the error straight away. how i did it just then right click desktop - gt applications - gt other - gt qtspim - gt file - gt load file - gt pick an exe.s file - gt click on the single step button on the menu. i tried putting a break point on the second instruction of the page before clicking on single step and it still comes up with the error. am really confused...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what value is showing in the pc register before and after you load the program","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"before when i first open qtspim after loading the file after i try to run the program","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"can't work it out from here. email me exe.s . what does the command which qtspim show","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"during the exam can we make another gedit to test the some of the theory questions on terminal","answers":[{"text":"you can open as many xterm s and gedit s as you like during the exam.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you should be able to open up more than one terminal in the exam environment and also gedit.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we express that answer with 0xfffb","answers":[{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will solutions for the sample exam questions be released if so when and where","answers":[{"text":"released","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in solution it says that for char type there are 1 byte and 3 bytes padding. i am confused about what is '3 bytes padding'. thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"the padding ensures that uoc_done is aligned to a 4 byte boundary. if status happened to be at offset 40 from the start of the record and you simply allocated 1 byte for the field then uoc_done would be located at offset 41. this does not produce a valid address for an int value.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will we have access to bc in the exam","answers":[{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is the compiling flag in the final exam gcc -wall -werror -std gnu99 -o or gcc -wall -werror -std c99 -o","answers":[{"text":"hadn't decided ... which would you prefer","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the one where you can specify the int in a for loop","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"gnu99 would be better.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was wondering whether ' 0' is counted as a character in mips. i've attempted q1 of practice test 3 and below is what happens. my code successfully converts the string to lower case however there are errors thrown. am i supposed to be using a string for ' 0' instead","answers":[{"text":"possibly try 'nul' or just a 0 the null terminator maps to a 0 ascii value","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i've tried both and they don't work but thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"loading 0 in does work did you load as an integer rather than enclosed in quotes eg li $t0 0 then append to the dest array using sb alternatively you should be able to load the null terminator from the src string in the same way as all the other chars and save it in the dest string. let me know if that still isn't working as it might be a separate issue","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i was using just 0 but turns out a typo had caused the bad address issue.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"in any case i'm working on the auto-testing for ass2 now.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"why does it matter i.e. how does knowing your assignment marks make any difference to your exam preparation where you should always be trying to get 100 anyway.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"of course it is. for me sometimes just keep worrying about it cos didnt do well in assignments. thanks for ur advice.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas will solutions/answers for the practice exams available be released thank you","answers":[{"text":"this week oct 22-26","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas can we have a little more sample exam such as the 18s1 one even without file and test really want to get some more information about the final exam. thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"the sample and 17s2 exams are quite representative enough of comp1521 exams. not to mention the practice prac exam questions.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi are we allowed to use python in the final exam to help us convert hex to binary","answers":[{"text":"python is not available in the exam environment.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i wanna redo the sample exam. in this case how to download the test file in vlab or i have to copy and paste those files one by one thanks.","answers":[{"text":"if i have time in the next week i'll make an exam.tar file available for the sample exam. in the meantime copy and paste the files one-by-one.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the problem i met is that for example in q1 i copied 1.exe and 1.sh then gave command exe array.s but nothing came out","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"try running '1521 exe array.s' - exe is in the cs1521/bin directory so in order to run it you need to be running a 1521 subshell.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi is there a possibility the final exam will ask us to write code for a stack or queue implementation thanks","answers":[{"text":"thanks for the suggestion. there was always a possibility of this.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was really struggled doing sample exam. so just wanna know when will the solutions be realesd wihch whould be really helpful for students like me. and btw when will we get our assignment feedback. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"no solutions will be released for the prac exam. just reading solutions doesn't help so much. ask your tutor to go through the process of developing the solution in tutes this week. this is far more useful. assignment marks should be done by week 13.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi will the questions in the practice lab test be released if we want to redo them thanks.","answers":[{"text":"have a look under sample exams","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i have a question about mips. how to show the if string i ' 0' in mips or say in mips how to show the ' 0' i write it as beq $s0 ' 0' else bne $s0 ' 0' if ps. the string i is in $s0. but it is showing wrong. please help","answers":[{"text":"use the int constant 0 rather than the char ' 0' for representing the nul char. in this case the instruction is assuming that the first two operands are registers . since you happen to have a register that always contains the value 0 you could that $0","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have an exam on the morning of november 5th that clashes with the final for this class. how should i proceed","answers":[{"text":"there is both a morning and afternoon exam session for comp1521. attend the afternoon session of the comp1521 exam. we'll be putting up a timeslot selection page soon and we know about all of the clashes already.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm just enquiring about the overall view of the use of the goto function for the assignment. usually i would avoid it but it makes my code a lot cleaner to view. is the goto function actually allowed to be used in 1521 thanks","answers":[{"text":"beware of dinosaurs https //xkcd.com/292/","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'd be very very careful in thinking a goto' would be useful here. prefer other control flow mechanisms first. but if it comes down to it and you're absolutely dying without it sure. be very very very clear about what you're doing with it more so than you usually would.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there i was just wondering if it would be at all possible to get some form of worked solutions to any of the questions specifically practical q's in the past exams posted i understand if this is not able to be done but i think many of us would really appreciate being able to check our attempts and improve our understanding/approach through having an idea of what would be expected as sufficient answers. otherwise any recommendations for ways to enhance our practical ability would be much appreciated as i am not sure where to find questions to practice and review my understanding of the content in the course. thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"i was just wondering if it would be at all possible to get some form of worked solutions to any of the questions specifically practical q's in the past exams posted see the notice i posted this morning. the answer is yes. i thought all of the theory exercises were already visible. apparently not but now they are. i am not sure where to find questions to practice any of the recommended texts garica-molina/ullman/widom silberschatz/korth/... will have a whole bunch of exercises and you may be able to find answers. and there are the exercises i did or at least noted in lectures.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we run code to deal with essay questions in final thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi are there going to be some autotests released soon from assignment 2 spec for correct performance measured by auto-testing on a range of test cases some of which will be provided for you to test your code as you write it","answers":[{"text":"after thinking about it and seeing some of the questions on the forum it's clear that giving you an auto-testing framework is never going to work. the chances of your mymysh running in your environment producing the same output as our expected output is almost zero. for us running it in our test environment is no problem because the environment is completely controlled by us. however i'll put up some examples of the kinds of tests we'll be using and the kinds of expected output for each. you can run them in your own directory but will have to interpret them relative to your environment.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks jas. for the practice practical lab test this week do we get access to the mips cheat sheet","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey sir when will we get feedback from assignment 1","answers":[{"text":"maybe this week.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how can we change to the home directory to make a file thanks","answers":[{"text":"you don't need to change to the home directory find the full path name of the home directory and then concatenate /.mymysh_history to it to get a complete filename.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will the child process stop after executing the execve function when i want to print something after the execve function it seems nothing can be printed. thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"if execve succeeds then it won't return to the code after it is called. what it is doing is basically replacing the currently executing program with another program to run. the child process will therefore exit from its new program rather than the one it was running before exec was called. if you can print anything after execve you can assume that execve failed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so if we want to print something after execve should we look through the command history and then determine if we need to print something","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi what is the use of command number in main function what is the command to clear the command history in that file every time when i use the cs1521/bin/mymysh and show the command history and there exists 8 commands. and when i close the terminal and open it again there are still 8 commands in history and what i typed before does not exist thanks","answers":[{"text":"if you want to clear the command history file simply remove it rm /.mymysh_history it sounds like you're not writing the history properly when you exit mymysh","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but i use the cs1521/bin/mymysh to test it seems that it cannot be removed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"cs1521/bin/mymysh uses your /.mymysh_history if you remove that file and the hsitory doesn't go away then there's something wrong with your initcommandhistory","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am still confused about what should we initialise in initcommandhistory the struct that needs to use have all been initialised above that function. thanks","answers":[{"text":"the struct might exist ... but what values does it contain maybe you need to fill it up from the history file.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will there be solutions for the wk 7 tutorial questions","answers":[{"text":"there will be solutions to all tutorial questions when i get some time to copy them across.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi question about the quiz mark i remembered that i submitted the quiz5 question but it is not shown in my marks. so could you double check if my quiz 6 answer has successfully been submitted thank you","answers":[{"text":"your quiz 6 has been submitted.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i haven't uploaded the quiz 5 marks from webcms3 to sms yet.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will the debugging lecture be recorded and uploaded","answers":[{"text":"yes ... i've grabbed the video from echo360 and edited it. i'll upload on thursday morning.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am still confused about how to use the chdir function. it is said in main that i should put a const str as an argument but i don't know what should this string be. thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"the pathname of the directory you want to change to ... e.g. /home/cs1521/","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi my compiler seems to be stuck in dcc even though my makefile specifies gcc. is there any way i can fix this here is a screenshot of what that looks like using c99 throws a lot more errors . also is there any way i can get past the error shown here because i'm calling addtocommandhistory in init i'm setting the struct in addtocommandhistory while i've initalised the strut in init. thanks in advance.","answers":[{"text":"are you using commandhistory anywhere else in your code","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes i'm writing the contents of commandhistory into the history file in savecommandhistory and i'm also printing from commandhistory in showcommandhistory.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the error message says that you're not using it ... in the function initcommandhistory . if you've moved the definition of commandhistory into this function then put it back outside like it was in the supplied code. if the original definition is still there outside any function get rid of your above definition. your initialiser is not correct in any case ... it's not an array of int values.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you i've gotten rid of my above definition and my compiler is back to gcc i have no clue why it went to dcc yesterday .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was just wondering if there will be more than one time slot for the final exam or if there is only one session. also will these be posted on webcms or will they get updated to the exam time table on myunsw for us to check thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"in the past there have been two exams one in the morning and one if the afternoon of the same day. jas will ask for an requests and if you don't give one you will be randomly assigned. the final timetable will be posted on webcms and you will be emailed.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"regarding the pwd functionality - is it safe to assume it will not be longer than maxline answer to this is probably no . if not are we allowed to use the posix.1-2001 standard change referenced in the man to dynamically create the string so long as we free it as an extension to the posix.1-2001 standard glibc's getcwd allocates the buffer dynamically using malloc 3 if buf is null. in this case the allocated buffer has the length size unless size is zero when buf is allocated as big as necessary. the caller should free 3 the returned buffer.","answers":[{"text":"you can use the posix extension. we'll be running it with the appropriate library.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas is there a way to see what's been written in our home/.mymysh_history thanks.","answers":[{"text":"just cat the file. or open it in a text editor.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas how should i think of handle history substitution in the main and how it works","answers":[{"text":"look at the examples. try it out on the reference solution.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"another question is about glob function i am confused about the first parameter pattern and i had checked man glob that it said matching pattern according to the rules used by the shell what's this parameter means","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"try some examples with the real shell e.g. echo .c to see how filename pattern-matching works.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so can i use /ass2/ for the first parameter of glob or argv else","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"have a look at 'man 7 glob' for what can be given as the first parameter.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sure as the first parameter to glob but it's unlikely to match anything so the result returned from glob would be the single string /ass2/","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"how should i find the right command line in the stdin by using loop cause i wanna deal with handle history substitution this part","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"history substitution and glob are for different parts of the shell. if a input needs history substitution it should be felt with first and no globbing or redirecting should be done.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas regarding to the cleancommandhisotry function i am a little bit confused and would like some clarification. since you have declared commandhistory as a global variable already does this mean we don't need to malloc memory to it anymore since any changes to it will be kept. for example if we call addtocommandhistory cmdline seqno it will still remain its changes after this function finishes. so do we still need cleancommandhisotry but maybe my understanding towards global variable is wrong looking forward to the response. cheers","answers":[{"text":"if you look carefully at the historyentry data structure you'll see that the comandline field is a pointer not a buffer so it needs tp be malloc 'd ... and cleaned. you're barking up the wrong tree with your global variable theory.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh i see. thank you for the clarification. also i just noticed that for the history substitution if we type something in bash like e it will be replaced by exit h will be replaced by history and so on. do we need to take this feature into consideration","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"mymysh isn't bash. only implemt whats in the spec.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"why this information occur when i sign in the vlab","answers":[{"text":"have you got two vlab windows open","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas how do we recovered our deleted files or directory in unix","answers":[{"text":"there's a command called tkrestore that can get them from the latest backup which probably happened early in the morning. it's described on the cse taggi . if you've made more changes since then then you've lost it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas would you mind uploading the lecture note of week 9 network. the lecture note on week 8 appears to be about network but they are actually about concurrency if we click in. thank you very much.","answers":[{"text":"i'm not sure why you say the lecture note on week 8 appears to be about network . they may have had the old networks slides attached there last week but i'm pretty sure i changed them on friday maybe earlier to the new concurrency slides. in any case i'm still working on the week 09 slides. i'll post them when they're in better shape. maybe you're talking about the course notes. they're mislabelled. i'll fix them now.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh yes i was talking about the labels. thank you very much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are the lecture slides down i get access forbidden","answers":[{"text":"i think i've fixed them.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will we go over the bank example with semaphores in the next lecture the recording just cut out just as jas was saying you can use semaphores to solve the producer consumer problem or will it be on the recording that isn't on echo","answers":[{"text":"come to think of it i didn't do that exercise ... i looked at the producer-consumer example. i'll do the bank example tomorrow.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's on my recording ... which i'll upload to youtube tomorrow wed morning.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are the quizes changed to one attempt only since previous quizes allows multiple attempts","answers":[{"text":"not intentionally. i've fixed it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"i'm not sure of the context but often indexes are in the range 0..npages-1.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how does fork know which is the parent in order to set the return value in the child to 0 at the moment it seems like fork in the parent creates a duplicate and gets the pid of the child it created but how does the recently created child know that it isn't a parent and then execute the fork as well instead of just putting 0 into the pid cheers.","answers":[{"text":"the child gets a return value of 0 from fork . that's how it knows it's not the parent.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi robert i'm not sure if this answers your question or not let me know if anything is still unclear. when we use the fork function the operating system creates a new process for us that is a fairly exact copy of the parent. the new process has its own address space think virtual memory that we just did in the labs but initially it copies the parent's address space. it assigns this new process a pid. the parent and the child will then run as separate processes. from the fork the parent gets a return value the os hands it the pid of the new process child just created. in the child we also return from fork even though technically the child didn't exist when the fork was called and the os hands the child process 0 as the return value. if we want to check if it's the parent or child we simply check if the return value from fork was 0 or something else.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeah that helps thanks all i was missing is that the os gives the 2 processes their fork return values thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"a bit confusion about failed system call in quiz 4 question 1 i tried that on my own machine. of course i don't have file 'xyz' neither access it as other user. it prints no such file or directory . my question is which expression prints out this error. it seems exit 1 made this happen also i still have question about memory management. one page size and one frame size are equal. why should we have to calculate off set won't one page be loaded exactly to the first address of one frame i know this seems a bit fall behind the lecture. but thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"which expression prints out this error. perror null prints the error message. it knows what to print based on the current value of the global variable errno which is set by any failing system call. why should we have to calculate off set because addresses can be anywhere at the start of a page at the end of a page somewhere in the middle of a page. virtual memory tells us which frame contains the address we asked for. the offset tells us whereabouts in the page the address is located.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"has quiz 4 closed i read the time wrong and assumed it was due at midnight.","answers":[{"text":"in the final exam ... i read the question wrong ... no second chance. fortunately this isn't the final exam so i extended the deadline to midnight.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i can t see my grades for recent labs and my mark for the last quiz","answers":[{"text":"ask your tutor about lab grades i'll be posting the marks for the quiz 3 later today. needs some fiddling.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am doing the lab06 and i am confused about the error in the terminal. so what wrong in here it said runtime error- illegal array pointer or other operation and stopped in main argc 2","answers":[{"text":"i don't know what your functions do exactly but i'd be very surprised if they returned a floating point number. your printf format string is now correct. think about what kind of values are being printed in each column and choose an appropriate format for each. hint most are strings","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"please help after 48 hours of debugging and 2 re-writes i am v frustrated i know that offsetting into a 2d array x y the offset is found by x number of columns y. now when offsetting into the bigstring array should we be using the number of columns as nscols or biglength. running my code through qtspim i notice that if we use nscols then on many of the loops the offset goes from for e.g. 0-9 and then 9000 or 1000 depending on whatever nscols is where as if i were to use number of columns as biglength then it goes from 0-9 to 10 which seems more natural and correct atm my code compiles and runs but it's just printing what i assume to be bunch of blank spaces as the curser flips about rapidly for a short while and then then the program terminates in success though not failure . any assistance to the above question or the nature of my output would be greatly appreciated.","answers":[{"text":"the length in bytes of a row in bigstring is 9 1 100. 9 because each bigchar is a 9x9 array 1 for the single column after each bigchar 100 because there is space for 100 bigchars in bigstring nscols is an unfortunate choice of name. it is actually a count of the total bytes in bigstring","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so changing nscols to 1000 is the way to go","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"probably not. that may have other consequences. easiest to just use the constant 1000 is computing byte offsets within bigstring. or if you don't want people accusing you of using magic numbers define a new constant give it a sensible name and use that.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you won't need to change it unless there is a specific issue which you shouldn't encounter.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the maximum columns in bigstring is nscols since bigstring nrows nscols . nscols isn't used as a point of comparison for loops rows lt nscols but ndcols is. clear your head a bit and make sure you're not mixing the 2. seems like your registers are being changed so make sure they are holding the values you expect them to. your output issue would be dependent upon the validity of your arrays so that may be causing issues there.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i keep getting this error in qtspim instruction references undefined symbol at 0x00400014 0x00400014 0x0c000000 jal 0x00000000 main 188 jal main edit yep ok","answers":[{"text":"this is the default address of main until a file containing main is loaded into qtspim. load your exe.s file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you are loading your file into qtspim right","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i try to run my code it become a full white board like this. what's wrong thx","answers":[{"text":"your arrays could be empty so printing our ' '. or the delay function is taking forever to show something so comment that out for now. if the arrays are not containing the expect character value make sure your formulas are correct and registers are holding their expected value.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if i use t0 to represent the address of an array and store a value into the array can i use t0 later to represent something else change it to other meanings","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"presuming that $t0 is not used in that loop then sure. make sure you remember temporary registers can be changed after a function is called.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi may i know what does this means tt","answers":[{"text":"something goes wrong when the program counter is at 0x00400364. go into qtspim and check what happens in that area. from a guess it has something to do with bigstring row col ' '. but common issues seem to be checking your array offset formulas are correct checking your registers are holding the correct values or something else. so could be going out of the bigstring array.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is it right to run the code such '1521 spim -file exe.s hello world' when i try to run that way it becomes like below and it cannot stop","answers":[{"text":"use this instead 1521 spim -file exe.s hello world with quotes currently your program is ignoring 'world' so this error hasn't got anything to do with having multiple words. the error you have is because you are trying to access a word int without 4 byte alignment. look at any loops you have that access arrays of ints. or any arrays of chars that are accessed with lw instead of the correct lb.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"why should there is lt gwmw class ginger-module-highlighter-mistake-anim ginger-module-highlighter-mistake-type-1 id gwmw-15357847692412475371398 gt lb lt /gwmw gt since and ' ' are all values","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"because chars are only one byte in size. while lw moves 4 bytes and that causes alignment errors.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i have checked all the place that i use lw . it is only used when i get the value from hash define. there is still exception5 error when i try to run the code","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"which hash define you having issues with","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry there is no problem with hash define. it just runs exception5 error infinitely. address error in store dylan says 'look at any loops you have that access arrays of ints. or any arrays of chars that are accessed with lw instead of the correct lb.' but i have checked there is no problem","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i personally find the lt gwmw ... impossible to read. presuming it is a lw/lb issue are you using lw when appropriate for your global variables/ defines so lw $t0 nrows. otherwise i can't understand your problem sorry.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how do i pass a string with more than one word in qtspim running 1521 spim -file exe.s two words works fine in the terminal but when i try to pass two words into the run parameters in qtspim it gives me the only letters and spaces are allowed in the string error. is there something wrong on my end or is there something different i have to do within qtspim","answers":[{"text":"what machine are you running qtspim on does it work for just one word","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes it works with one word but not one word in quotation marks so it works for hello but not hello or hello world . i'm running it through vlab on my mac.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if it works for two words in the terminal that's fine. we won't be testing your code in qtspim.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"further on this point i can run my program fine in a terminal but there seems to be a bug when i have a space in the input like below ./scroll.s why not as qtspim or mars don't support an input like above it makes it extremely difficult to debug the issue using only the terminal. is there any other approaches i can take to try and fix this below is an example ignore the extra -'s they are there for troubleshooting. of what i am trying to resolve. thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i told you in lectures that you can get around the qtspim problem by defining a constant string and using that instead of getting the string from argv 1 . you'll need to tweak your main program a bit to accomplish this but at least you can debug. note that spim itself has some crude debugging ... run spim without any args and type help","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was trying to use $s8 but always get this error when clean the stack. i'm really confused about how to fix it.","answers":[{"text":"here's where it gets weird ... there technically is a s8 register and it's the same as the fp register. if you don't use the fp register at all you get a free save register in practice it's not done often.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi the save-registers go from $s0 to $s7. you'll need to use a different register name. check the spim instruction set summary here https //webcms3.cse.unsw.edu.au/comp1521/18s2/reso...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"https //cgi.cse.unsw.edu.au/ cs1521/18s2/docs/spim.php","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"save registers only go from 0-7 so $s9 does not exist as a register name","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi. whenever i try to run spim on vlab i always get the message bash spim command not found how can i fix this","answers":[{"text":"try the command 1521 spim ...","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in the assignment 1 template i got global variable is given the value 9000 to hold with a description that it's the number of columns in bigstring matrix with the equation nrows maxchars chrsize 1 but wouldn't give this the total bytes for bigstring the max chars atm is 100 meaning 100 letters can be printed. chrsize is the width and height of a bigletter which is 9. each bigletter also gets 1 column of spacing meaning that the total number of columns in bigstring should be maxchars chrsize 1 100 9 1 1000 why did nrows get put in there too also bigstring is given 81000 bytes because it's nrows nscols.","answers":[{"text":"each column has 9 nrows rows. you're right that nscols isn't necessary but since it gave more than enough memory we left it unchanged.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are we supposed to be able to have multiple attempts at quiz 4 like the other quizzes i can't change my answers after submission.","answers":[{"text":"i forgot to check a box. now you should be able to resubmit.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"should we submit the file with comment delay function's file or not. if we submit the file with the delay function should we set a suitable display speed","answers":[{"text":"leave the delay function in place. we don't care what speed you set it to.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm a bit confused about align. i always get error 'unaligned address'. i know that i should align with 4 but in the string every element only take one byte. so for alignment i still need to time 4 when i calculate the address in a string","answers":[{"text":"if you use lw rather than lb to try and load a char from memory that would cause your error.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh yeah. i got it thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how can i pass in arguments using qtspim when i type qtspim -file exe.s hello it said cannot open file hello . also if i type spim -file exe.s hello it shows this write to unused memory-mapped io address 0xffffffffc what does this mean thanks for any help","answers":[{"text":"for unused memory-mapped io address 0xffffffffc have a look at your stack frame set ups and tear downs. qtspim is opened with qtspim file... ie. just a list of file names to set arguments go to 'simulator gt run parameters' then to the send box.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi regarding to the ass1 code where does this $t1 come from in the code provided i believe you want this register as ch but isn't ch stored in $s2 but $t1 can you please have a look at it thank you very much","answers":[{"text":"do you have the right version of scroll.s i just checked version in assign1.zip and it correctly has sb $t1 $t0 for that line.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh yes i have the wrong version.i have changed it back. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello in show_display function where is the first element display 0 0 stored thanks.","answers":[{"text":"the display array is stored in the .data section and must be loaded with 'la $t display'.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can i drop 1521 and still get my fee back now...","answers":[{"text":"census date is friday. so yes but please talk to your tutor about why.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi for the./scroll if you do hello amp it will not show hello amp . but for the exe.s it will show hello no amp . also if do hello hello it will not show for ./scroll but for exe.s it will show hello ... why","answers":[{"text":"scroll only shows a sentence if the whole sentence can be displayed. only uppercase and lowercase letters and spaces can be displayed so hello amp should not display anything. './scroll hello hello ' and '1521 spim exe.s hello hello ' should both print hello hello","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there a way to run scroll.s without using qtspim i'd like to see what the code actually prints in the real console window but i don't know how to pass arguments when using spim","answers":[{"text":"on a cse terminal the command is 1521 spim -file exe.s hello world","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank so much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas just wondering where the youtube lecture videos for week 5 are thanks","answers":[{"text":"there won't be any until i'm in a position to copy the echo360 videos across .. maybe tonight but maybe not until sunday.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"which of course means they're available on echo360 right now","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i couldn't submit the files by using the given give command and there is no matrix.h files in ex2.","answers":[{"text":"matrix.h isn't mentioned in the output you supplied where did you get the idea that it was relevant","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how to enable syntax highlighting in vi/vim like lecturer. for mips","answers":[{"text":"i do it via syntax on in my /.vimrc","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is there a way to enable syntax colouring for gedit i found some ways to do it but need access to the config files to add in the package and obviously that can't happen.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"on a cse computer run jashankj/bin/install-spim-style courtesy of jashank jeremy.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how to finish the main function and return 0 to imply that the program is successfully finished or executed. because for the fac2.s i have computed n correctly but the problem is when the code gets to jr $ra after this instruction it goes back to the line where the function fac is being called and it keeps doing this forever how to fix that i hope that what i have written explains the problem. thanks","answers":[{"text":"which jump method did you use to get to fac j or jal","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"are you printing out n forever or is it just not terminating","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"my lab marks are still not appearing when webcms tries to fetch them. i don't understand why this is happening i really want to view my lab marks over the course of this semester.","answers":[{"text":"you don't get marks. you get grades. i just checked the sms database where the grades are actually stored and there are no grades although it does note that you submitted something webcms3 also tells you this . have you asked your tutor when they plan to enter them","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you i will ask them dr shepherd","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the lecture example with the grades today we did .data for allocating mark and grade space but we didn't .text before the code part is that just forgetting or was there a reason to not put .text cheers.","answers":[{"text":"i just forgot. there should always be .text to introduce the code.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will lab exercises ever have answers as an example code solution","answers":[{"text":"i would like to know as well","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"usually not we haven t given solutions in the past.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"why is this so if someone had trouble with one of the exercises it would beneficial to see the answers and examples. without seeing the answers after the cut off time has passed the opportunity to learn will be reduced.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"while you wait for an official answer to why it s not posted i could suggest other ways of learning. you all should be working in pairs so it s highly unlikely that both of you don t know how to solve the lab. nevertheless feel free to collaborate with other groups group learning is encouraged. just don t blatantly copy code of course don t plagiarise. during marking in week x 1 ask your tutor how to do it. the tutor might not have time to explain the whole lab to you but they can at least try - especially when the lab is quiet. in my experience all the students were able to figure out how to do the labs. i haven t seen a student in my classes in previous years that never solved the labs. so don t stress i suspect it s not posted because jas is very busy. that was his answer to not releasing the quiz answer as well.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for your answer. i appreciate people may be busy but i don't really think that is an acceptable reason not to provide answers for these types of tasks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in previous subjects the recorded lectures were uploaded to echo where they could be downloaded and viewed offline. this cannot be done easily with youtube without either paying for a program to do this or putting our trust in a website to convert for us without adding anything malcious. can these lectures also be uploaded to echo thanks","answers":[{"text":"fyi youtube-dl is a open source command line utility that can grab videos from everywhere youtube included","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"afaik all of the lectures are uploaded to echo. there's a link to them at the top of the lectures page.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks i can see them there also.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will videos for week 3 wednesday's lectures be released","answers":[{"text":"yes ... they will ... well-spotted ... i thought i'd done them and actually removed them from my laptop ... fortunately they're on a backup drive in my office ... i'll do them on monday morning when i'm next at work.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"will these still be uploaded today i can't see them on echo or webcms.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"done","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i can see them now.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do i get cisco anyconnect and vnc lab on my home computer","answers":[{"text":"i'd try typing download anyconnect and download tigervnc into google.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i tried that but cisco keeps asking for money","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's also described in some of the cselearning videos windows or mac","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if you go to the cse's taggi page it gives you some links to download tigervnc and a login portal to get cisco anyconnect","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the licence for you use anyconnect is paid for by the organisation that installed the cisco firewalls the vpn terminates on i.e. unsw. so in this case there is no need for you to pay to use or download anyconnect. go to https //vpn.unsw.edu.au using your browser and after you authenticate the firewall will automatically attempt to install anyconnect on your computer to allow you to create a vpn tunnel to the device. that being said if you're using linux you may already have an cisco compatible vpn client on your machine. i have been able to connect to the vpn using the built vpn client on fedora 27 without using anyconnect.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i completed quiz 2 on week02 but i cant see my grades for that quiz","answers":[{"text":"i forgot to export them from webcms3 to sms. i just did that. they should appear tomorrow. if not remind me.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i don't know why this prints size 20 bytes instead of 24 bytes. if it should be multiple of all the elements in the union it should print 24 because one double is 8 bytes. someone can explain it for me please","answers":[{"text":"in this discussion there seems to be some confusion between alignment and size alignment is where the object starts in memory i.e. its address size is how many bytes it occupies after its starting address. the size was always going to be close to 19 which is the size of the largest element in the union. the precise size probably depends on the c compiler. rounding it up the next multiple of 4 above 19 i.e. 20 would be plausible. some other compilers might round it up to the next multiple of 8 if it needed to be aligned for the most restricted-alignment component in the union which would be 8 because of the double . if you had an array of these unions that would be a plausible scenario. but this assumes that a double is 8 bytes. is this guaranteed in any event these kinds of considerations point out that trying to analyse things at a level close to the machine leads to revealing machine and compiler dependencies.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"a union takes the size of its largest member. i compiled your code character for character and got size was 24 although i had to use lu . you might have forgotten to compiled or saved then compiled so updating your file otherwise i am not sure.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"uh... the size should have been 20. and when i compile it it gives me 20. remember that the size of the union will be the largest of its members. this is because it only stores enough space for only one element the largest one . one way to think of it is that the address of name is the same as the address of x which is the same as the address of i. in this case the largest element is the array which is 19 characters long. however the size of the union is not 19 bytes because it adds a byte at the end to keep it 4 bytes aligned.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"why should it be multiple of 4 bytes is it because every computer is aligned like that in terms of union memory allocation i read somewhere that the size of union should be multiple of every element and at least the largest of the element the 2 conditions must be satisfied. and a double is 8 bytes.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i think you miss understood what you read on the internet. it s not multiple but alignment. integers are 4 byte aligned hence since it is part of the union - the union is 4 byte aligned. this is not strictly necessarily but some compilers - such as gcc - do this alignment. why didn t it align to a double. tbh i m not sure. if i had to take a guess it would be that since cpu registers are 32bits in a 32bit computer then accessing a double is a two instruction operation anyway.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"registers have been mentioned a lot so far during lectures. do we need to know what they are or just that computers use them to do things","answers":[{"text":"if your question is do we need to understand the electronics behind their construction then the answer is no. for this course you can treat them like 32-bit memory cells with names like $s0 etc. you can only perform operations on values that are loaded in registers so they're very important when describing computations at the machine level.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"that makes a lot of sense thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is this error message about","answers":[{"text":"are you compiling yourself or running make it can't find the main function. does your add.c file definitely have a main function at the top with no typos did add.c actually compile","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am not sure how to use spim like dr shepherd does from the terminal . do i have to install anything other than spim beforehand because i keep getting bash spim command not found .","answers":[{"text":"yes. you need to install spim . if that turns out to be too difficult use qtspim on your local machine or use vlab then spim .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i log out at unsw computer successfully but when i went home and try to open it via vlab on my laptop it tells me that i have exceeded my disk quota in my home directory and only left a terminal to me. what should i do","answers":[{"text":"i use the du command to work this out du d isk u sage . start at your home directory and type du -s then cd into the directory with the largest disk usage and repeat. keep descending the directory tree until you find a directory with a very large file. remove the offending file. voila or if you're not old school and if you have a window manager use the cute gui that's mentioned in the taggi.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you it did help me","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"https //taggi.cse.unsw.edu.au/faq/disk_quota/","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"exceeded disk quota means the total size of files you have on your drive is higher than the allowed limit. i think the command to check is rquota or something like that. look for big files to delete. a few students in week 1 generated very big output files in the lab by accident when doing the printing to files sometimes thats the cause.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"a couple that we've used as texts in the past the indispensable guide to c by davies programming problem-solving and abstraction by moffat the c programming language by kernighan and ritchie","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"regarding help session on tuesdays and wednesdays should we bring our own device to law 210 amp 202","answers":[{"text":"https //www.learningenvironments.unsw.edu.au/space... as you can see there are no computers in law so i would say definitely bring your own devices.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will the answers to the quizzes ever be posted thanks.","answers":[{"text":"maybe ... if i ever get some free time ...","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do i get in touch with my tutor if i don't have his email i want to send him some code to ask him for some assistance but i forgot to ask him his email in the introductory tutorial. could the course admins or tutors somehow help me get in touch with him","answers":[{"text":"look on the timetable. find you class. click on your tutor's name and there might be an option to send them email.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can i get lecture notes weeks 3 all in one file beforehand its easier for me to print out and jot down while lecture is held","answers":[{"text":"that requires me to write them all beforehand which is proving impossible at the moment.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"program simply gives 'segmentation fault' when attempting to run. used make add with no errors or warnings and i am unable to see where illegal memory was accessed... code deleted by jas","answers":[{"text":"ellen is right. the gdb debugger is useful to sort out segfaults. alternatively re-compile the code with dcc which does a lot of extra checking and might give an error message that helps you to debug.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi dean to find the location of the segfault you could try running the code with gdb to debug or you could try using printf statements in various places in your code to give you a clue where the program is getting up to and what function it is breaking in. then try to print the specific variable values at that part of the program and see if they are what you expect them to be. some things to consider when we declare a local variable the memory is uninitialised. if we don't assign it it could have any value possibly quite large inside. segfaults very commonly occur in arrays when we are iterating over them and access an area out of bounds. think about how this relates to point 1. it's best if you don't post actual lab code on the forum test output is fine but not code files but you can either take it to a help session or ask your tutor if you need some help debugging.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"my program makes this wired symbel when it reaches a new digit. i have realloc the array but doesnt work. thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"you might be picking up garbage from beyond the end of the array try re-compiling with dcc . or ... learn to use gdb or some other debugger","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"or you might have generated a weird character and stored it in the array ...","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm a bit confused about bonus mark. for challenge question can i get full mark if i do not do challenge and if i get a for every lab can i get full mark finally thank you","answers":[{"text":"if you get a for every lab you'll definitely get 10/10 for the labs. you may even get a small bonus because we allow for students to possibly miss one lab during the semester. any a marks give you an a towards your 10/10 plus an extra addition to the bonus lab mark.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"okay. i got it thank you","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it was indicated on the lab page as how i understood it a grade full marks a full marks bonus marks. so if u do well in the normal exercises getting a's and not do the challenges you'll still end up with full marks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are we supposed to modify add.c so that is disregards non-integer arguments there is no specification for this in the lab instructions but i cannot think of another reason why test 5 is failing. regards harold","answers":[{"text":"i only modified the bignum.c file to let it disregard any leading non-digit characters in the string. pretty sure you can do it without changing the add.c file.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"my bignum.c worked pretty well when i tested it manually but when i tested it using cs1521/bin/check add command it gave me these fails i'm really confused now is there something wrong with my program or have i done any other mistakes thanks","answers":[{"text":"have a look at the .out files in the test folder and run the diff commands - it will give you some more info about what's going wrong in the tests.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh jokes i forgot to compile it to add instead i just used the a.out so it didn't recognize it in the auto testing. thanks a lot.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"why we change int to item i know it is convenient to change struct to stack but changing int seems meaningless and when should i use the int and when to use item","answers":[{"text":"if i wanted to define a stack of chars all i'd need to do is change to typedef char item and the rest of the code would remain unchanged. admittedly the whole notion of generic types is a bit lame in c.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"similar with define","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what would be another way to determine the end of an integer array when we define an integer array whatever by malloc or simply declaration. we would know its size. hence we could loop through the array by index. but array of integer doesn't have ' 0' in its end. hence what could be another way to determine the case of terminating the loop. for example here i would like to fill in an array with 9. this for loop runs much more times than 10 and trigged seg fault at last. it seems p null is not the case that p reaches end of x. what could be the correct way to exit instead of the way in comment thank you","answers":[{"text":"c doesn't have an inbuilt way of getting the size of an int array you would usually store the size of the array and use that the way you did it the first time . edit the second way doesn't work because you are checking the pointer value p is not null rather than the value at x 9 which would be gotten with p. you can generally set a guard at the end of an array that tells it when to stop. this is how strings work with '/0'. in your example you are trying to use a similar technique with an int array - but you will have to manually set the guard value at the end of the array. null is a pointer value so you won't be able to set an int to null. another way is to calculate the final address in the array and use that to terminate the loop. you would have seen an example of that in lectures or tutes. but that's basically the same as using array indexes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i keep getting this error while trying to compile. what's going on and how can i fix it","answers":[{"text":"put the int i declaration before the for loop eg. int i for i 0 ............ the version of c you are compiling with doesn't allow declarations inside the loop conditions.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the error message tells you exactly what's wrong and even tells you how to fix it. modify your makefile and add -std c99 to the cflags line. or define the loop variable outside the loop. before the exam you need to learn how to read and act on error messages from the c compiler.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"regarding the recommended book computer systems programmer's perspective this course is not about all of the book contents from the course outline. then which chapters would you suggest i read","answers":[{"text":"it's not which chapters it's which sections of chapters which should be obvious from the topics in lectures e.g. tuesday's lecture included unicode ... look up unicode in the index and go to the relevant chapter . don't expect the material to be explained anything like i do in lectures. it gives an alternative view. the one topics you'll find nothing on in the book is mips architecture and assembler. but there's plenty of material attached to the web site for mips.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello what is the procedure if i am too unwell to attend a lab/tute i can do the work from home but my lab partner would be alone and i'd miss out on any participation marks. i can msg my partner with shared solutions but is there something i can do to not lose that participation","answers":[{"text":"there isn't any mark for participation if that means a mark simply for being at the lab . messaging your partner and working on the solution that way is participation enough.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the reply","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there a way to download all the lecture slides at once would like to annotate it and have all the slides in one file","answers":[{"text":"i've added a link for this under the week 01 lectures. it's html but you can always save as pdf if that's what you want.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes that is what i wanted thank you do you mind adding it for all the upcoming lectures","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"where can i see the timetable for help labs or consultations","answers":[{"text":"on the menu bar there is a help sessions tab with the timetable","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'd forgotten to put my consults on the web site. i just added the times/locations on the timetable page. maybe that's why nobody had been coming along ...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello when i try to log in using vlab i get this error. server disconnected code 1006 i've asked other people to try logging in and its working fine for them. what can i do to fix this thanks","answers":[{"text":"it looks like you're using vlabgateway. you shouldn't be vlabgateway is not well supported. instead you should follow the instructions on taggi to set up vlab locally. you'll need both software capable of talking to the unsw vpn -- either cisco anyconnect or openconnect -- and a vnc viewer like tigervnc.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh and i forgot to add i was using cisco anyconnect amp tigervnc before this happened. i was completing the wk1 lab exercise. it was when i compiled for cat3.c everything kinda froze so i closed my tigervnc. upon reopening tigervnc and trying to login i couldnt log in anymore. so i decided to try vlabgateway which also didnt work giving me the error server disconnected .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it sounds to me like you've blown a quota or otherwise made something unhappy. either way say hi to one of the friendly staff in any of the 1521 labs or in a lecture break","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh crap i completly forgot to mention that that's exactly what happened. prior to getting this error it said i had went over my quota. i proceeded to delete the files that were taking up space using the 'rm' command and then after that i was able to log in like usual. but then after doing something i guess wrong while coding everything froze and then i closed vnc and reopened it only to see it not letting me log in. yep i will thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"have you tried rebooting your laptop","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep i have","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hard to tell without seeing your entire setup. can you bring your laptop to a consultation","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"unfortunately all the help sessions for this week are clashing with my lab sessions for other courses. i dont think i'll be able to go to a help session until next week so at this rate i won't be able to do lab2 as well what can i do","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what about my consultation wed 11-12 or after the lecture and why can't you do the lab exercise in the lab","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i have a tutorial during that time. oh yes i will see you after the lecture then. i just assumed that if it didn't let me log in at home then it wouldn't let me log in at the lab either.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you could just use a lab workstation ...","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i clearly remember making a submission of week 1 lab exercises yet on webcms it says that there is no record of the submission","answers":[{"text":"the monday 11am submissions ended up in the wrong place on the system. once i move them to where they're supposed to be later today your submission will show up. in the meantime demo to your tutor using the files in your directory.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how many attempts do we get at the weekly quiz","answers":[{"text":"if understand the meaning of the allow multiple attempts button in webcms3 it should be as many as you want before the deadline . if that's not the case let me know.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i clicked on submit and it says you submitted a response to the quiz thanks . it doesn't say how many i got correct or incorrect but i can change my answers and then click on submit again upon which it saves my newly chosen answers. so i assume we are allowed to make multiple attempts but we aren't told if the answer is correct or not after each attempt.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"correct.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm just wondering where exactly we do the weekly blog","answers":[{"text":"via the little speech bubble at the bottom of the webcms3 menu ... next to your name and next to the little graph icon that lets you check your marks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are the blogs that we are meant to maintain private","answers":[{"text":"i can read them. the tutors can read them. other students are not supposed to able to read them. can you read other people's blogs","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"there's a dropdown at the bottom of a blog post in edit that lets us set privacy. i assume we want to set it to course staff","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"having just come from comp1511 i have not come across makefiles before so an explanation of these would be nice especially considering they seem to create even more file .o files . can this be discussed in the next lecture thanks","answers":[{"text":"ok ... i probably should have talked about them when i was talking about the c compilation pipeline.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how much of the course will cover c programming comp1511 was all about c programming. i am wondering how much proportion is about c in this course.","answers":[{"text":"thank you a lot for the replies.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i think the whole course is in c as well.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"apart from the part that deals with mips assembler around 3-4 weeks .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will we be assessed on theory in this course if so how much of it","answers":[{"text":"there will be a final exam which tests your theory. i can't say how much but i can say that past students found it reasonable and fair.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"past exams have been 50 50 programming theory. i don't see any reason to change that.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello may i change my answer to the quiz questions before the due date of the quiz","answers":[{"text":"i think so. i set the allow re-submissions flag on the quiz page but since i'm not a student i can't test whether it's working.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do we access the files to the code presented in the lecture","answers":[{"text":"they'll appear as a lecture exercises link on the lectures page as soon as i get a chance to upload them.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"where do we put our blogs can i just have my weekly thoughts in a notepad doc and give it to my tutor at the end of the semester for that glorious bonus mark","answers":[{"text":"use the webcms3 blogs in the sidebar the speech bubble takes you to your course blog.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there gonna be solutions for tutorials thanks","answers":[{"text":"tutorial solutions are typically released the following week.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"where can we find the timetable of web stream lecture","answers":[{"text":"web stream lectures are just videos of the live lectures. the videos will be uploaded to youtube a couple of hours after the live lecture finishes.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh i see thank you","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"where can i find a link to the lecture youtube channel","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"they are in the lecture tab.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"where can i find my quiz marks thanks","answers":[{"text":"after the quiz's due date is passed you'll get your quiz marks uploaded to your sturec. you can see the grades link down the bottom of the menu bar.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what am i generally expected to write in the cs1521 blog","answers":[{"text":"what you discover each week. mistakes you made. what you learned from them. how you will do better in the future.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in comp1511 we used edstem.org as a forum to post all our questions. is there one for comp1521","answers":[{"text":"you're using it now","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"typo i meant is there an edstem forum but i'll take your answer to mean no this is the forum","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"correct.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how long will it take for new lecture spots to open up in this course i was previously in the web lectures but i had to change my tutorial to a better day because of timing issues and now i lost my spot in the web lecture.","answers":[{"text":"sometime in week 1. spots will open when the people who failed comp1511 and comp1911 get dropped from the course. i've asked the student office when they're going to do that. i'll edit this message when i know the details.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so what do i do for week 1 then do i still go to a lab or do i have to wait until i can get a lecture spot","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"go to a lab. if there's room you can stay. if not try another. hopefully within a day or so some spots will open. i cannot open more spots. and the stupid way unsw organises enrolments means that all you can do is wait for someone to drop out.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the c programming questions can we implement our own helper functions and then call them in our answers can we also include any extra libraries if for whatever reason we decide to","answers":[{"text":"yes and yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm confused abut the part a of this tutorial question. why the answer is 2 instead of 99 1 page for the code and 98 pages for the big array the working set of a process could be defined as the set of pages being referenced by the process over a small window of time. this would naturally include the pages containing the code being executed and the pages holding the data being accessed by this code. consider the following code which computes the sum of all values in a very large array int bigarray 100000 ... int sum 0 for int i 0 i lt 100000 i sum bigarray i answer the questions below under the assumptions that pages are 4kb all of the above code fits in a single page the sum and i variables are implemented in registers there is just one process running in the system. how large is the working set of this piece of code","answers":[{"text":"from my understanding you just need 2 because when the os is managing each process you only ever need to see the code you're looking at 1 page and then 1 other page for the array part you're looking at. the whole thing with the working set model is that you don't or should not load all pages up because that is unnecessary since you only will look at each page in terms of the array section maybe once and if they are needed to be looked at again then they will be loaded up again. otherwise the remaining total pages in the 'whole system' could/would be allocated to other segments for other processes.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"correct. the two pages are the page containing the code for the for loop plus the page containing the section of the array that you're currently looking at.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"when talking about the valgrind memory leak is that detected from the physical memory or the virtual memory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"process memory","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i use check q1 on the sample exams 5 released for the prac exam they are all showing failed tests although i am sure the code is correct as they produce correct output if i manually insert input and crosscheck with output. is there a trick to running check","answers":[{"text":"are you sure it's not just the loading message at the start of the output alternatively trailing spaces or non-printing characters. are you cross-checking using your eyes easily deceived or using diff","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is the proper way to access asciiz array in mips","answers":[{"text":"it's just an array of bytes terminated by a 0 byte. if you want one of the bytes try lb .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"looking through the sample exams there are a few questions that ask us to write a code 'fragment'. the question doesn't say write a full program which would involve writing all required code in order to have a working executable. this implies to me we don't have to compile the code 'fragment' we submit as it won't be a complete program. that being the case is the code fragment expected to be syntactically perfect or is the aim of the question to demonstrate the programming logic required to achieve what the question asks without compiling the code fragment there is a high likelihood there will be atleast one or two small syntax errors i.e. missing bracket or semi-colon so i would like to understand is this particularly important or should we just be focusing on the programming logic in what we submit","answers":[{"text":"if it's not a prac question then i won't be expecting syntactic perfection.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how can we define the null terminator in the .data section of our mips code .data nterm .byte ' 0' the above throws an error - invalid syntax. please advice. are we explicitly supposed to check against char '0' or the number 0 when looking for the null terminator thanks","answers":[{"text":"just use the number 0 i.e. nterm .byte 0","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks jas","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm not too sure why the answer to q3 c i on the 2017s2 practice exam is 8bytes your answers say it's the size of the largest component all components share the same piece of memory i thought the size of a struct is the size of all of its components added together padding if the compiler doesnt re-arrange the fields","answers":[{"text":"it's not a struct . it's a union . big difference.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"/","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"curious about 17s2 q7 why there is a empty memory in the middle of the physical memory isn't physical memory filled up one after another","answers":[{"text":"the contents of physical memory evolves as processes come and go. process pages are allocated to whatever frames happen to be free at the time they're needed so they won't necessarily be allocated to consecutive frames in memory. this physical memory might have an empty frame because some process just finished and released it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i see thanks a lot","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"why in qn4b of the sample is c set to 0 i recall in the lectures something about it stopping once it sees the decimal and when i compiled and ran some code to test c was set to 1 i presume what was held in the memory beforehand . after some further testing c isn't being changed by the scanf at all. so only when i initialise c to 0 as below it still spits out c 0 include lt stdio.h gt int main void int n a b c c 0 n scanf d d d amp a amp b amp c printf n d na d nb d nc d n n a b c return 0","answers":[{"text":"it read 42 and assigns that to a. it reads 64 and assigns that to b. it stops at the '.' because that character is not a valid char to find in a decimal integer. when it tries to find a value for c it looks at the '.' and says hmmm. not an integer and gives up without changing c.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks - so to confirm the solutions where it says '0' for should be a ' ' instead since c is uninitialised https //cgi.cse.unsw.edu.au/ cs1521/18s2/exams/sample/soln/q4.soln.txt","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"in the code you posted c is initialised to 0","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but not in the actual question's code sorry upon rereading i realised my question wasn't particularly clear https //cgi.cse.unsw.edu.au/ cs1521/18s2/exams/sample/q04.html","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"in that case or undefined or garbage would be acceptable","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there a mistake in q6e from the practice paper - when i convert the 2's complement binary straight into octal i get 177634 confirmed with wolframalpha vs the 177632 which the answers suggest. or is there some technicality in this question which i'm overlooking","answers":[{"text":"no. it was wrong and i've fixed it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i have 2 questions about the answer of sample exam e. sigtstp - user types control-z in controlling terminal - suspend process for this one why the action is not stop the process i think in the man page the default action is stop e. -100_16 0xff9c -100_8 0177632 -100_2 1111 1111 1001 1100 and for this one i think the octal should be 0177634 by the way just to make sure we are allowed to use man page and writing a program to do the theorem questions right thank you","answers":[{"text":"depends what you mean by stop. in this context stop ping a process means halting execution but leaving the process active. the process can be restarted from the point it was stopped. i'd call this suspended . the man page calls it stopped . yes. 0177632 is a typo. i've changed it 0177634 and yes as i've said quite a few times you have access to the unix man pages during the exam.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"okay thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i have a question about q2 of the 17s2 exam. i'm confused as to why i'm having issues printing the point structure. my code reads as follows point temptl while read in temptl sizeof point 0 printf d d n temptl- gt coord- gt x temptl- gt coord- gt y my error messages reads q2.c 74 44 error invalid type argument of '- gt ' have 'coord' printf d d n temptl- gt coord- gt x temptl- gt coord- gt y from my understanding of the data structure this should be fine. could someone please tell me if i'm missing something","answers":[{"text":"whilst you've created temptl as a pointer temptl.coord is not a pointer so using - gt notation isn't valid to access the x and y values so instead of temptl- gt coord- gt x try temptl- gt coord .x and same for the y","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahhh thank you for that.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how are we meant to install the exe and check scripts please advice. thanks","answers":[{"text":"you don't need to. they're in cs1521/bin ... fix your path.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i would like to ask if the built-in function mergesort can be used in exam i found in the answer there is qsort . i used mergesort on 17s2 q3. however it doesn't compile on cse machine with make telling implicit declaration of mergesort . so is it ok to use built-in sorting function such as mergesort in exam thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"it's fine to use ant sorting function from the library. but as i said elsewhere i'd be disappointed if you couldn't produce a bubble sort yourself.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i can't figure out why my program for q1 in practice prac exams can't pass the test even it has the same output with the expected output. gt _ lt","answers":[{"text":"as jas has stated the expected output contains a line the loaded one which is filtered out of your output by check . feel free to change the expected output files and remove the loaded lines if you want the satisfaction of seeing test x passed . so in the expected file there is the line loaded /home/class/lib/exceptions . so neglecting that it looks like you have the correct output. could also delete that line from the expected files.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thx mate","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i was wondering where the 8 came from in the answers for q4bi 17s2 i 68 4 20 20 1 3 4 1 3 4 8 thanks liz.","answers":[{"text":"the major field was 6 bytes. need to round up to a multiple of 4.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i am still a little confused about this. i know from the lectures that character pointers can be any number so is this a principle of arrays structs or something else i.e. do we want the 68 to be a multiple of 4 or the 8 to be a multiple of 4 if for example the array was of size 2 characters would it be rounded up to 4 also is there a name for this principle so i can do some further reading thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's because we want the total size of the struct to be a multiple of 4. so that we can put structs one after another in memory without needing padding between them. character arrays can be any length you want. whether padding is needed after them depends on what kind of value is following or on whether it's the last field in the struct.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the questions in sample final exam refer to files is directories called q1 q2 etc. can someone tell me where these directories are","answers":[{"text":"they don't exist. however i think at least one of the questions was like one of the practice prac exam questions so you can use the files for them. you could always take the solution files remove the appropriate function then try to recreate what it did.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm not getting something about the bitwise operations on the i assume octal numbers here in q5 comp1521 17s2 final exam for example the solution for ii is given as o_wronly o_creat or 00000101 but when i try to replicate that in c with printf o_wronly o_creat is o n o_wronly o_creat i get o_wronly o_creat is 1001 how are the numbers in the solution generated","answers":[{"text":"how are the numbers in the solution generated i got them off a man page if i remember correctly. maybe some unix system defines the symbolic names differently. or maybe i copied them wrong. either way you should work with whatever values are given and answer relative to those. i was actually expecting symbolic answers rather than numeric. if you simply wrote 00001001 as your answer i would assume that you'd messed up the bitwise or and mark it wrong. if you want to write a program that gives you a different result say how you generated this result e.g. give your one-liner and if it's valid then i'd mark it as correct. note if i run your program on williams.cse.unsw.edu.au it gives 00000101","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what do you know the results on different systems must be different. ok that clears it up a bit i guess. i'll stick to symbolic answers if it comes up thanks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"though the answer given for i looks wrong no matter what. o_rdwr o_append or 00000102 looking at the given defines and also the output on weill is should definitely be 00002002.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"fixed. thanks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi for 2017 q7b why is there 8 page table entries and 5 page table entries contain loaded pages i noticed that there is an empty page in process address space why not 7 page table entires thanks.","answers":[{"text":"there are 8 page table entries for the process' address space. and there are 5 memory frames in the physical memory. only 7 of the pages in the process' address space are currently in use. the other page might eventually have stuff put into it if e.g. enough objects are created with malloc.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but why not 6 memory frames in the physical memory including the empty one","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the number of memory frames is determined by the size of physical memory. it has no correlation with the size of any process address space.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"dr. shepherd i am working on these questions at home using vlab. how am i able to install the exam files files.tar into vlab if i try to access the download page in vlab it will just give me error. thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"i don't know why you all seem to think there's something magical about the vlab environment. it just gives you a virtual screen which is equivalent to sitting on a cse workstation and doing things. what kind of error does the download page give and how are you trying to access it","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i do not know what is happening here. i just clicked on the files.tar icon on the cs1521 page","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"this is a browser problem rather than a vlab problem. an easy way to get the exam.tar file would be to run the command cp cs1521/web/18s2/exams/17s2final/files/exam.tar . or even better make a directory where you want to work on the exam change into that directory and then run the command tar xf cs1521/web/18s2/exams/17s2final/files/exam.tar and it will put all of the relevant files in your directory.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you so much dr. shepherd","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for q4 a i in 2017 sample exam 00000000000000000000000000101010 flip digits- gt 11111111 11111111 11111111 11010101 add 1- gt 11111111 11111111 11111111 11010110 which is a huge number instead of 42 in the solution. what is wrong with my calculation thank you.","answers":[{"text":"you misread the question. what i wanted was for you interpret the bit-string as a number x in twos-complement format. what you've done is negate the number and given -x. i was asking you tell me what x was.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi in the 2017 sample exam q6d. write a recursive function to free the memory associated with a list i.e. free all of the node s . use the following function header void freenodes node l ... the solution is void freenodes node l if l null freenodes l- gt next free l i don't quite understand how it is recursive. isn't it just freeing l and l- gt next what if there exists l- gt next- gt next thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's recursive because it calls itself as long as the list isn't empty which happens when the recursion winds its way to the end of the list . comp1521 doesn't cover recursion much or linked lists but comp1511 does afaik.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for 2017 sample q6 converting 100 in decimal to octal. why answer is 0144 rather than 144 also for all other answers in this question there are all one 0 in the left most digit and for question7 b why the answer could be 0 isn't like lb loads bits from lower to higher up to 8 bits so that 1001 1010 can only be loaded thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"0144 is to make the point that it's octal since a leading-0 is how you indicate octal in c on some architectures it could be zero. of course we're dealing with mips and so it can't. i assume that you wrote a small mips program to check.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"got the idea of 0 for signed octal.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are solutions for this going to be released","answers":[{"text":"they're now there ... follow the solutions link","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"only after you've attempted the questions.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i've completed exam1 q1. the rmm0d function is running correctly i think however there seems to be a quirk in the output. i get the correct answer however the output differs to the expected output. this happens in all .cmp. does anyone know the reason why this would occur i'm running exe arrays.s to create the files. i'm doing this while ssh'd into the cse machines. i've tried to use the re-start q1 command as suggested in the spec however i don't think re-start exists in the default or /home/cs1521/bin path anymore. tl dr is this a bug in my code or a bug in the system","answers":[{"text":"yes. the expected output contains a line the loaded one which is filtered out of your output by check . feel free to change the expected output files and remove the loaded lines if you want the satisfaction of seeing test x passed .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the exam spec front sheet says that calculator apps are available do you know which ones exactly i can use or more specifically will gnome-calculator be available","answers":[{"text":"xcalc and bc","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i don't understand how could i install the script of check and exe to verify my answer of 17s2 exam should i use chmod 755 or what","answers":[{"text":"that would certainly help. and you could always run them as sh check or sh exe if you copy the scripts into the directory where you're working.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how to install these files into vlab","answers":[{"text":"which files specifically","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can't use check is there any other way to check program","answers":[{"text":"run the tests by hand look at the tests/ .sh files . compare your output against the tests/ .exp or whatever they're called files. in other words look in the tests/ directory and work it out from there.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"q18 not sure about the answers here. anyone care to explain please","answers":[{"text":"it's just showing how a given set of bits can be interpreted in many ways","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey jas i think the -2 marks penalty for being sloppy about the printing might be too harsh and unfair. mainly because i had students whose code had one features working attempted two others and got more marks .... than those who attempted 3 features successfully but had a printing error. i reckon it is better if we deduct -1 for a serious error like printing the dash line before the running program ... and -0.5 for spelling errors like return 0 instead of returns 0 .","answers":[{"text":"how about reducing the penalty as you suggested but have a hard cap of 7/9 for code with formatting errors","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i've been interpreting if some tests really fail and if they have formatting errors on the rest work out their mark without formatting errors and if it's more then 7/9 set the mark to 7/9 with a comment about the formatting. as essentially that","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh i understand that sentence now. i m glad i brought it up. thanks oliver","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeah i second that.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"binary files tests/6.exp and tests/6.out differ how do i get and open the file","answers":[{"text":"since tests/6.exp is not a binary file then i assume that your program is producing a binary file. you can read what's in tests/6.exp simply by cat 'ing it. if you want to see what's in tests/6.out try the command od -c tests/6.out this sounds like something to take to a help session or ask your tutor in the lab.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"quiz 2 q4 isn't the answer to it none of these answers are correct since there are syntax errors and the code doesnt comply","answers":[{"text":"what syntax error did you get","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"wait nvm do we assume we run the code with header files and a main program","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes you can assume that the code needs to be put inside a main function.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi dr. shepherd how are you this is raymond again may i know what segmentation error means thank you. raymond setiawan soedargo","answers":[{"text":"it means you've dereferenced a pointer variable which contains a value which is not a valid address. e.g. int p 3 p 42 will generate a segmentation error. try also this explanation on quora .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"allright thank you dr. shepherd","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there can anyone help me with void addbignums bignum n bignum m bignum res function in week 2 lab why does some of the functions shows n while some shows n what are the difference i understand n means it is a pointer to where the memory is located while n means the actual address of the memory is this correct when do i use n and when do i use n thank you. regards raymond","answers":[{"text":"n means that the parameter value being passed is a pointer to a bignum structure. n means that the parameter value being passed is an actual bignum object. you use no star if you simply want to supply a value to a function this is analogous to regular function arguments in maths . you use a star if you want to pass in a pointer to an object in the caller and the intention of the function is to change the thing being pointed to. think about scanf d amp x . the intention is to change the value of x so we need to pass a pointer to x to the scanf function. all of this might become clearer when we see how functions are implemented in mips.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi dr. shepherd allright i will take a look again at the function. thank you regards raymond setiawan soedargo","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm not sure why but my code fails the autotest but if i do the tests manually going through the .sh files and applying the commands there i pass them. can someone tell me why this is happening","answers":[{"text":"i know with the fifth test ./add 20 300 it is actually ./add 020 300 with a couple of spaces. so something like ./add 020 300 i think you had to trim the white space i'm not too sure why you would be failing tests 1 and 2. it could be perhaps you are printing an extra space at the end of the line you have to make sure they are exactly the same. use the diff command to tell you what is different. so go into your tests folder and do diff 1.exp 1.out and it will tell you what is different. if diff does not print anything to stdout then it means they are exactly the same.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"unfortunately doing diff doesn't really say much for me as shown but i did find a bug when adding 020 and 300 together so i'm going to assume the same about printing white spaces or something to do with that. thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hmmm... i'm pretty sure it isn't meant to be a binary file. can you check something run cat tests/1.out then run cat tests/3.out and see what happens. i'd be interested to see if it prints the contents of 3.out","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"may i ask how do you go about the showbignum function in your printf line are you using c or d","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"c in a for loop that ends when it reaches ' 0' i fixed the issue it was white trailing space but i'm failing the 5th test so i just need to fix it up. thanks for your help","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"woohoo good luck","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi stella have a look at the .exp files expected output of test 3 and 4 and how they might be different to the rest of the tests. you might see a pattern there that helps you.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"did you check the differences between expected and observed output and without seeing your code or having more info on the output your program is producing nobody will be able to tell you why.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i couldn't check observed output but i got some ideas to check if i'm printing white spaces or not so i'll try that first.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the file tests/2.out is not a folder. it's a file. can you open it as a file","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am having trouble copying the chars in the string provided from stdin to the array in the bignum struct. i have tried simple assignment strncpy and even atoi but keep getting compile errors. here are some high level examples of which i have tried various different versions n- gt bytes j atoi s i n- gt bytes j s i strncpy n- gt bytes s j 1 strncpy n- gt bytes i s j 1 can anyone provide any advice","answers":[{"text":"are you talking about the scanbignum function i think with strncpy the third parameter should not be 1 if you look at the man page the third parameter should be the size of the string which you can get by strlen s also when scanning in you have to reverse the numbers 123 should stored as 321 it makes the addition part way easier. i basically used a for loop which is simple when you have the length of the string then in the loop i did n- gt bytes i s insert expression here to reverse i hope this helps if not keep asking questions.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks alex yes referring to scanbignum. i was using 1 with strncpy as i was wanting to use it to copy just a single char from the string and then place that into the appropriate element in the n- gt bytes string tha being in the reverse order. however i am not sure if it can be used that way and it needs to copy the entire string. i had initially used n- gt bytes j s i format but was getting illegal array pointer or other operation errors at runtime. so found no reason to use strncpy nor had similiar runtime errors thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"strncpy can be used the copy a single char but probably won't help because it will set the next char in the array to ' 0' which will wipe out anything you'd put there earlier. n- gt bytes i ch would be the way to do it assuming that your array was set up properly and it sounds like your isn't.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks john i will investigate further.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"nevermind. found the issue.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"maybe just type in make not necessarily make bignum","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i keep getting the following assert failure but my function works otherwise. i know that means it doesn't really work but the 'intlistok' function isn't really documented and i don't see how it's causing my function to fail. assertion failed intlistok myotherlist function main file useintlist.c line 25. does anybody know roughly what that assert is testing because my function produces a list in order of all the numbers input into the program. thanks","answers":[{"text":"is this in relation to lab 02 i don t see this assert in the main function of add.c. i have a feeling you posted in the wrong course... did you mean to post in cs2521","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh my god yes sorry wrong course.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i gotta an error message like this and the only test i couldn't pass is the tests 9 . when i printed out my result at my own laptop the result is exactly same as the one supposed to be. why would it getting size error but the printing results are same any help would be much appreciated.","answers":[{"text":"programs with errors behave in unpredictable ways depending on what happens in the underlying system. this is going to be a recurring theme in this course. this is why we want you to understand what happens when the program executes. looking at the error message my guess is that you've overflowed a buffer and messed up the heap which manifests as the invalid size error. it might happen to work on your laptop because it uses a different implementation of malloc where the buffer overflow doesn't have the same effect.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i think i'm having some issues with realloc . the error i get is add malloc.c 2868 mremap_chunk assertion size offset amp glro dl_pagesize - 1 0' failed. it is only when i am adding 2 very large numbers. such as tests 8 and 9. any help would be much apprecated thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"hi brendan i suspect the pointer you are passing to malloc may not be valid. the only pointers you can pass in to realloc are null or a pointer that's previously been returned from malloc . is it possible you passed in a pointer to a local variable instead of a pointer that's on the heap ie. from malloc","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"or perhaps you ran over the end of a malloc'd buffer earlier. doing that inevitably messes up the heap so that future malloc's are likely to fail possibly in other parts of the program away from the original error . this one of the joys of c's dynamic memory management. you could try compiling with dcc which reasonably good at detecting and reporting such problems.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"whenever i try to make add after i run it i get a segmentatiom fault. what does this mean and how do i fix it","answers":[{"text":"a segmentation fault is from an illegal memory access. it is often the result of trying to access an array element and going too far off the end or dereferencing an invalid pointer. for example you could get a segfault if you loop over an array but go one too far or if you try to loop over an array where no memory has been allocated to it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i realised just now that i've scanned in the bignum opposite from what we're supposed to however my code passes the tests. would i get penalised for implementing an opposite bignum","answers":[{"text":"no. we're more interested that you can produce a working solution ... and also that the code is readable and reasonably efficient.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi. if i have finally completed the challenge exercise should i submit bignum.c file with the subtractbignums and mutiplybignums functions i manually added or put them in a separate file to submit or show them to my tutor instead since i didn't see any files containing the challenge exercises..","answers":[{"text":"it's harmless to include them in the bignum.c that you submit as long as that version passes all of the check tests. if you want the bonus you'll need to demonstrate to your tutor that your functions actually work.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"because bignum is only supposed to hold chars of digits from 0..9 for subtractbignums can we assume that the result will always be positive or do we extend this to include a '-' character","answers":[{"text":"you should implement negatives but it doesn't necessarily have to be with a character in the bytes array it could be stored on the struct.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can't scan big numbers hi my bignum.c works fine for numbers that are relatively small in length 20 characters but stops scanning after that. what are some possible reasons for it to do that i think i've ensured that the size nbytes amp malloc'd array of chars of bignum matches the argv exactly. not sure if i can post code extracts so i won't. can someone please help me d","answers":[{"text":"easiest to debug if you can see the code ... but don't post it here. take it along to one of the help sessions","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is this the correct give command give cs1521 lab02 bignum.c","answers":[{"text":"yes it looks correct. is it not working","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it is working but i also have made changes to bignum.h and i have added sub.c and mul.c","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok the give command will only upload your bignum.c file i don't think it will let you upload those you can try by adding the file names after bignum.c but i'd suggest just showing the extension work to a tutor next week in class.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i've been trying to figuring the issue with these 3 tests my program can't pass how do i find out what input is received during these tests","answers":[{"text":"look in the tests/ directory.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the warm-up question can i use 04x to print the hexadecimal","answers":[{"text":"does the 04 pad it with zeroes such that the length of the string is always 4 i changed all my xs to 04x and i saw no change.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"lt var gt n lt /var gt d pads right to the width of lt var gt n lt /var gt with spaces. 0 lt var gt n lt /var gt d pads right to the width of lt var gt n lt /var gt with zeroes. - lt var gt n lt /var gt d pads left to the width of lt var gt n lt /var gt with spaces.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i am not sure about this. i think it should be output as 0x000000 form. so the prefix for hexadecimal should be 0x.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm also not sure about this but i think it is fine without the prefix. i know that p can give you the prefix while x will just print it out in hex. i think p is used more for printing memory locations. either way it should be too hard to add the prefix if needed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"p is the format code for an address not for a general hexadecimal number. you should use x instead.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep. i agree with you. p is print out the memory address. i think 0x x should be fine.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i've passed all the tests except the 9th one and was wondering what was causing the problem attached is a picture of my output and it seems like the first number is being overlapped by the second number if anyone could point me in the right direction it would be great thanks ./add 123123123123123123123123123123123123123 9879879879879879879987987879879879","answers":[{"text":"with only that amount of info it sounds like one of your arrays isn't big enough and you've overflowed into the other array. check whether your check for array being full is ok and then check that your code to increase array size is ok. best to ask your tutor or at a help session.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"about lab02 challenge exercises do we need to consider negative number like 3-5 -2 do we need to add negative sign to the string and output it or we can ignore negative numbers","answers":[{"text":"yes you should consider negative numbers. as part of the challenge you need to come up with a more compact structure so you can change the struct however you like to take into account negative numbers. just make sure it s backwards compatible with the original test cases add function etc.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"idk i guess you can add it in if you want. i just added an int is_negative in the bignum struct then in the sub function if m gt n then i would do a sub m n res and set res- gt is_negative to 1.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am doing lab02 now which is about calculating big numbers. and i almost finished but i tried to test it. unfortunately it passed all tests except test5. and i checked the test file. it includes .exp and .out files. and i thought that's all for testing my program. but i opened test 5.exp and use the information inside to test my program directly. and the output matches the answer in 5.exp. but when i compared 5.out with other .out files i found that the other .out files are all vacant but 5.out includes the information exactly same with the output i use diff after i test my program. hence is there any program with the test files or is there something i understand incorrectly","answers":[{"text":"the 5.exp file is the expected output from running test 5 in the 5.sh file the 5.out file is the one that your program produced when you ran the check command. i'm not sure whether that answers your question ...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh actually when i tried to test ./add 020 300 i found the weakness of my function. thanks very much.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is the test .sh file correct ./add 020 300 as compared to ./add 020 300 -- added some extra code into my add.c this is what i get","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the 5.sh file is correct. it's checking for how you handle spaces around a number the example should have only three argv values argv 0 ./add argv 1 020 argv 2 300","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"actually on second thoughts it seems that the issue was the way that i was running the tests","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"with the warm up exercise am i allowed to use the pow function from the math library","answers":[{"text":"the warm-up is working with integer values. pow works with doubles. i'm not sure how it helps.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i know that with the unsigned data types i can underflow them and that will give the biggest value. but i'm still a little lost with the other data types. two methods come to my mind. 1. keep incrementing by 1 until you detect an overflow and return the value. probably takes a long time . 2. use the pow where the base is 2 and the power is the number of bits. i type casted pow to the appropriate data type. e.g. int pow ... one weird thing that i have notice is that if i incorrectly put the power number higher that it should be the int data type does not overflow ' int x int pow 2 4 10 ' does not overflow but when i increment it it will overflow.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"try using lt lt for powers of 2.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the answer to q5 states that 'constant strings are located in the data region of memory'. is this correct i read that they are stored in the 'text' region of memory which is read-only hence why they can't be modified and therefore given the name 'constant'. strings stored as arrays on the other hand can be modified and so are stored in the 'data' section of memory which is writable.","answers":[{"text":"interesting question. constant string values are certainly read-only but they don't seem to be in the text area if you believe the output from the following program include lt stdio.h gt extern char etext edata end char buf 100 int i1 5 const int i2 7 int main void int i amp i2 char s abc printf s p n s printf i1 p n amp i1 printf i2 p n amp i2 printf buf p n buf printf etext p n amp etext printf edata p n amp edata printf end p n amp end // s 0 'b' produces a runtime error // i2 5 produces a compiler error return 0 when i run this on a cse server it tells me that s and i2 are located just above the top of the text region etext . the buf and i1 variables are located a little higher in the memory. my take there is a read-only region at the bottom of the data area where immutable objects are placed. to find out about etext edata and end try the command man etext","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks john i added the extext edata and end variables to my code below include lt stdio.h gt extern char etext edata end char s1 abc char a1 4 abc void func1 void int main void char s2 xyz char s3 'b' printf etext p n amp etext printf edata p n amp edata printf end p n amp end printf --------------------------------- n printf address of s1 pointer is p n amp s1 printf address of s1 element 0 is p n amp s1 0 printf data in s1 element 0 is c n s1 0 printf address of s1 element 1 is p n amp s1 1 printf data in s1 element 1 is c n s1 1 printf address of s1 element 2 is p n amp s1 2 printf data in s1 element 2 is c n s1 2 printf address of s1 element 3 is p n amp s1 3 printf data in s1 element 3 is c n s1 3 printf --------------------------------- n printf address of s2 is p n amp s2 printf address of s2 is p n amp s2 1 printf address of s2 is p n amp s2 2 printf address of s2 is p n amp s2 3 printf --------------------------------- n printf address of s3 is p n amp s3 printf data in s3 is c n s3 printf --------------------------------- n printf address of a1 is p n amp a1 printf data in a1 is s n a1 printf address of a1 element 0 is p n amp a1 0 printf data in a1 element 0 is c n a1 0 printf address of a1 element 1 is p n amp a1 1 printf data in a1 element 1 is c n a1 1 printf address of a1 element 2 is p n amp a1 2 printf address of a1 element 3 is p n amp a1 3 func1 void func1 void static int i 1 printf address of i is p n amp i when i ran it it got the following etext 0x8048828 edata 0x804a02c end 0x804a030 --------------------------------- address of s1 pointer is 0x804a020 data in s1 pointer is 0x8048830 address of s1 element 0 is 0x8048830 data in s1 element 0 is a address of s1 element 1 is 0x8048831 data in s1 element 1 is b address of s1 element 2 is 0x8048832 data in s1 element 2 is c address of s1 element 3 is 0x8048833 data in s1 element 3 is --------------------------------- address of s2 is 0xffce003c data in s2 is 0x8048834 address of s2 is 0x8048834 address of s2 is 0x8048835 address of s2 is 0x8048836 address of s2 is 0x8048837 --------------------------------- address of s3 is 0xffce003b data in s3 is b --------------------------------- address of a1 is 0x804a024 data in a1 is abc address of a1 element 0 is 0x804a024 data in a1 element 0 is a address of a1 element 1 is 0x804a025 data in a1 element 1 is b address of a1 element 2 is 0x804a026 data in a1 element 2 is c address of a1 element 3 is 0x804a027 data in a1 element 3 is --------------------------------- address of i is 0x804a028 so i could see that the address of the elements of s1 global string constant and a1 global char array seemed to be in different locations. where as the location of the s1 and s2 local string constant were located next to each other. comparing these memory addresses to etext edata and end it looks like the strings whether they be string constant s1 s2 or array a1 are stored in the data area but definitely s1/s2 are stored separate to a1. the actual pointer addresses of s1 and a2 are next to each other as is the rest of the data of a2 but the memory location that s1 points to is in a seperate area of memory the same area s2 points to. does this align with what you saw thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes. and this is a nice exploration of the problem.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for confirming john.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we have the official solution for tutorial and lab sometimes i felt hard to understand the tutor's explanation.","answers":[{"text":"i'll put up solutions to the tute exercises. if you find that your tutor is difficult to understand ask them to explain again but differently.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi jas can you please upload the answer for this tutorial and last week's one all the other tutorials have a show answer button for every question except these 2 weeks which are week 11 and 12","answers":[{"text":"done","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i have some questions about system calls in cat3.c in the lecture exercises int in open argv 1 o_rdonly if in lt 0 error errno errno can't open s argv 1 above is the code for open when we call open it returns a file descriptor here it checks if it's less than 0 but wouldn't it be better if we do in lt 3 instead cause we don't want 0 1 and 2 as file descriptors since they're default for stdin stdout and stderr. char buf max int nread while nread read in buf max 0 write 1 buf nread and this is the code for read read returns -1 when it fails shouldn't we check if nread gt 0 instead of 0 cheers","answers":[{"text":"for the open question checking for in lt 0 is correct. the open call won't allocate any of 0 1 or 2 because they're already in use so there's no use checking for them. if it succeeds it will return a value 3 or higher. if it fails it will return -1. no other values are relevant and only -1 is an error result. for the read question yes ... checking for the return value being gt 0 would probably be better. the code is assuming that there won't be errors and in that context the termination return value is 0.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i'll just check them both is greater then 0 before using it","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in testing suggestions should cat assign1 not be saved into history since it generated an error message and returned 1 or is it supposed to be added to commandhistory thank you","answers":[{"text":"since the cat command actually executed it should be added.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh okay thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what exactly are the tests regarding 'nonexec' doing for some reason my 'isexecutionable' function isn't picking up that the 'nonexec' file is not an executionable.","answers":[{"text":"note that nonexec is executable. it gets recognised as problematic when the execve fails.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ah ok - that makes sense. however when i use perror after the execve i get ./nonexec exec format error instead of ./nonexec uknown type of executionable . should i just hardcode it to match the error message in the sample","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes. just copy what cs1521/bin/mymysh does","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"how are you checking for this","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it is similar to the lab code - wherein it checks if we have permission to execute it whether its a regular file and whether its accessible.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it should succeed in all these checks and fail when you try to execve it","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"had some problems with permissions could just be my code isn't working correctly. mymysh$ ls -l cs1521/web/18s2/assignments ls cannot open directory /import/ravel/3/cs1521/web/18s2/assignments permission denied cd cs1521/web/18s2/assignments ls ls cannot open directory . permission denied","answers":[{"text":"ok ... now fixed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm getting the same. i don't think it's your code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i got the same problem.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if anyone is wondering how to test the wildcard stuff other than i ve made a list of commands that you can try in your shell in the following order mkdir atestfolder cd atestfolder touch q123123.c q1.c q2.c q3.c q4.c q5.c q21.c q22.c q23.c q31.c q33.c q34.c random.c ls ls q .c ls q .c ls q .c ls q .c q .c ls q 2-4 .c ls q 2 1-5 .c ls q 1-9 1-9 .c ls q .c cd .. rm -r atestfolder exit","answers":[{"text":"thanks. but people won't see this unless they subscribed to the comment stream on the assignment testing page. i've added your tests to the testing suggestions page.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i try to fscanf in from the history file i have bits of the previously scanned line or am missing parts of the new line. how do i avoid this i am currently placing the scanned string into a buffer char of length 100 a chosen buffer length and reusing that char for each scanf.","answers":[{"text":"don't use fscanf . use fgets to read each line into a buffer and then use sscanf to parse the text in the buffer.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is this memory leak on line 299 the code i have on mymysh.c is if strcmp args i lt equal my code doesn't even go to 299 on history.c","answers":[{"text":"at the moment all i can tell is that you are calling strdup in findexecutable and never freeing the result.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"its line 299 in the malloc.c file. you don't appear to be compiling with the -g flag so it's not giving very good info.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i was hoping someone could explain why 'showcommandhistory' is supposed to take a file input in the history scaffold. the parameter has two different names in history.h void showcommandhistory file histfile in history.c void showcommandhistory file outf i thought it might be to redirect output but displaying history shouldn't ever redirect going by the example program . the other option would be to read in the history from the history file but the history is already loaded into the 'commandhistory' struct and that is all i use to display the command history. am i missing something obvious or is this parameter useless","answers":[{"text":"the parameter makes the savecommandhistory function easier to write","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahh ok thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"cd is not working when i input cd by itself and then cd'ing into another folder i know i have. cd works when i am in cs1521 folder but not when i'm in my home directory. i am wondering if it is a permission issue or my code's issue. anyone else","answers":[{"text":"does cd /knownfolder work when you use cd by itself what do you see if the next command is pwd or ls","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"all 3 of your suggestions work - it is only when i try to cd file when it does not work. the error is triggered by chdir returning -1.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you can't cd to a file if that's what your comment meant. and if you're putting quotes around the directory name that you want to cd to that won't work either. have a read of man 2 chdir ... do any of the errors mentioned there apply in your case","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry i phrased that very carelessly i meant directory and the quotations weren't part of input. i've looked up chdir but am unsure how to check the error output except for the fact chdir returns -1 if it fails which i've used to print no such file or directory . how do i print errno to output so i can find out which error i am facing thanks edit worked it out by passing absolute path to chdir instead of just relative path before.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"perror will tell you which error","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm currently trying to add an extra element onto my tokens array to implement glob properly. assuming that it was tokenised to have 2 elements - ls - .c how would i create a new one so that i can include the wildcard returns from .c i've tried things such as the following i 3 tokens i strdup gl_pathc i but i receive an illegal array pointer. i thought that strdup would allocate the memory for me. thanks for any help.","answers":[{"text":"first off gl_pathc is an int. gl_pathv is the array you want. secondly you will need to realloc the tokens array to its current size plus gl_argc-1. if you take this approach. both of there problems will cause an illegal array error. to fix this you could realloc like i mentioned above or you could use glob_nocheck as a flag to glob and call glob on all elements of the tokens array in order. this will give you back a gl_pathv array that you can use as your new tokens array without needing to strdup every element.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahhh. finally got it thank you dylan. the only thing is i'm not sure whether i should tokenise this gl_pathv array or not. i'm currently returning gl_pathv but it sometimes works and then sometimes segfaults. i assume this has to do with running out of memory maybe i can return gl_pathv but then i'm not able to free it at the end of my program because it's not recognised as a glob_t anymore. alternatively i could tokenise it and send this back but i'm not sure what i would pass as the second argument of tokenise. there is no string that separates each token. have i missed something edit i should also mention that i'm using the glob_append flag.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"gl_pathv is a tokenised array. you can free it with freetokens.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thank you for that. do you know why i would be getting this error message then when i input ls it seems to be intermittent and i can't figure out why. it goes away when i create a debug loop printing out all the gl_pathv strings and then comes back when i delete this loop. i can't figure out why this would be happening. mymysh.c 234 runtime error - illegal array pointer or other operation execution stopped here in filenameexpand tokens 0x60300000c850 in mymysh.c at line 234 int i for i 0 tokens i null i -- gt glob tokens i glob_tilde glob_nocheck glob_append 0 amp result values when execution stopped i 0 tokens i ls let me know if it's easier if i email my code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the first call to glob shouldn't have glob_append only on subsequent calls. also the second last argument should be null not 0.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you so much dylan","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i am confused as to how far back our code should go with this input 'ls / ' - my ref imp is functioning for ls / / but breaking on ls / / / - my implementation works up to / / / but is snail pace on / / / / - also the actual bash on cse says argument list is too long if you try to do this outside the mymysh how far back do we have to do thanks","answers":[{"text":"as far as the example goes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"no such file/ directory error i keep getting this error when i do cat lt xyx.txt even though it does execute the command and print the contents of the file to the terminal. i cant seem to figure out where i'm going wrong because the error isn't any of the ones i'v set up using perror. any ideas where i should be checking","answers":[{"text":"you're passing lt as an argument to cat you need to remove lt and the file name after you do the redirection and before you execve .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"fixed thank you so much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i understand when you call execve and it succeeds it throws away the child process after the execution. however if it fails the child process is still running. how do i close the child process my issue is when i type the command ./nonexec execve fails but it doesn't close the forked shelled. therefore i have to type exit 2 times instead of 1","answers":[{"text":"put a call to the exit function after you print the error message for execve failing","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you. i was trying kill 0 sigterm and kill 0 sigkill and it wasn't giving the same output but exit 1 did it. thanks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if we were to run an invalid command such as cat lt is it necessary to print an error message and then proceed to ask for input prompt","answers":[{"text":"go by what the example does.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we have any guarantees on the maximum size of the expanded form of the string $home/.mymysh_history","answers":[{"text":"$home wont be longer than max_path the whole thing shouldn't be longer than max_path but that's not entirely guaranteed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"where's max_path defined","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"include lt linux/limits.h gt although it is probably better to just use strlen on the return of getenv home","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi in the suggestions for testing how is this particular error message generated i'm asking because the error message that my program produces is different. i don't get ./nonexec unknown type of executable","answers":[{"text":"what error message do you get this issue was discussed in another comments thread .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the error message that i get is ./nonexec exec format error . i used perror and exit 255 but the message is different. the thread that you linked said that the error was manually printed does that refer to the unknown type of executable part","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"clearly mymysh doesn't use perror ... just copy what mymysh does.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have a problem with isexecutable function even though it wasn't modified in any way. i haven't had this error message until today.","answers":[{"text":"nvm i forgot a curly brace somewhere lmao","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"regarding printing errors to stderr or the current output stream a number of answers already have indicated that when printing our own errors our choice doesn't matter. however this creates a functional difference with the reference program. in the tests released today trying to run the non-executable file nonexec with ./nonexec printed an error message ./nonexec unknown type of executable . if we run with ./nonexec gt ne.out the error message gets printed to the ne.out file instead. however printing the error to stderr in our own programs causes it to be printed to the terminal rather than the file. can we assume that the autotests used for marking won't be redirecting commands with error messages if we can't can we have a list of when the reference uses stderr and when it uses the current output stream to ensure that our functionality is the same","answers":[{"text":"we will try to fiddle the output to ensure consistent output whether to stderr/stdout. i'm sure we'll be able to filter the output from your program to knock it into canonical form. if we can't work out how to do it then we won't use that test and we can manually check whether you've handled non-executable objects appropriately.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi quick question about the cs1521/bin/mymysh given a clean history if 'h' is the first command typed the response is my current code does this instead is the sample solution bugged or should we try to follow that thanks","answers":[{"text":"this isn't what i see. when you say clean history what precisely does that mean remove the history file make it zero length edit it and have a single newline","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ah i think it was the edit with single new line causing this. thanks one more quick question should sequence numbers begin at 0 or 1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"they begin at 1.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"mine shows nothing with clean history. hope this may helps","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when creating the string path for opening /.mymysh_history home is being changed to the assignment 2 directory. after this code printf s n getenv home and printf s n path are the same output. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"your declaration of path doesn't allocate any memory. the getenv function returns a pointer to the string in the environment array. the strcat function will then try to append the name of the history file to this element in the environment array. the elements in the env array are fixed size it doesn't make sense to concatenate something onto the end of a full fixed-size array. define path as a large array. copy the environment string into that array. the append histfile.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"should i add the function to the history if there is an fopen error when i try and redirect stdout say i do ls .txt gt so normally it wouldn't output to a file anything since there is invalid file redirection but running execve would still return 0 so it is technically a success my current output is mymysh$ ls .txt gt ls.out running /bin/ls ... -------------------- fopen failure bad address -------------------- returns 0 is this acceptable or should i just make it terminate upon an error","answers":[{"text":"this should result in no execve happening and the command shouldn't be added to the history. the running... should only be printed if you are going to execve and all checks for a valid command should happen first. but the line given should work.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks something must be wrong i'll give it a go","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello when i do something like cat file.txt gt test.txt the result in my text.txt is https //pastebin.com/ek0sj4nm the content of file.txt is https //pastebin.com/bvrik5rq i am unsure of how i am suppose to get rid of the unwanted parts in text.txt","answers":[{"text":"don't use pastebin. all of those crap ads it spews at you obscure the text. you can paste images into your post using the little mountain icon on the command line just above.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"test.txt after running the cat command file.txt so there s a bunch of unwanted text in test.txt. it should just say this is the contents of file.txt","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"looks like your dup2 ing too early in the program. the dup2 s should be inside the child part of the fork.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i think you were right. i added my redirection code in my child process if statement if pid 0 which got rid of the ending divider and return value. however it is still putting in the top part of the content in my test.txt file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it still looks like you're dup2 is too early or at least the running... is to late. the running... should be right before the fork.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hmm... what i am doing is 1. forking 2. if statement to check if i am in the child. 3. in that if statement in the child i print running 4. execute 5. in parent i print the ending divider","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"move 3 to before the fork.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you i fixed it. i just forgot to move the dup2 part again","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"1. print out running 2. forking 3. if statement to check i am in the child 4. in child i execute 5. print out divider outside the if statement output of text.txt","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm getting this error everytime i use my file card expansion twice. free invalid next size normal aborted . this occurs on the line that i call glob wildcard_s glob_nocheck glob_tilde 0 amp glob_struct . what does this mean and how would i fix it p.s. it works perfectly fine the first time","answers":[{"text":"sorry didn't see the rest. its because you don't have the glob_append flag on your glob call.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i added glob_append but that didn't solve anything. i noticed something else though in this loop args 0 originally ls changes midway through the loop. is there something wrong with the way i'm mallocing while j lt glob_struct.gl_pathc printf args 0 s n args 0 if args i null printf i d n i args i malloc sizeof char maxline strcpy args i glob_struct.gl_pathv j printf s n args i i j args i null","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is the args array malloced large enough the last line sets args i to null. if i is 0 this will be bad.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"your freeing something that isn't malloced. run with valgrind or gdb to find out where.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello can we make the assumption that the correct usage of ' ' will always be as the first letter in a command what i mean valid cd /me.txt cd cs1521 ls invalid i can't think of any examples ls root/","answers":[{"text":"follow what the example does.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm unable to unzip /home/cs1521/web/18s2/assignments/assign2/files.zip i'm not sure why. am i doing something wrong thanks.","answers":[{"text":"now fixed. try again.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in cs1521/bin/mymysh mymysh$ lt asdf will print invalid i/o redirection shouldn't it print ' lt command not found","answers":[{"text":"that's one way you could do it. cs1521/bin/ mymysh does it another equally valid way. copy what the reference solution does.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"this really just has to do with the order that things are checked in. try to recreate this error.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in a directory with a file named cd the provided solution executes the built-in cd command upon the input cd lt some_filename gt moreover it does not execute the built-in history command on a similar corresponding setup. does this constitute a bug or should we replicate this behaviour","answers":[{"text":"in a directory with a file named cd the provided solution executes the built-in cd command this is what i'd expect it to do. i'm not sure what the precise problem is here if mymysh sees a built-in like cd and h it processes that and doesn't bother looking for a command with that name in the path. a file with the name cd would never be executed even if the x flag was on.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"just poking this question will any auto tests be available before the due time thanks _____________________________ yinan feng 10 days ago hi i wonder can we have some autotest to make sure we do not have silly mistakes including format n space... thank you in advance lt header gt john shepherd 10 days ago lt /header gt once i've finished writing an assignment for my other course i'll put up some testing stuff.however but this stage you ought to be able to do testing yourself ...e.g. write a sequence of shell commands in a file then do something like ./mymysh lt fileofcommands gt out.obs cs1521/bin/mymysh lt fileofcommands gt out.exp diff out.obs out.exp after all this is what we do for auto-testing. lt footer gt lt /footer gt","answers":[{"text":"some testing suggestions are now available. auto-testing no. see the notice.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"my output the correct outpu i cant figure out how to get the error names correct and still have them launch to the correct directories. do you have any suggestions","answers":[{"text":"your code execve tokens 0 tokens envp example code execve command tokens envp the example doesn't modify the tokens array with the full path but creates a new variable while you are modifying the tokens array.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"several questions 1. in both redirects it is written tokens ' gt ' ' lt ' and a filename as the last two tokens does it mean that we can treat both cases separately we can ignore the possibility of input and output in the same command line example $ ./executable lt input.txt gt output.txt 2. in the history part what does it mean by an executable for the command first token actually exists isn't all executable counted as valid command or am i getting it wrong","answers":[{"text":"1. getting both an input and output redirection is an error only one is allowed at a time. 2. if the user enters a command that doesn't exists eg cta instead of cat then cta isn't added to the history.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi should i be concerned that my program works but i haven't used pipe anywhere thanks liz.","answers":[{"text":"you don't necessarily need the pipe function it would be useful in the challenge though","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run my code through valgrind i get a few of the follow errors uninitialised value was created by a stack allocation conditional jump or move depends on uninitialised values uninitialised value was created by a heap allocation use of uninitialised value of size 4 invalid write of size 1 address 0xsome_address is 0 bytes after a block of size 200 was alloc'd however my code seems to work fine no compile warnings or errors and valgrind doesn't report any memory leaks with memcheck. do i need to be concerned about these errors what causes them and how can i fix them","answers":[{"text":"this means that you are using a piece of memory as a condition probably in a loop or if before you assign a value. it's a good idea to fix this issue even more than memory leaks as the memory you're using could have any value stored in it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when running the commands cs1521/bin/mymysh lt command.txt gt exp ./mymysh lt command.txt gt exp2 i notice that the outputted files have different values however when output is directly in the shell they are the same. i understand that this is due to stderr when there is an error however based on the above output i'm not sure what is in stderr when i run cs1521/bin/mymysh lt command.txt gt exp i get when i run ./mymysh lt command.txt gt exp2 i get why would the given shell not output the '-----' below the error message './cat unknown type of executable' cat is just an empty file","answers":[{"text":"try doing your redirection using ./mymysh lt command.txt gt output.txt 2 gt amp 1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hello i checked using your command however it still gives the same output","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"your output is more correct it has to do with the order of error checking in the example i believe.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i have some questions about this assignment. 1. will our program be tested under some special conditions like $home is not set or being provided an invalid .mymysh_history random order or invalid sequence number invalid line ... 2. i notice that /cs1521/bin/mymysh will also tokenise ' t' which is the horizontal tab. are there any other characters that need to be used in tokenise 3. if i interrupt a command for example run sleep 10' then immediately press ctrl c both sleep and cs1521/bin/mymysh will exit. are we supposed to keep myshsh running when it is running a command and we press ctrl c 4. for the redirection should we treat the commands like cat lt .c valid or not if .c matches exactly 1 file 5. if i run a command like echo abcd gt .txt and .txt does not match and files with glob_nocheck glob will preserve exactly .txt and cs1521/bin/mymysh will actually create a file called .txt . is this correct or not 6. should we print running xxxx ... -------------------- -------------------- returns xx to stdout or stderr 7. should the error message printed by our myshsh matches exactly what cs1521/bin/mymysh prints if so what should be printed if fork execve malloc wait etc... fail since these errors rarely occur. thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"some of these questions can be answered by do what cs1521/bin/mymysh does. for those questions i'll just say follow cs1521/bin/mymysh . 1. will our program be tested under some special conditions like $home is not set or being provided an invalid .mymysh_history random order or invalid sequence number invalid line ... no ... they'll be tested under normal conditions . and we're not mean or stupid. if we find that everyone's prrogram is failing because of some assumption we've made we'll change the tests. 2. i notice that /cs1521/bin/mymysh will also tokenise ' t' which is the horizontal tab. are there any other characters that need to be used in tokenise no. it used to tokenise on and ' as well but we stopped doing that a while ago. 3. if i interrupt a command for example run sleep 10' then immediately press ctrl c both sleep and cs1521/bin/mymysh will exit. are we supposed to keep myshsh running when it is running a command and we press ctrl c follow cs1521/bin/mymysh. 4. for the redirection should we treat the commands like cat lt .c valid or not if .c matches exactly 1 file follow cs1521/bin/mymysh. 5. if i run a command like echo abcd gt .txt and .txt does not match and files with glob_nocheck glob will preserve exactly .txt and cs1521/bin/mymysh will actually create a file called .txt . is this correct or not follow cs1521/bin/mymysh. 6. should we print running xxxx ... -------------------- -------------------- returns xx to stdout or stderr stdout i.e. follow cs1521/bin/mymysh 7. should the error message printed by our myshsh matches exactly what cs1521/bin/mymysh prints if so what should be printed if fork execve malloc wait etc... fail since these errors rarely occur. you can assume that fork malloc wait won't fail. they won't fail during our testing. you can test an execve failure easily enough to see what cs1521/bin/mymysh does. it would have been useful to ask these kinds of questions two weeks ago in the period when we were tightening the spec. too late to change it now.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we need to handle ' gt ' and ' lt ' in the command something like lt command.txt gt output.txt in the spec it says having gt or lt anywhere but the 2nd last token in the line should result in an error but i've been seeing posts that include it.","answers":[{"text":"no command to mymysh should contain both lt and gt the posts you've been seeing are talking about running mymysh from bash the real shell and capturing mymysh 's output.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i used the glob to do the file expansion i don't know why sometimes an empty space or a messy code start on my buffer maxline . please help me to find out . thank you","answers":[{"text":"it is impossible to diagnose your problem effectively with this much information. note that the expanded filenames don't need to go into the command line buffer anyway. they should be added as extra tokens into your tokens array. the .c should remain in the command like buffer and be stored in the history list. perhaps you could use gdb to track how the values of tokens 0 or whatever you call you array of tokens changes during the execution of your code that does the glob expansion.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi should we get rid of the if debug region in the base code for the assignment","answers":[{"text":"edit the makefile and use a version of cflags that doesn't have -ddbug in it. and then ... make clean make","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but for final submission does it matter whether we keep the debug portion in or should we remove it","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"we're suppliying the makefile for auto-testing. we won't run with debugging on. if you add your own debugging output remove it before submission or wrap it in ifdef dbug ... endif","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm experiencing issues with the cat command printing output in different order when i run the command cat .h gt gt abc using cs1521/bin/mymysh i get this however when i run using ./mymysh i get the two lines cat gt gt no such file or directory and cat abc no such file or directory are being printed before the .h file in my program but after the .h file in the sample shell. is there any way to fix this","answers":[{"text":"mymysh doesn't handle gt gt it's producing the correct response in this case.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it looks like you convert cat .h gt gt abc to cat gt gt abc history.h . when you expand wildcards you should expand in place. hence it should be converted to cat history.h gt gt abc","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey. i was wondering why my file name expansion function did not expand the tilde wild card properly. all the other wildcards seem to work. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"this is what my program/terminal displays","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the man page for glob explains the different options that can be used with it. i think you'll find your answer there.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep consider what simon said and also consider the hint in the assignment hint use glob_nocheck glob_tilde as the second parameter of the glob function","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello as per the spec i am compiling under dcc. i have compiled the provided template mymysh.c file and receive the following error during runtime mymysh.c 59 runtime error - illegal array pointer or other operation execution stopped here in main in mymysh.c at line 59 //if envp 0 null // -- gt for i 0 envp i null i if strncmp envp i path 5 0 break values when execution stopped i 0 envp i this error does not happen with gcc. is there a workaround for this thanks","answers":[{"text":"as per the spec i am compiling under dcc. that was a typo in the spec. it should have been gcc . and the makefile uses gcc . i can't see why dcc should be complaining. i'd need to see the rest of your code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i have the same issue but it occurs when i run the shell. i've tried recompiling using both dcc and gcc but same error occurs","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"as i said i'd need to see the rest of the code to see what you've done wrong with envp which is the most likely cause of such an error.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm currently trying to replace the token with the result from glob . edit removed code. left what was most needed for the question. glob_t result int i printf found a tilde n printf corresponds to s n result.gl_pathv strcpy tokens i result.gl_pathv i had thought that a simple strcpy tokens i result.gl_pathv would be fine to pass the value across to replace the tilde with the path to the home directory. i had thought this would be fine as the space has already been malloced from the tokenise function. however i'm receiving errors related to illegal array pointer or other operation. could someone please explaing to me what i'm not understanding here. i have also tried using array elements. e.g. strcpy tokens 0 result.gl_pathv 0 strcpy amp tokens 0 result.gl_pathv 0 thank you for any help.","answers":[{"text":"hey joe not sure but maybe when tokens was malloc'd the amount of space allocated is less than you need to copy the expanded home directory into the same location. you could maybe create your own char array and malloc it to copy the strings from result.gl_pathv or maybe pass the actual result struct itself back to main and read through the expanded paths in result.gl_pathv. this would require a bit of tweaking though as the result.gl_pathv array doesn't hold the executable name and any of switches that execve needs so it needs to be massaged a bit to work. using glob_dooffs with glob allows x number of slots to be left available at the beginning where other strings could be copied to. i.e. executable name.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for that simon.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"please remove your code from the forum. if you need to share code please do it by email. the problem is size expanding a results in a much larger string than what you started with and tokens 0 hasn't got the space for it. you could either 1. realloc tokens 0 2. free tokens 0 then strdup into it 3. free tokens 0 then assign it as a pointer.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry dylan. have removed the code and left what is needed for the question to make sense. let me know if i need to remove that too. i'll give your suggestions a try. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am having trouble with the char glob_command array i am using within the filenameexpand function to hold the possibly larger list of tokens to return back to main for execution. i can't seem to populate it with more than two string elements. i malloc the array as below based on the number of expanded paths in the paths struct after globbing plus the number of switch arguments identified in tokens args starting with '-' plus an extra element to hold the command being executed. i have confirmed the values used to calculate glob_command_size are correct while debugging this. char glob_command glob_command_size paths.gl_pathc switch_count 1 glob_command malloc glob_command_size sizeof char i am testing with a command such as ls -l -a intentionally with multiple switch arguments and i am able to copy the first string the command from tokens to glob_command strcpy glob_command 0 tokens 0 debugging output from above command was glob_command 0 is now ls but when i then use a loop to copy all switch arguments starting with '-' from tokens to glob_command i can only copy one string before the function breaks for i 1 j 1 tokens i null i printf current j is d and i is d n j i printf current tokens d s n i tokens i if tokens i 0 '-' printf found switch n strcpy glob_command j tokens i printf copied switch s n tokens i printf glob_command d is now s n i glob_command i j i have performed debugging by adding print statements and can confirm the second switch -a argument in the command ls -l -a is matched by the the line if tokens i 0 '-' but the strcpy function following that condition statement fails. glob_command 0 is now ls current j is 1 and i is 1 current tokens 1 -l found switch copied switch -l glob_command 1 is now -l current j is 2 and i is 2 current tokens 2 -a found switch -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ as part of my troubleshooting after mallocing glob_command i printed its content expecting all strings in the array to be null but found the first two seemed to hold garbage as shown below and i am not sure if this is related to why i can only copy two strings the command to execute and the first matched switch argument to it or not glob_command 0 is hd x x x 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w glob_command 1 is hd x x x 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w 'w glob_command 2 is null glob_command 3 is null glob_command 4 is null glob_command 5 is null glob_command 6 is null glob_command 7 is null glob_command 8 is null glob_command 9 is null glob_command 10 is null glob_command 11 is null glob_command 12 is null glob_command 13 is null glob_command 14 is null glob_command 15 is null glob_command 16 is null glob_command 17 is null glob_command 18 is null glob_command 19 is null i think the issue has something to do with memory allocation but i can't work out why the above for loop fails when trying to added a third element to the glob_command array. can anyone shed any light on this for me","answers":[{"text":"the problem your having is how to alloc a 2d array. glob_commands is an array of pointers but but each element of the array also needs to be alloced as an array of chars. now filenameexpand takes a char so you can pass tokens directly into it and if you give glob the glob_nocheck flag glob will do all if this for you as glob mallocs the strings it returns.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so do i need to malloc within a loop first mallocing the outer array and then traversing through it to malloc each inner array","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"for a array of strings normally yes. but the strings returned from glob are already malloced so you shouldnt need to.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks dylan i was original using the array within the glob struct but it seemed a bit fiddly as i needed to use realloc to get it working properly so i decided to rewrite this section by copying the content out of the glob output into a char array. i seemed to have got it working now though. thanks for your help.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"permission denied with open o_creat hi i was trying to use open outputfilename o_creat to have a output file to redirect. but by perror it showed permission denied . the file was created but showed permission denied again when using cat command to inspect this file. how could this be solved thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"i am still trying to perfect file output redirection myself but i think you'll find you need to tweak your permission flags when calling open . have a look at 'man 2 open' and there are a bunch of options you can use with o_create to set the permissions on the file you create.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run the special notation for re-executes the previous command with additional strings behind for example sfihkdff in the cs1521/bin/mymysh shell it still re-executes the previous command. however from the linux bash command it doesn't execute the previous coommand and shows bash sfihkdff command not found . so for this assignment which spec should i follow","answers":[{"text":"mymysh isn't bash you should stick with the example and just ignore everythong folloing .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run cs1521/bin/mymysh with cd it automatically cd home but this feature is not the spec should we modify this feature in our code","answers":[{"text":"your shell should do this yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for some reason the return status of my child process is always 256 times larger than that of the reference soln. is it safe to just divide mine by 256 or will that potentially cause problems later reference soln my soln","answers":[{"text":"you need to use the wexitstatus function described by man 2 wait","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahh i see. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi the example mymysh returns no command x for x at a sequence number 20 less than the highest sequence number. however for my history file i have saved all historical commands such that 1 to 999 can all be accessed providing they exist. do i have to make them not exist for max - 20. furthermore is it possible to create a differently named history file such as .mymysh_history new so that if prior versions of the history file with invalid syntax exists it does not effect your code thanks.","answers":[{"text":"the internal history and the history file should both only have a max of maxhist 20 items in them. history shouldn't stop at 999 either any positive integer should work.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i keep getting this error. i've commented some parts of my code out and it runs fine if i comment out my initcommandhistory function.","answers":[{"text":"you are trying to free unallocated memory. run gdb or valgrind to find where.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i was running cs1521/bin/mymysh lt command.txt gt exp for wc . command i found error message input redirection no such file or directory will be printed in terminal but not exp file all other message printed in file except this i have no idea about when it should be printed in terminal rather than in file can i get some hint about it","answers":[{"text":"if you want to capture all of the output from mymysh try the command cs1521/bin/mymysh lt command.txt gt exp 2 gt amp 1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"looks like that message is being printed to stderr not stdout. this is because this error is produced by perror not printf.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run ./mymysh lt test0 gt myout where test0 has cat lt doesntexist.c my program will have input redirection no such file or directory in the myout file. with the sample solution the out file doesn't have it but instead prints it to stdout. i have tried moving the printing of the error message inside the fork and outside but still doesn't reproduce the output of the sample solution. also when i run cd on my solution i get /import/glass/2/z5112735 on the sample solution i get /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/2/z5112735 is this difference significant","answers":[{"text":"on my solution i get /import/glass/2/z5112735 on the sample solution i get /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/2/z5112735 is this difference significant did you run both commands on the same machine","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i ran it on the same machine but i had opened two terminal windows","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"were the shells in both windows running on the same machine in any case the difference doesn't matter.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes the shells were running on the same machine. i tried it again with just one terminal and ran the same tests. the only difference was once again the result of cd . surprisingly when i cd in my own shell and then pwd the directory printed is /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/2/z5112735. so the only time i get the weird /import/glass/2/z5112735 is the result after calling the cd command i assume from what you're saying that this difference won't affect the autotesting of my shell then","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if the redirect isn't working on the sample then the sample is printing to stderr. you should end up in the same place. how are you getting the home directory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"they both seem to be the home directory ls providers the same result . i used the following command to goto home chdir getenv home","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"running make produces very strange errors which i don't understand nor know how to fix the white text is a cse machine and the green text is my mac. i have included history.h in mymysh.c and in history.c so i am not sure what the issue is. pls help","answers":[{"text":"why do you have a main function in history.o to me it looks like an issue with your history.o have you tried make clean and then make","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i had copy and pasted mymysh.c into history.c ... facepalm","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"include history.h included in both files mymysh.c amp history.c // otherwise you might need to download all the new files again. hope it helps mate.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"couple question about the sample shell 1. redirect input/output is not working for the build-in command pwd history in the sample shell but it is working for the normal shell in the linux system. so i choose to stick with the normal shell of linux is that ok 2. in the sample shell provided for command like ls gt abc since the stdout is redirect to the file part of command like running xxxxxxx... --------------------------- is also being redirected to the file as well so the stdout of the command left to be half of the ------------------- line and the return value which looks weird to me. so instead in my own shell i preserve the whole running---- part and only redirect the part that is produced by the command to the file is it okay to do that","answers":[{"text":"so i choose to stick with the normal shell of linux is that ok no. the spec asked you to implement a clone of the reference shell not a clone of the real shell.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"redirection should not work for inbuilts it's in the spec. only the outup of the command itself should be redirected that's a bug in the example.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi my code works well on terminal but when i am trying to put the output to file out.obs it have different output from what i have in terminal i can not figure out why. can i get some hint on that","answers":[{"text":"ls output output one file per line when not outputting to a terminal. this is intended behavior. the order is wrong because of buffering but this is the correct output for this assessment and the example program does the same.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"this is what my program ptint","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but my file even not print running /bin/ls ... -------------------- makefile b.txt cmd.txt history.h mymysh mymysh.o out.obs a.txt c.txt history.c history.o mymysh.c out.exp these lines which suppose to be printed. it works well in terminal i have no idea why it does not work when print to a file","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but my file even not print running /bin/ls ... -------------------- makefile b.txt cmd.txt history.h mymysh mymysh.o out.obs a.txt c.txt history.c history.o mymysh.c out.exp these lines which suppose to be printed. it works well in terminal i have no idea why it does not work when print to a file","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok so only two lines are missing running... and --------------------- this could be because your printing this inside the fork not before it. other than that i would need to see your code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes i do it inside the fork so we must do it before the fork but these things listed must be inside the fork print by execve function makefile b.txt cmd.txt history.h mymysh mymysh.o out.obs a.txt c.txt history.c history.o mymysh.c out.exp so how can we print that before fork i miss them as well","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"that is printed by ls and is being printed. at the top of the file one line for each item. and that is expected.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you very much dylan. i just have another 2 questions. 1.when we use history command the definitly $ cs1521/bin/mymysh will behave different from our owns. since the command stored in txt file is different. and that does not matter right 2. the struct returned in glob function are different for mac and cse serve one according to man i search on google almost all answers follows the mac one rather than cse one do we need to use the cse one and will the test run in this environment","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i don't quite understand your first question. you program needs to run on cse. use man in the cse server as your guide to glob .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"when we use ./mymysh lt command.txt gt out.obs cs1521/bin/mymysh lt command.txt gt out.exp diff out.obs out.exp command to check whether out output is same as the cs1521/bin/mymysh all other command will be fine exccept the h or history command the output for these two will be different since they have different history and create .mymysh_history file in different place so that is supposed to happen and does not matter right thank you in advance","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the history file is the same so that's not a problem the shell never prints its own path so that shouldn't be a problem either.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but when testing by ./mymysh lt command.txt gt out.obs cs1521/bin/mymysh lt command.txt gt out.exp diff out.obs out.exp they will not run at the same time so when we first run ./mymysh some history recorded and when we start to run cs1521/bin/mymysh some history have already recorded in the history file so if we run h command will we have different result thank you in advance","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run ./mymysh on terminal it returns no such file or directory can someone tell me why that happened please","answers":[{"text":"you need to run make first.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for redirect part we only need to handle lt and gt write to/read from we do not need to handle something like gt gt append right thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"you don't need to handle append no.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we make a copy of the trim function in history.c","answers":[{"text":"definitely. although as the history lines are in a known format you don't necessarily need it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i type into the given mymysh i get the .c files printed to terminal as well as some random symbols. i'm assuming this is a bug so should the correct output be 'invalid i/o redirection'","answers":[{"text":"gt gt isn't a recognized symbol so it is just passed to cat as a file name.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"o thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"should the sequence number still increment with an invalid command even if it is not saved to history i had assumed not but have just realised i'm not sure and this would definitely cause problems with my current implementation.","answers":[{"text":"i believe an invalid command does not increment the sequence number as it's not placed into history. you can check with the testing shell at cs1521/bin/mymysh","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what would be the directory that contains the .mymysh_history file i tried using $home/histfile but nothing seems to be created after i used the ls -a command in the home directory. are we supposed to use /histfile or something else instead thanks","answers":[{"text":"in your cse terminal type cd then pwd that should be your home directory. otherwise you can use this command to print out your home directory printf your $home is s n getenv home","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"got it thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i try to run my shell with an input redirection these problems don't exist when i run the shell and type commands in e.g. ./mymysh lt test the shell prompt gets randomly printed as seen in the mymysh$ right before the second set of lines for each call i read something online about needing to fflush stdout before forking to fix this . furthermore when i try to then output redirect e.g. ./mymysh lt test gt a not only are the lines jumbled similar to a previous forum post but i'm also missing the mymysh$ running xxx... as well as the first set of -------- . any help on this problem would be much appreciated.","answers":[{"text":"are you printing running ... and --------- inside your fork if so then that's your second problem. moving all prints before the fork will probably fix the first problem too.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep that fixed it why does it not work as expected when we print inside the fork","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the read and write execute commands section the spec says before the command it should show the full pathname of the command executable for a relative path ie ./test should it show that or the absolute path","answers":[{"text":"if it requires a path search then you print the full path. if you are given a relative path ie. starts with . or / then just print it as is.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"just on this point wouldn't something starting with / be an absolute path not a relative path. would it be more correct to say that in the case of this particular requirement of the assignment that a relative path is something that either starts with . or or contains but doesn't start with an / i am trying to clarify this so also i can be sure i achieve the correct outcome here. thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"true. if you are given a relative or absolute path print what your given. if you need to search path ie you'r given a command name only eg 'cat' then print the full path.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the clarification.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi is there some simple way to make execve function fail i want to test that case.","answers":[{"text":"try to run a normal text file with the executable bit set. chmod u x file.txt","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"do you mean this it seems like running well.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"dylan meant ... try to execute the file whose mode you changed ... try running file.txt","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi when i run that mysh got error message exec format error but sample got unknow type of executable i got the message from errno i have no idea about how to get the same error as sample","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"by the way what number should i return when execve fail i did exit errno should i do this","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the error is manually printed. exit 255","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh yeah i got it thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi. when i run command such as ls c or ls .c print out also ls cannot access .c no such file or dicrectory . can anyone help me please picture below. thanks","answers":[{"text":"are you using the glob function to expand .c","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes dylan","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"are you inserting the expanded file names back into the token string in place of c and .c before execve 'ing the ls command","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i have inserted the expanded file name command after execve the ls command. but i still get the same problem. thank you.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you're clearly not inserting the glob results into the token string because the command line arg you pass to ls is .c what you should be passing as args to ls is glob.c history.c mymysh.c ... etc.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for history.c are we allowed to change the arguments for some functions since if i change the arguments for some functions i need to change the history.h file as well. is that allowed thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"as you give history.h you can modify anything in either file.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i get something like this in $ cs1521/bin/mymysh as well as my own program. so this is acceptance right if there is no ' n' at the end of the file it will looks like it","answers":[{"text":"this just means the file is incorrectly formatted. this is the intended output.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when running the reference solution and redirecting the output to a file should the order of the output be changed","answers":[{"text":"are you outputting anything to stderr sorry this is the referance. idealy this probably shouldn't happen. it has to do with buffering. 'ls' is smart and knows then its outputting to a file and changes how it outputs mymysh isn't that smart. there is a work around but it's complicated and uncomfortable.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hey i'm still confused about what is expected for testing. for example test02 ls gt xyz cat lt xyz rm xyz on cse machine $ ./mymysh lt test02 gt myout $ cs1521/bin/mymysh lt test02 gt theirout myout mymysh$ running /bin/ls ... -------------------- -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ running /bin/cat ... -------------------- makefile history.c history.h history.o mymysh mymysh.c mymysh.o myout test01 test02 test02 amp testdir testhist testhist.c theirout xyz -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ running /bin/rm ... -------------------- -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ mymysh$ theirout makefile history.c history.h history.o mymysh mymysh.c mymysh.o myout test01 test02 test02 amp testdir testhist testhist.c theirout xyz mymysh$ running /bin/ls ... -------------------- -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ running /bin/cat ... -------------------- -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ running /bin/rm ... -------------------- -------------------- returns 0 mymysh$ mymysh$ as you can see the output of ls is written to the file at different times. does this mean i'll lose marks on the autotests should i change my program so that it behaves the same as the model solution shell at all times include output redirection of this form","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"your output is in the correct place so you won't lose marks. the example output is what i would expect because of buffering how did you fix that issue","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i got this output by using fflush stdout immediately after any text is written to stdout during the execution of main . is that ok","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"don't fflush. you are circumventing the buffering being done. the out of order order of output is expected when mymysh is redirected to a file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"gotcha thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"also not that 'ls' has different formatting when redirection to a file as well.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"a fix for this on your end it to run stdbuf -i0 -o0 -e0 cs1521/bin/mymysh lt etc gt","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"should we use this to run both the reference and our solution when redirecting the output to a file for testing","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if your running for testing don't use it. if your savings a session for debugging or just to look at then do.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"only if malloc/fopen fails etc","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"see my edit.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi the trim function is currently breaking when i enter no text i.e. no characters or a string of spaces as the last value moves to an illegal array index i.e. last -1. i should mention that this only occurs when compiling with dcc. gcc does not pick this up. i should note that i'm running dcc locally rather than on the cse machines due to the issue with the new c libraries breaking dcc. my question is is this considered acceptable behaviour seeing as gcc allows it and i get the desired outcome or should i be editing the provided trim function to check for this alternatively should i be checking for this before the trim function is called. ideally i would like the trim function to deal with all of this. edit i would like to keep using dcc as its error checking is really useful so i would ideally like to resolve this within the code. thanks joe","answers":[{"text":"this is a bug with trim . you can fix the trim function in your code to keep dcc quiet. that won't break auto-testing after you submit.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi are we able to assume that the .mymysh_history file already exists or are we required to create the file in history.c if it does not yet exist. thanks","answers":[{"text":"consider the case where you're running mymysh on a brand new computer for the first time . it wouldn't exist yet. so no don't assume it already exists and make checks to see if the file is there or not.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i run mysh if there is error the message will be like /bin/cat xxx no such file or directory but the example one will be cat xxx no such file or directory i think it makes sense since one of them is in the directory bin but the other not. should i do something to it or it's okay","answers":[{"text":"they're both in the directory /bin. one shell is displaying the complete command pathname the other is not. do whatever cs1521/bin/mymysh does","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"for execve args 0 args envp if args 0 is 'bin/cat' then you get the first for execve command args envp if command is 'bin/cat' and args 0 is 'cat' you get the latter.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"okay thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"memory leaks in sample solution i was wondering if we need to check memory leaks for our assignment i tried to check the memory leaks of the sample solution and spotted several does it mean we actually don't need to check memory leaks for our assignment","answers":[{"text":"we will check for memory leaks if it's easy but just to make the point not to dock marks. as dylan says you should not have memory leaks in your programs. do what i say not what i do.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"lol roger that my program doesn't have any leak though","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i don't know if memory leaks will lower marks but you should strive for none anyway.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello using the given mymysh i notice that i get different outputs when i run the programs - using given mymysh - using my mysh is this an error on my part that needs to be fixed or is there just a difference when run on different machines","answers":[{"text":"is this on the cse server","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi just wonder do we need to have exactly same error message as cs1521/bin/mymysh i think it's a bit hard to try all situations.","answers":[{"text":"as much as possible yes. anything else will cause auto tests to fail.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if i try to run an empty file that has execute permissions perror seems to print out exec format error and 0 is returned. however the sample prints unknown type of executable and 255 is returned. is this from perror or just from a print statement if it's from a print statement do we associate all execve failures with this error or only specific ones and use perror elsewhere","answers":[{"text":"that's from an explicit printf which is followed by return 255","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you i found it odd for it to print unknown type of executable even for permission denied errors however i will follow the sample.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if my shell is not reliably saving commands to commandhistory.commands i .commandline i.e. sometimes will leave them null would a possible reason be due to lack of pipelines forking etc so far i've only used pid fork for the process where i implement findexecutable - the rest of my shell built-in command history implementation is just while loops if statements together with functions i have written in history.c. are they sufficient for the shell command history or do i need to implement forks/pipelines there too thanks","answers":[{"text":"if my shell is not reliably saving commands to commandhistory.commands i .commandline i.e. sometimes will leave them null would a possible reason be due to lack of pipelines forking etc probably not. it sounds more like a problem with the way you're managing the memory in and around your commandhistory object.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i noticed in the shell will copy the previous command and any extroneous s are added onto the previous command. in the sample shell it doesn't do this - which implementation is advised i.e. if i enter cat i run the cat process if i subsequently enter do you want it so a we return an error as cat is not a valid process or b we run cat as per the sample shell","answers":[{"text":"mymysh isn't bash so don't model expectations off of it. for now go with running the last command as the example does but that may be a bug. the correct outcome is probably to error as is a valid inbuilts but or any other lengthed string of isn't.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"if i run cd /filename and cd username/filename will these lead to the same destination from what i understand represents the home directory and the path can be obtained by using getenv home . is this home the home directory for the user called username","answers":[{"text":"you can't cd to a file but cd will take you to your home directory cd username will take you to username's home directory eg. cs1521 you can use glob to expand check man 3 glob for the required flag.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"does that mean that if username corresponds to your username then cd and cd username will be the same but if username is another user's username then it will go to their home directory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"correct.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"out of nowhere this message comes out and ive been working on this assignment and this has never cam eup no matter how many testing ive done before weill ./mymysh ./mymysh /lib/i386-linux-gnu/libc.so.6 version glibc_2.27' not found required by ./mymysh","answers":[{"text":"on september 30th at 10 22pm someone replaced the 2.27 version of glibc with the 2.26 version on all of the cse systems. you need to recompile all sections of your assignment with the 2.26 version of glibc you need to make clean and then make - after that you will be able to use your ./mymysh","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"have you compiled your assignment make clean make","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeh i have","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"same problem here when i ran the sample solution it seems to be a system wide problem","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep error started from yesterday night","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i was trying to run cs1521/bin/mymysh but i get some error message /import/ravel/3/cs1521/bin/mymysh /lib/i386-linux-gnu/libc.so.6 version glibc_2.27' not found required by /import/ravel/3/cs1521/bin/mymysh did i accidentally unlink something or did i just wreck my own account","answers":[{"text":"on september 30th at 10 22pm someone replaced the 2.27 version of glibc with the 2.26 version on all of the cse systems. in order for people to use the sample solution now the staff will need to recompile the reference solution with the older version of the software or re-update back to version 2.27 of glibc","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"all i can see is from https //askubuntu.com/questions/421642/libc-so-6-v... . you don't have a high enough version of libc6 that is causing the error. from how to fix /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libc.so.6 version glibc_2.14' not found super user that means the program was compiled against glibc version 2.14 and it requires that version to run but your system has an older version installed. you'll need to either recompile the program against the version of glibc that's on your system or install a newer version of glibc the libc6 package in debian . so you just need to upgrade your libc6 package. all versions of ubuntu have at least version 2.15 because it's a faily important package reference . to upgrade it use these commands in a terminal sudo apt-get update sudo apt-get install libc6","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but there appears no sudo command on cse machine if use without sudo it shows permission denied.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i've same problem so it seems system wide.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank god thought i broke something. i used ldd /bin/bash linux-gate.so.1 0xf7743000 libtinfo.so.5 gt /lib/i386-linux-gnu/libtinfo.so.5 0xf76fa000 libdl.so.2 gt /lib/i386-linux-gnu/libdl.so.2 0xf76f5000 libc.so.6 gt /lib/i386-linux-gnu/libc.so.6 0xf7521000 /lib/ld-linux.so.2 0xf7744000 so the file exists. i'm checking online now","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"any particular fix for this still get the same issue","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are we allowed to alter the functions in history.c for example instead of char getcommandfromhistory int seqnum can we alter it to char getcommandfromhistory char command instead","answers":[{"text":"you can. but what exactly would you pass to your new function","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"don't know if i'm doing this horribly wrong but this function is for the seqno commands. so it takes 28 for example checks if there's a history entry with that sequence number and then returns the command line corresponding to that entry. is there something i am missing","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the is the command and 28 is the argument you don't need to pass the only the number.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so would my function be valid i trimmed off the ' ' command before passing it into the function","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sure would.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"great news thank you dylan d","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"error while sscanf'ing values into struct this sscanf is within a while fgets loop but i keep getting a runtime error and have been searching the net for a while now. help would be appreciated __ could it be because i didn't malloc for commandline","answers":[{"text":"its definitely because commandline isn't malloced","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you also - i have gotten away so far with not mallocing for seqnumber. is it recommended i do","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"seqnumber doesn't need to malloced because it's just an int.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is it okay to leave cleancommandhistory empty as it doesn't need to be freed","answers":[{"text":"clearcommandhistory needs to be implemented.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but what should i put in if the data structure i implemented doesn't need to be freed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the data structure will need to be freed as you are storing strings.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but since u offered maxstr so it can be declare in fixed size as a global temporary variable like this typedef struct _history_entry int seqnumber char commandline maxstr historyentry typedef struct _history_list int nentries int end historyentry commands maxhist historylist historylist commandhistory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok in that case you don't need a clearcommandhistory.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i'll just leave a comment then","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi did we have to implement a way to directly call clearcommandhistory","answers":[{"text":"clear command history is only used to free the memory used by the history struct just before exit.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so we didn't have toimplement a way for the user to clear the mymysh_history file","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if the user wants to clear the file they can rm it. no call to clearcommandhistory can be made by the user.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how to pass command to execve's second parameter hi i'm trying to solve seqno with execve hisarg here is the corresponding history command. but execve seems only start another mymysh process which doesn't take in hisarg as the command. so how could i let mymysh in the execve function run the command i specified hisarg if this is not the way we handle may i have a hint about it thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"the command you want to execve is hisarg 0 as that is the name of the program. also there are two errors in the tokens line you need to fix.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey. i was wondering whether it is 'ohkay' for my history entries to start from 0 instead of 1. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"no","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i think give cs1521 ass2 mymysh.c history.h history.c has a typo - from what i see it that should say assign2","answers":[{"text":"yep should be give cs1521 assign2 mymysh.c history.h history.c","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes i just had the same thought this afternoon.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"file not saving hi the assignment spec says to save the history into a file $home/.mymysh_history however when i try to use ./mymysh_history as the filename fopen is returning null. i am not sure why this is the case. how should i be creating/saving the file","answers":[{"text":"you can't use inside c programs. it is interpreted by the shell. you'll need to work out the full path name of the directory using the home environment variable. it's in envp or you can read up on the getenv library function . you can assume that this environment variable always has a value.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahh i see thank you i didn't know that. i tried to get the full path name and then append .mymysh_history onto it using strcat strcpy filename getenv home histfile but i was still receiving null which is why i resorted to trying to use . am i using the function incorrectly","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"as long as filename is malloced large enough that looks correct.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i increased the size of my char buffer however it still doesn't seem to be working the print statement for the path prints /import/glass/2/z5025097.mymysh_history and the saved message doesn't print so i believe the file isn't being created. any suggestions on what else might have gone wrong","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the problem is that you haven't got a '/' between the path and the file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you so much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what error message shall i print if the first command ever exit is a","answers":[{"text":"check the example rm /.mymysh_history start 1521 mymysh and run as the first command.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"shall i include the space in the / space .mymysh_history","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i don't think i added a space but no there shouldn't be a space.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have been reading previous posts about the showcommandhistory and savecommandhistory functions and am still somewhat confused. i know we can use these or write our own if we want but given they are in the skeleton program files i figure i should try and use them unless i come up with a reason why not to. maybe my confusion is around their names. unintuitively to me the showcommandhistory function takes a fd to output/save to where the savecommandhistory function does not though it seems to be it should the other way around based on the function names. previous posts mention showcommandhistory should be called from savecommandhistory but the assignment specs to me imply the savecommandhistory function is only called on exiting the shell to write the history to file. showcommandhistory on the other hand could need to be called many times when h/history is typed into the shell before exit so calling it from savecommandhistory on exit doesn't seem logical. is there something i am missing with my understanding of these two functions as at the moment i am not any clearer on their interaction and operation. thanks","answers":[{"text":"savecommandhistory can save by showing the command history to a file instead of the stdout.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks dylan so it would seem to me that the prototype for savecommandhistory would need to be modified to receive input to indicate if it should save to file or call showcommandhistory and have it output to stdout. the original function it doesn't take an argument but i think that would need to change to work as describe.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"savecommandhistory always writes to /.mymysh_history which is why it doesn't need an argument. showcommandhistory sends the history list somewhere ... the somewhere has to be indicated via an argument. maybe the name showcommandhistory suggests that it's going to display it to the screen but that's not the intention. maybe the name writecommandhistory would have been better ... or not ... then you'd probably complain that it gave the impression that it was meant to go to a file ...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"then you'd probably complain it was a question not a complaint and i think a valid one.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi simon jas was just giving a catch 22 statement p basically the showcommandhistory function puts its output into the file pointer argument it was given","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what kind of mode shall i open the redirecting file 777 or 700 or 770","answers":[{"text":"definitely not 7 that adds the execution bit and you'r making text files. the standard is 0644.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so that creating a file is not the more permissions the better why can t i use 666","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"look back on the lectures and tute for a full answer. 666 gives everyone on the system reading and writing permission on the file. 644 gives you read and write but everyone else read only.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi should ls output on a newline per entry since i iterate through a bunch of execve's using globlist.gl_pathv it does newlines every execve call . if not what should i do to get rid of the lines i tried printing b escape sequences but it wouldn't get rid of them...","answers":[{"text":"ls in mymysh should output exactly what it does in bash.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"how do you recommend i do this i am using execve so i looked at appending flags to the exec value so that it would be one line thinking of -c but since ls will print a n at the end whenever its executed no flags to stop it i am pretty much clueless as to how to stop execve printing a new line.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you should never need to modify flags. ls prints one entry per line if it's output is not a tty. are you using an output redirection on mymysh or on ls inside mymysh if you are then what's happening is the correct behaviour. if you aren't using output redirections anywhere then look for incorrect calls to pipe if you have any and dup2 .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i am not using any output redirections yet nor pipe or dup2 . my code is basically replace the command with the wildcard with the globlist output one by one and execve each one so obviously it is going to print a new line for each one as is the case for a normal execve . the only case i need to not newline is for when the command is ls not -l as for all other commands the output is the same as terminal's output.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"execve is only called once. after a glob expansion all the results are passed to execve at the same time.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"cmdno initcommandhistory i am not quite sure about the purpose of cmdno variable in main . which int value the initcommandhistory should return and what is cmdno used for can someone explain about it for me thanks","answers":[{"text":"initcommandhistory returns the smallest number greater than any previous history number. eg. if you have a history file that has 12 commands numbered 1-12 then 13 will be returned. if you load a history file that has 20 commands numbered 46-65 then 66 will be returned. if no history file is found then 1 is returned.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we need to handle symbols the sample seems to separate tokens on as well as space.","answers":[{"text":"dylan's right. quotes are not treated specially. i'm sure i addressed this somewhere maybe another comment thread but i'm surprised it's not somewhere in the spec .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the problem is that quotes are treated special they are removed. entering mymysh$ cat text file will actually run cat text file","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i believe the sample is incorrect. the spec doesn't note any special behavior for or ' so is handled like any other character.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"just asking out of curiosity. why is 'cd' command not stored in bin folder unlike other commands eg. mkdir cat etc. also cd - is not working in cs1521/bin/mymysh.i don't know if it's meant to be like that","answers":[{"text":"cd is a shell builtin. every shell bash zsh fish mymysh have there own way of storing environment variables and in particular the current working directory. our shell is piggy backing off of unix standards and uses the default method of storing and interacting with the environment. even if every shell stored and used the environment in the same way there are many other tasks shells have to perform when cd is called. globbing is only one way a path can be expanded other ways like regev and custom matching schemes could be used br different shells cd can have shortcuts bash allows naming directors in a global scope for quick switching to regularly used directories and many jump utility exist for custom path movement. in essence that's the real reason customization. path movement isn't a regulated thing and there are many schools of thaught about what's more efficient so different shells are allowed to do it in different ways. other utilities are very strictly regulated about how there task should be done so it makes sense to have one program that does it exactly as defined. the only common thing for path traversing is that after all processing is done the result is stored in the unix environment under pwd.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for history.c are we required to use every function prototype provided","answers":[{"text":"function prototypes are provided to serve as a guide. any function can be added removed or modified.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we need to implement options for the shell built-in commands","answers":[{"text":"inbuilts should work as described in the spec.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"so i'm testing out the sample executable and i'm wondering if a command including wildcards and redirection should work","answers":[{"text":"your example should work ok and now does work in the reference binary.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"this is a bug with the example. this and other commands like it should be allowed.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"sorry that this question might sound extremely stupid but can we put define histfile .mymysh_history on mymysh.c or history.h so that we can use it when we are using showcommandhistory file on mymysh.c","answers":[{"text":"the define is only needed in history.c but you can move it if you want to.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"wait if that define is only needed in history.c what's file pointer file outf for on showcommandhistory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"a call to showcommandhistory can be used to do most of the work of savecommandhistory","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run my code with valgrind i get a whole bunch of these errors. instead of showing the line numbers where the issue occurs it just provides three question marks. when i run the sample mymysh with valgrind the same issue occurs. is this something to worry about","answers":[{"text":"seems to be an ongoing issue with valgrind and dcc. unfortunate you will have to debug without for now.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey i was trying commands on the given mymysh and i noticed the following result should cat .s gt me.txt not work","answers":[{"text":"already reported. it is a bug and should be accepted.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"o right thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for saving history part we are asked to save the history in $home/.mymysh_history. i'm quite confused about the dot after '/'. what does that dot stand for i made a small program trying to create a file without the dot and it works and the file can't be created if the file name starting with a dot.","answers":[{"text":"you might think it didn't work because it's hidden run 'ls -a' to view hidden files as well.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"a dot file is a hidden file on a linux system. a file starting with a dot definitely can be created in c.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok that makes sense. thank you very much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are we allowed to modify the provided function prototypes","answers":[{"text":"there are no mandatory functions in the spec go for it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm a bit confused about error handling. it says that if the file does not exist or is not readable that is an error. having lt as the last token or elsewhere in the command-line is also an error. so if there is an error should we just print the error message and continue the while loop or just stop the mymysh if print message what function should we use perror thank you","answers":[{"text":"unless you encounter an unrecoverable error like malloc running out of memory you should continue the while loop but print an message. you can only use perrot is a syscall fails otherwise use fprintf.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"why should we use fprintf can we just use printf","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if you want to output to stderr then you need to use fprintf. it's not mandatory but in extream debugging cases it can help having errors separate.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi i wonder if we can use perror. if not why","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"perror reports an error if errno is set. errno is set by a failed system call. a system call is anything in man 2. read the man page of functions and if they say on error return -1 and set errno. then you can use perror immediately after to report an error. otherwise use fprintf.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"just in case anyone else freaks out i think dcc might be segfaulting everything at the moment","answers":[{"text":"yes as well as valgrind.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is the valgrind as well as dcc and dcc --leak-check in vlab broken now even when i try to printf hello n . when i run valgrind ./hello it says some uninitialized memory access.","answers":[{"text":"don't use valgrind and dcc together they do the same thing. use dcc for run time checks then gcc and valgrind for a final profiling.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but i still believe something wrong with valgrind since when i run this simple program with gcc valgrind the reaction is unbelievable. and now when i run all my previous programs with valgrind the same error message will occur","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for pwd can we assume the cwd is maxline 200 chars long","answers":[{"text":"read the man page on getcwd. it tells you about size.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i've been stuck on this error when i compile. i'm not quite sure what the error is telling me.","answers":[{"text":"you have included unistd.h in mymysh.c but using chdir in history.c so it needs to be included there too.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do the errors we create such as invalid i/o redirection and command not found go to stdout or stderr i believe the model solution sends them to stdout so that's what i've done but i feel like they should go to stderr.","answers":[{"text":"as long as the error is the same the output stream dosen't matter stdout and steer can be merged later.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi this is about displaying the history of file expansion my code displayed the official code displays does this count as inconsistent output","answers":[{"text":"if the example saves the command as it was before globbing so should you.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in a dir with multiple .c files i execute the following with the model solution shell mymysh$ wc .c gt xyz invalid i/o redirection is this intended behaviour confused because the model shell doesn't complain about this mymysh$ wc mymysh.c testhist.c gt xyz running /usr/bin/wc ... -------------------- -------------------- returns 0","answers":[{"text":"a glob pattern before a redirection is allowed. the model solution is incorrect.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we get marked down if we got memory leaks","answers":[{"text":"only if the reference mymysh has no memory leaks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i also wonder if there is a error why sometimes the program return 1 and sometimes the program return 2. what is the difference between them thanks","answers":[{"text":"the printed return value should be returned by the executing process. what the actual values is changes depending on the program.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is the value get from wait but my program get different value to the cs1521/bin/mymysh one. it will have some value like 11 or 512 rather than 1 or 2","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the spec tells you how to do this wexitstatus","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you very much and i have another question. for redirect files if we have a pattern match eg cat lt .txt as i was told before it should return an error message but i have tried the cs1521/bin/mymysh it will not return an error but process it with the file file matched so should we print a error message or not. if so what message should we print","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if .txt expands to more than one file name it should complain. cs1521/bin/mymysh is currently doing it wrong. it should be treated as if you had done cat lt a.txt b.txt the error message should be invalid i/o redirection","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so will it eg. cat lt .txt be recorded in history or not","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"only valid commands are recorded. 'cat lt .txt' is valid if it expands to only one file and is invalid if it expands to multiple.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i wonder can we have some autotest to make sure we do not have silly mistakes including format n space... thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"once i've finished writing an assignment for my other course i'll put up some testing stuff. however but this stage you ought to be able to do testing yourself ... e.g. write a sequence of shell commands in a file then do something like ./mymysh lt fileofcommands gt out.obs cs1521/bin/mymysh lt fileofcommands gt out.exp diff out.obs out.exp after all this is what we do for auto-testing.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello two relatively generic questions this time not asking for details at this stage . 1. is the i/o redirection any different to the method covered here https //webcms3.cse.unsw.edu.au/comp1521/18s2/reso... 2. seeing as though the command output is only worth 1 mark is there really any major difference between that and the input case thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"output redirection is very similar to input redirection a more accurate marking guild would be 2 marks for either input or output redirection and an additional 1 mark for the other. there is a small difference as you are redirecting from a file to a process not from a process to another process. because of this you don't need pipe s only dup2 s","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"cool thanks dylan. although the spec seems to hint at pipe as well as dup2 though. was that bit extra or was it for something else","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"pipe is only needed for the challenge.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so to clarify do you need to pipe at all or only for output redirection oliver.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"pipe is not needed for in/output redirection.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ah right. thanks again for all the hard work answering these questions","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry also 3. for our purposes shell commands will never be i/o redirected right","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"inbuilts like cd history and pwd will never be redirected.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i think i've gotten my history implementation working except that when i call getenv home for a second time eg to save to the mymysh_history file it returns a different path to the first time i call it. i use the following code and call it when opening and when saving the command history file. the first time i run this homedir is /import/ravel/4/zxxxxxxx/ . the second time when trying to write to history file homedir is /import/ravel/4/zxxxxxxx/.mymysh_history/ . how the heck is that possible it's almost as if the home environment is being modified during my code execution to become... a random file is there any way that could happen","answers":[{"text":"it's not a random file that is the history file. if you are modifying the return of getenv in place then the next time getenv is called your modification stays.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so if i change the string that getenv gives to me it'll change the home path too","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"concatenate the history file name on a copy of the home env var.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is there a better way to do that than mallocing a string and strcpy newstring getenv home also when i try to cd to the home i get a problem that my directory is set at the home for the rest of the shell run regardless of me running cd somewhereelse . would that be caused by the same issue of not using a copy of the getenv home string","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"is there a better way to do that than mallocing a string and strcpy newstring getenv home no. why do you think that's not a good way to do it assuming you make the buffer big enough which means malloc'ing strlen enough to append the name of the history file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm still not used to c string manipulation so everything looks messy and horrible and i usually assume there's a better way to do it than i do it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"not quite. the memory location used as the return of getenv is always the same. if you modify what's at that location you modify what you get back next time.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"extra feature i've implemented both input and output redirection however i've also handled the case of both input and output redirection in the same command e.g wc lt infile gt outfile . this is how bash/dash etc behave and more than the spec asks for will that be a problem thanks in advance.","answers":[{"text":"deleted","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no problem thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it will be a problem if one of our test cases checks for this and expects to see an error. submit a version that precisely meets the spec. anything beyond this is a private thing that you can use to impress your tutor.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi is the sequence number and the command number the same thing or whats the difference between them also initcommandhistory returns an integer what would it be thanks","answers":[{"text":"yep they're the same. initcommandhistory returns the first sequence number greater than any already used.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello any advice on testing filename expansion i know i can do cd ls .c and ls on the sample solution but that's the extent of my knowledge. thanks","answers":[{"text":"have a look at 'man 7 glob' all the examples should work as you are using the glob function. also try /filename and username/filename.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi just wondering what should be the environment of ./mymysh and how should i type it in the command line because i am getting this error when trying to run thanks for any help","answers":[{"text":"what kind of machine are you running this on","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"my own laptop lenovo thinkpad..","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"running windows","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes my laptop is win10. but running this on vlab linux.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hmmm ... strange ... i just tested cs1521/bin/mymysh on vlab vx4 and it worked ok. does cs1521/bin/mymysh work what does the command echo $path show","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes cs1521/bin/mymysh works fine. echo $path shows","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"did you change any variables before your code reached this point line 66 what did you change and how did you change it","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no i don't think so. the only thing i did was to cat history.c mymysh.c gt exe.c and run gcc on exe.c if this counts. also i have tried to import history.c instead of history.h but i have changed it back to history.h when i ran the code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's a dcc thing gcc works fine. https //gist.github.com/dylan-brotherston/41acb999...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"off topic but you should run 'make' with c source code catting was only for mips code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh didn't notice this. thanks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i am having this error as well i am very sure i haven't changed anything my code runs happily in cygwin on windows but not in the vnc environment i get the exact same error the only change that i believe may be relevant is i changed the make file to make in dcc rather than gcc.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i believe clang dosn't allows for envp as a thired argument to main dcc uses clang so try using gcc instead.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok cool thank you","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's a dcc thing gcc works fine. https //gist.github.com/dylan-brotherston/41acb999...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i tried gcc and it shows this cannot open file the segmentation fault thing may be my own bug. but what about the no such file or directory thing","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"also please use the makefile.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"probably coming from trying to open .mymysh_history incorrectly.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"got it thanks for your help.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am getting this error when i submit but it compiles fine using the makefile given","answers":[{"text":"which host did you run the give command on","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it was on a cse machine but it seems to be working now when i submitted again","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"does our mymysh_history file have to only store the last 20 commands or can it store more all history and have the showhistory function only print the last 20 thanks","answers":[{"text":"don't care. as long as it only holds the last 20 internally i'm not fussed what's in the history file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"are we allowed to read from the mymysh_history to get the past commands e.g. the last 17 from the last session and store the current session commands e.g. the 3 in the current session in the buffer the result of running history would still be the correct 20 commands.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if there are less than 20 commands in the history file load them up and start adding future commands to the historylist. if there are at least 20 commands in the history file load the most recent 20 in the historylist and start replacing the oldest command each time you enter a new command.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi using the sample mymysh is possible to do shell redirection with multiple files cat lt history. ch which works like the bash shell but when a similar command is given cat lt history.c history.h the following error is returned invalid i/o redirection do we need to match this functionality or can we assume that redirection will not be tested with filename expansions as the specification states that the last command line should be a filename","answers":[{"text":"only one file can be given to a redirect. if a glob pattern expands to more than one file then it should be an error. the mymysh example actually only works with the first file even if two are given from a glob.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the clarification dylan","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello. i'm sure this has been asked already so sorry for potential repost just can't find it. for i/o redirection are we assuming that we're only ever reading/writing from one file and never doing both at the same time as well the shell mymysh looked like it was doing that. thanks","answers":[{"text":"correct only one of lt or gt is allowed at a time.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what should the showcommandhistory file function in history c do the comment above the function is not completed.","answers":[{"text":"print the contents if the history structure to the file provided.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i am using fprintf in my showcommand function. if that is the case can i just call the showcommandhistory function inside the savehistoryfunction","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you can yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"clang error unable to execute command executable ld doesn't exist clang error linker command failed with exit code 1 use -v to see invocation make mymysh error 1 i get this error when i want to submit it but when i make the file on my own computer it compiles properly. what is this trying to say","answers":[{"text":"nothing is wrong with your code. just wait for the submission to be fixed.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we assume the gt or lt is not a valid file name","answers":[{"text":"you can yes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what does inithistory return the function says it returns 'cmdno' but what exactly is 'cmdno'","answers":[{"text":"part of what initcommand reads are the sequence numbers for the commands. it returns the next sequence number i.e. one more than the largest number in the history that it just read in .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"by the way when initcommand is run do the sequence numbers of the commands start back at 0","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i see i see thanks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"when you read the .mymysh_history file each command will have its number. return the largest number 1 wa that is the number of the next command to be executed.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey. does 'nentries' refer to the number of entries in the buffer that are not empty or does it refer to the number of entries that have already been added to the history even if they have been removed from the buffer . follow up question when initialising the commandhistory are we supposed to assume that there are 0 entries in the beginning before reading the file such that the number of entries after the file has been read in will the number of commands in the file. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"i used it as the number of entrys in the array. but you can use it however you like. inithistory is the first thing done by the shell. so you can assume that there are no commands in history.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahh thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello is there some special catering we must do if for some reason our history goes past the 999th command i.e. into 4 digit numbers thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"no. amway use the same format. i doubt that testing will go on long enough for this to matter.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"why doesnt .mymysh_history act like a proper file i cant fscanf from it or fgets from it even though i cat it i see theres content ive written on it","answers":[{"text":"the .mymysh_history file needs to be in your home directory as given by the home environment variable if the file is at $home/.mymysh_history it also needs to be opened with fopen $home/.mymysh_history r but $home needs to be expanded into a path first.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"where does $home come from what is it i assume it's some sort of absolute path to the current user's home file but i don't remember it being covered yet.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you can find it in the environment.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i haven't seen week 9's lectures yet are environment variables covered there or somewhere else","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"not sure. they were covered in week08 lab and tute.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"iirc our tute mostly skimmed over them since we could just pass in the envps we got from main. is there another source of info for the 1521 course you know of that i could look through","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"not really sure chech week07/08 lecture notes. and also the answers to the week08 tute. also 'man getenv'.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how many of these cd variants do we need to code i know chdir handles .. for you but some of the others behave rather strangely cd username and straight cd for example. oliver.","answers":[{"text":"try them on the provided executable at '1521 mymysh' and see what works and what doesn't.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i deleted a comment on an old post i made because i realised that it doesn't bump it back to the top so i'm just making a new post. original discussion lt header gt rui tong 4 days ago last modified 4 days ago lt /header gt i'm currently looking at the showcommandhistory function and basically i gather that i'm reading from a file pointer to the .mymysh_history file . is there really any purpose for doing this because when i look at the assignment i feel like it'd be much simpler to just store everything in the already defined global struct variable commandhistory and then read from that instead for the show function. and then call savecommandhistory before the program quits. whereas from what i see in this current implementation every time i want to add to my history i need to always store it in commandhistory and then write it out to .mymysh_history. which feels like i always need to write to 2 different places at once the struct and the file. thanks. lt header gt john shepherd 4 days ago last modified 4 days ago lt /header gt showcommandhistory writes to the file handle.this allows you to double up using it interactively for the h command and to save the command history to the .mymysh_history fiile. lt footer gt reply lt /footer gt lt header gt rui tong 4 days ago lt /header gt hang on sorry about this jas but in that case what's the distinguishing factor between showcommandhistory and savecommandhistory lt footer gt reply edit delete lt /footer gt lt header gt john shepherd 4 days ago lt /header gt savecommandhistory could be implemented very easily using showcommandhistory lt footer gt reply lt /footer gt deleted reply sort of thanks jas although i'm now wondering about this. from my understanding i may have misinterpreted but my understanding is that savecommandhistory call s showcommandhistory to ensure that showcommandhistory does the writing for me. but if my shell wants to exit now this is going to be problematic because the last thing i want is for my shell to print out a history log right before it exits. is there any way i can overcome this thanks","answers":[{"text":"and to clarify any and all functions can be edited added or removed. its recommended to call showcommandhistory from savecommandhistory but you don't need to.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahh i see your point now. we can send it to stdout or send it to some file we made in save. thanks dylan","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"showcommandhistory only outputs to one place. the place given by the file argument.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i try cat lt .txt command at cs1521/bin/mymysh i found that only the first matched txt file will be matched does that mean we only need to match the first file in the redirect command thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"only one file can be redirected into or out of. cat lt .txt should be an error as only one file is allowed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"since it is really hard to let stdin/stdout to point to several file descriptors at same time.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi since we need to print the return 0/1 at the end for this situation mymysh$ cat xyz running /bin/cat ... -------------------- cat xyz no such file or directory -------------------- returns 1 although it will print no such file or directory but it is not a error. so we can not get the error message from the child process. can i get some hints of how i know the child process goes wrong somewhere so that i will know i should return 1 rather than 0 thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"read man 2 wait.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how many commands do we record in the current shell instance history the assignment spec says 20 but jas said 50 in the lecture. also could someone explain to me the difference between the permanent record of command history and the instance history like do we on closing the shell save the current temporary history into this permanent file then when the shell next runs use that history as the current instance history as well does the permanent command history file only hold 20/50 commands at a time also if we start overwriting the oldest command in the temporary command history list is the new command sequence 21/51 or does it become 20/50 and all undeleted commands have their sequence reduced by 1 with the current sequence 1 command being deleted finally for now is pipe handling a challenge component or a requirement in the lecture it seemed to be phrased as a requirement but the spec says it's a challenge. edit are the commands h and history recorded in the history","answers":[{"text":"20 commands are in history. there is a defined constant in the history.c file that has the correct number. when the shell starts if a history file exists it is loaded into memory inside the shell. when the shell executes a correct command the command is added to the internal history if there are more than 20 in history the least recent command is removed from history. when the shell is shutdown the internal history is saved into the history file overwriting whatever is in there. command history starts a 1 if there isn't a file to read. then always increases by one for each command. 1 2 3 ... 19 20 21 ... 100 101 102 ... pipes are not required by the shell. only input or output redirection. always go by the spec. above jas above me above supplied code.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"does the program need to handle multiple redirects for example cmd lt cmd gt cmd or can i assume that there will be 1 redirect","answers":[{"text":"if you try it on the provided executable '1521 mymysh' and you'll see that only one of lt or gt is accepted at a time.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i wonder if there is specific requirement of the format of the return value of the char filenameexpand char tokens function if not will this function be individually test how it will test and can i not use this function if i can use other way to handle the pattern match/glob case if so what should be the format thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"to my knowledge no functions will be individually tested. you can add as many functions as you want to either mymysh.c or history.c/.h","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"and i can also not use some of the function which already added and need me to fill for example if i think i can implement my shell to expand all file names without using char filenameexpand char tokens function i can just not use it. as long as i can get the right output i can still get the mark for lt dl gt lt dt gt expand filename wildcards 2 marks part i can delete that function which already written for me and want me to implement with //todo in the file that i submit","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"as long as your shell does it it doesn't matter how.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we need to handle several pattern match by using glob in one command which means we need to have a array of glob_result","answers":[{"text":"yes. multiple arguments might have to be globed. glob returns a struct with a gl_pathv for you. read man 3 glob for info on the struct and how to glob multiple things.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"since if the pattern matched is one we can simply replaced but if pattern matched greater than one we need to have a loop. so will we have 2 or more like .txt in one command that means we will have several gl_pathv i am not to sure how to handle this case.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you need multiple calls to glob but only one glob_t steuct. read the man page it has info about calling glob multiple times.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but if i use append all the path will be append in one struct if i have 3 argv token contains when i actually run the command does that mean i need to have 3 loops to loop through all the command","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"there is no problem with having all paths in one struct.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is the interaction between filename expansion and io redirection running echo hello gt .txt in the sample program when test1.txt and test2.txt exist in the current directory writes hello to test1.txt and leaves test2.txt empty. this seems inconsistent with the spec as after filename expansion the tokens in the command line would be echo hello gt test1.txt test2.txt so gt is not the 2nd last token and so this should instead be an error","answers":[{"text":"file name expansion should not happen after lt or gt . only one file can be given.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i've noticed something with both the sample program and my own mymysh.c when i try to execute gedit mymysh.c sometimes the shell just have no reactions after executing the command unless press control z or c . but when i try to run gedit mymysh.c amp aonther text file ' amp ' will be created. how can i fix this","answers":[{"text":"graphical programs won't be run under mymysh. there is a lot of hacks and tricks used to make them work. now amp is a shell builtin like gt or lt as your shell doesn't do anything with this like bash does it is simply passed to the called program.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i wonder for void showcommandhistory file outf function if the outs already open and is what this function does quite similar to void savecommandhistory both these 2 functions do is to write the content to the file thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"void savecommandhistory saves the contents of the history structure to the file $home/.mymysh_history. this can be done with a call to showcommandhistory void showcommandhistory file outf prints the contents of the history structure to a specified file stream outf.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so the file stream 'outf ' have already been opened before it is passed into the function all i need is to write things to the function and i do not need to close the file stream inside the function void showcommandhistory file outf thank you in advance","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it needs to be opened before the function call yes. showcommandhistory uses the file stream only.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"and the contents are the same","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"does the ordering of the commands in the mymysh_history file have to exactly match the ordering when history is displayed although individual commands are stored in the same format as when displayed they happen to be ordered in the reverse order.","answers":[{"text":"the file should be in ascending order the same as the history command.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i also wonder what should be returned by int initcommandhistory is that int nentries inside the struct","answers":[{"text":"as i was told the other day it returns nentries 1 ie. the sequence number of the next command. thats why its return value is assigned to the variable cmdno in main .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will command change internal order of history for example if i have a history recording 0 cd 1 ls 2 cat xxxxx then i used 1 which corresponds to 0 cd. will cd enter the queue so that it looks like 0 cd 1 cd ... or keep consistent as before thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"what does cs1521/bin/mymysh do","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry didn't fully read the specification","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have a problem about give why when i run give it says that executable 'ld' doesn't exit i can guarant my code could complie with make.","answers":[{"text":"'ld' is the program used to combine .o files in your submission by clang. this isn't a problem with your code. it will be fixed soon.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have a question about the mode of open path mode . in the redirection part of the assignment if i want to write to a file how can i guarant that i can overwrite everything in the file not just the first few lines","answers":[{"text":"open is actually open path flags mode read 'man 2 open' for the full list of flags but the o_trunc is one of the flags you need.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have a problem about the execve command. why after i try to redirect a command i suddenly blow up the disk quota of vlab.","answers":[{"text":"what command","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"execve ls and redirect to hello","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"and after that the folder occupy 60 of my total memory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"any increase in ram should only last for the duration of the ls command and it should only be a small increase.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if you don't close after dup2 correctly then all output can start going to your file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"can the fork blow up memory i only fork before the actull exe","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"a fork-bomb can blow up memory but that requires each forked process to also call fork .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes i've just fixed the bug which is a fork bomb this morning. but how can i reduce the memory currently there's only 1.6 mb in that folder. but the quota is still reach the limit.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"memory ram or storage disk","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i ve already clean up the file during help sessions.thankyou","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"a fork will at most double the memory ram used. after the exec then you have the memory of that new process instead of a second copy of your own program.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm currently looking at the showcommandhistory function and basically i gather that i'm reading from a file pointer to the .mymysh_history file . is there really any purpose for doing this because when i look at the assignment i feel like it'd be much simpler to just store everything in the already defined global struct variable commandhistory and then read from that instead for the show function. and then call savecommandhistory before the program quits. whereas from what i see in this current implementation every time i want to add to my history i need to always store it in commandhistory and then write it out to .mymysh_history. which feels like i always need to write to 2 different places at once the struct and the file. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"showcommandhistory writes to the file handle. this allows you to double up using it interactively for the h command and to save the command history to the .mymysh_history fiile.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hang on sorry about this jas but in that case what's the distinguishing factor between showcommandhistory and savecommandhistory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"savecommandhistory could be implemented very easily using showcommandhistory","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how can i create the history file in the home. currently when i try open or fopen home/.history will always fail and error says no such file or director","answers":[{"text":"$home is an environment variable that needs to be expanded either with getenv or by a search of envp .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there a small mistake in the redirection command of the sample program when i run cat lt try_2 try_3 the two file are in my own directory it actully cat try_2 however according to the definition of the assignment having lt as the last token or elsewhere in the command-line is also an error. this case should produce an error not directly taking the argument next to lt as the file name also like wc -l try_2 gt try_3 try_4 try_5 the output is in the try_3 but not an error.","answers":[{"text":"fixed. new mymysh installed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"correct. only one file name is allowed.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the history file when i run the cat command on it shall it be exactly the same farmat as the one i print in the stdout or i could update it only when the program actually finishes.","answers":[{"text":"the .mymyh_history file is updated by savecommandhistory and that is only called right at the end.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so when i cat the mymyh_history file shall it be the same format as the history in the stdout","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if you are in mymysh and you cat the file it should look like it did before you started your session. only after you type exit will the file be updated. but the format is the same yes. 3d s n .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so can i assume that it is only updated when someone press exit for example when i press control c and terminate the process the records in the history_list will just disappear","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"only exit and d will update history. if mymysh is terminated with c then the history file stays as if the current session didn't happen.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have 2 questions about redirect. can i assume that the redirect command always have the last 2 token as gt and a filename and reditrct input command always have the first 2 token as lt and a filename and for the redirect do we need to consider cases with mumltiple pairs of lt gt","answers":[{"text":"no you could just get a command then a gt with no filename. the last two tokens are either lt filename or gt filename both input and output redirection is not allowed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"should input be the first two token and should this type of command needed to be consider inputfile lt ./sort gt outputfile. and what is the meaning of getting a command then gt with no filename","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"see my other post. input or output redirection is always after the command. gt with no filename is an error.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"there are 3 possible correct formats for a input line. command arg... command arg... lt filename command arg... gt filename where arg... means optionally one or more arguments. only 1 is correct for inbuilts. everything else is incorrect in some way.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeah thanks so this shell is different from the one in vlab even if redirect input we need to put lt file name at the back.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what shell on vlab all shells i know of need redirects after commands.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh i made a mistake but will this kind of command considered for this assignment like the command used in 2521 lab time sort -n lt /tmp/nums gt /dev/null","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"as i said only one redirect will be used either lt /tmp/nums or gt /dev/null but not both.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks so much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"reference program is returning two status codes exec is an empty executable file","answers":[{"text":"hi andrew the sample program has been fixed mymysh$ ./test running ./test ... -------------------- ./test unknown type of executable -------------------- returns 255 mymysh$ exit bash$","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the return code from an empty program should be 0 not 255. looks like jas isn't killing a forked process correctly so there are two returns. there should of course only be one return printed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hm it looks like a bash thing actually. tried it in zsh and i get the error code 126. bash is probably running the file as a bash script","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"and that's just a zsh thing. per posix there is no defined behaviour when an empty file is executed. bash just runs it as a script and zsh errors out with a 'file was not executable' it's undefined behaviour as jas is returning 255 you should do the same.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the same is true for any non shebanged script file jas's implementation will break you should not break and return 255. for now. jas may have an update once he fixes the problems.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when shall a filename expansion happen for a character can the be used as the middle of a file expansion for example ls -l hello cs1521","answers":[{"text":"must always be the first char in a path.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so in this case i can just glob and move on","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep. that is as long as you check globs return for errors.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so in what case involves shall i remove some part of the path name i'm getting really confused. for example if i do wc -l zid/cs1521/week07/ .c the actull command saves the path name but when i do wc -l .c the output removes the path name","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"sorry yifan i don't follow.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it is like for the same directory wc -l zid/cs1521/week07/ .c the correct output will be home/zid/cs1521/week07/a.c home/zid/cs1521/week07/b.c etc. but if i'm in the directory and do wc -l .c the output would be a.c b.c so my question is in what case the path name obtained by glob should be removed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"for zid/cs1521/week07/ .c first glob resolves the . then every file in home/zid/cs1521/week07/ that matches .c is found and the full path is return as the full path is given. for .c every file in the current directory as found by getcwd that match .c is found and the relative path from the current directory is returned. you can then get the current path from getcwd or from pwd in envp. and strcat each result onto a copy of it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"then can i assume that home is the largest directory every other directory comes from home","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"/ is the root directory. every absolute path starts with / a relative path starts with anything else.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i finally understand.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"should error messages be sent to stderr or stdout","answers":[{"text":"unless specified it doesn't really matter. debugging and logging can be easier if errors go to a different place than normal output. but in this case it's is entirely up to you.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when a command fails and needs to print an error message how to remove the /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2/ in perror i mean instead of showing wc /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2/ c no such file or directory how can i just show wc c no such file or directory with perror","answers":[{"text":"dylan is right in his comments about perror. i assume that this output is coming from your attempt at mymysh and not the reference solution. did you use glob to do the expansion i just tested this command on the reference solution and got jas williams cs1521/bin/mymysh mymysh$ wc c running /usr/bin/wc ... -------------------- wc c no such file or directory -------------------- returns 1 mymysh$ which is what i would have expected.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the only difference is that instead of printing wc c no such file or directory my out put is after the call to execve function wc /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2// c no such file or directory","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it appears that you are just appending c onto the end of the current path or just giving c to wc. jas mentioned the glob function. the file path needs to be parsed by the glob function in order for special chars like to be expanded. edit let me rephrase. i assume you are entering something like this mymysh$ wc c and you then tokenise this line into wc c . at the moment it looks like you are just calling execve wc wc c envp now c has no special meaning to wc so wc is just appending c onto the end of the current path the current path is pwd in envp. and is /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2/ this is where the error comes from. to get this working properly c needs to be transformed into an absolute path so that wc does't append it to pwd. to do this use the glob function. then pass the globed path as the second argument like so execve wc wc /home/username/c envp where /home/username/c was returned from glob c .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"do you mean that not only the args the path must also be expanded","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"see my edit.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"deleted","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi yifan that's a bit to much code for the forum please delete that and send me an email.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"perror is only used when a system call fails ie. something found in man 2. perror then generates an error message based on errno. for other errors like not finding a command use fprintf to stderr. if you are running wc and wc is producing wc /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2/ c no such file or directory then that means that wc is getting /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2/ c as its second argument.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i understand that wc is getting /tmp_amd/cage/export/cage/2/z5173587/cs1521/assign2/ c as the second argument however currently the file pass of execve file arg envp should be the one above. is it possible to let the eveve print a different error message like something begin with wc c.....","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is .mymysh_history","answers":[{"text":"a file in the home directory of the current user of mymysh that is read on startup of mymysh is created on exit of mymysh holds the current users command history of mymysh","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in the sample output after h is executed it would be added as 31 and 11 will be discarded. shouldn't it make more sense to output 12 - 31 so the user doesn't even get visual feedback about 11 no point in knowing that command if you can't use it","answers":[{"text":"mymysh executes commands before they are added to the history because only valid commands are added. this has the side effect that showing history shows the history as it was before the current command.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"could it be implemented differently thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it could have been but this aspect won't be changing. mymysh is not bash and doesn't need to behave exactly like bash .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"history substitution is this valid","answers":[{"text":"it probably shouldn't be. you can implement it however you like. we won't include it in our testing.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we have to malloc for the strings or just put the maxstr as string size in the struct since it is very difficult to read from the file when the string is dynamically allocated. the address cannot be guaranteed to be the same for each run.","answers":[{"text":"dynamic allocation is only relevant while the shell is running. you should be writing the string not a pointer to the string into the history file.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so you mean that malloc is not necessary in the history.c","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no. that's not what i meant.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but when write fd amp current_history sizeof historyentry the one written to the file is always a pointer how can i instead writting the string","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"open the history file using fopen rather than open and then use fprintf to write stuff into it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"communication","answers":[{"text":"communication.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"should we be using the same error messages provided in the sample program or will it be fine if we type our own error messages","answers":[{"text":"use the same messages. including the same spacing and upper/lower-case characters. you can use your own error messages if you don't care about failing auto-testing.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how should we get the return value from sub-processes i used wexitstatus on the wstatus given by wait but this gave 1 for the command cat xyz where the file xyz doesn't exist whereas the sample output and sample executable both show 256 as the output. should i multiply all return values by 256","answers":[{"text":"i didn't use wexitstatus ... but i think i should have ... i'll change the executable and the spec to reflect this.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what should initcommandhistory return the number of history entries","answers":[{"text":"the first history number to use ie if you run ./mymysh and run 5 commands then close mymysh the next time it is run the history numbers start at 6 so initcommandhistory returns 6.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"once there are 20 commands in history is the most recent command always number 20 or do the command numbers keep rising forever","answers":[{"text":"the history number is always increasing. but only the last 20 need to be remembered.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the cd command should we take directories with spaces into account","answers":[{"text":"no spaces are only used as argument seperators.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we need to save the $home/.mymysh_history in the same format as the sample executable or are we allowed to make up our own format","answers":[{"text":"same format. the only format that you're allowed to fiddle with is the internal format of the history list.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can shell built-ins be redirected for example is h gt history.txt a valid command this would imply that shell built-ins would need to be handled after redirection was applied.","answers":[{"text":"no. they can't be redirected.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"does the command history file only contain the most recent 20 entries or everything","answers":[{"text":"only the most recent 20 entries. since you can't see more than that there's not much point storing them.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the sample program seems to start sequence numbers in the command history at 2 is this correct","answers":[{"text":"no ... it's not correct ... and it's now fixed. it's not going to fix any old .mymysh_history files that start counting at 2 but if you remove the file and restart mymysh it should start counting from 1.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are all command lines max 200 characters or do we have to dynamically allocate char lines to store into history","answers":[{"text":"if the spec doesn't say that you have to dynamically allocate command line strings for the history then you don't. i think the data structures i gave you assumed that you would dynamically allocate command lines for the history but you can change those data structures if you want.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am not sure if i am using the right command but running cs1521/bin/mymysh gives me a no such file or directory error.","answers":[{"text":"ooops ... forgot to put the executable there ... it's there now","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the challenge what are some examples of hostnames and ip addresses with aliases to check if my program is working correctly","answers":[{"text":"172.217.25.46 has some","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the give command line given to submit in the assignment 2 specification is not correct it should be give cs1521 assign2 mymysh.c history.h history.c rather than give cs1521 ass2 mymysh.c history.h history.c","answers":[{"text":"fixed","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i submit i receive a message saying that clang .... executable ld not found","answers":[{"text":"try again","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"anyone know why this is happening","answers":[{"text":"the website only works if i run ./server and then wait about a minute for it to get a connection.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i could only obtain 404 error when tried to open like this but i tried curl -d - http //localhost 8000/hello it looks quite normal. same results happen to all path. what could be the issue here thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"is your code making every webpage return a send_404 message","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes dunno why the path will become user agent instead of the path given in the request when i use browser to open the website","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"well if you coded it so that every web page returns send_404 change it so based on the web page request it returns something else","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes already dealt with that. thank u very much","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"should http //localhost 3490/hello return hello or hello","answers":[{"text":"lt h1 gt hello lt /h1 gt","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i was trouble shooting my code and so changed teh compiler to dcc and it raised a seg fault with line 35 where the skeleton code loops through envp i what's going on","answers":[{"text":"hi robert i just ran the supplied code under dcc and it worked fine. check if you have edited anything before the start of the loop in main. and maybe just to be sure re-download a new copy and copy across the execute function and the loop body.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"actually no it still messes up with dcc but executes exactly how it is supposed to with gcc","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i can't quite work out why a loop of mine doesn't seem to execute those lines in the the function after the loop ends. having played around with it the following loop seems to execute properly note that the condition is just fore testing int i 0 for i 0 i lt 9 i printf d n i printf ---ending execute n the above code produces the following 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 ---ending execute however when i add one line to the loop to print the path the line ---ending execute after the loop no longer prints. also the loop only increments to 6 and not 8 as per the loop condition int i 0 for i 0 i lt 9 i printf d element in path is s n i path i printf d n i printf ---ending execute n this outputs 0 element in path is /import/glass/4/z5200681/bin-pc.i86.linux 0 1 element in path is /import/glass/4/z5200681/bin 1 2 element in path is /usr/local/bin 2 3 element in path is /usr/bin 3 4 element in path is /bin 4 5 element in path is null 5 6 element in path is null 6 interestingly when i change path i to path 2 the loops starts working again. int i 0 for i 0 i lt 9 i printf d element in path is s n i path 2 printf d n i printf ---ending execute n this outputs 0 element in path is /usr/local/bin 0 1 element in path is /usr/local/bin 1 2 element in path is /usr/local/bin 2 3 element in path is /usr/local/bin 3 4 element in path is /usr/local/bin 4 5 element in path is /usr/local/bin 5 6 element in path is /usr/local/bin 6 7 element in path is /usr/local/bin 7 8 element in path is /usr/local/bin 8 ---ending execute can anyone provide any input as to why this happens as it seems utterly strange to me thanks","answers":[{"text":"why are you using i lt 9 as the loop condition do you know for sure that there are 9 elements in path i have no idea why the second loop terminates after 7 iterations but the fact that the last few iterations even work and show null is pure luck. if you use path 2 rather than path i it's hardly surprising that it runs for 9 iterations. why are you surprised","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"as mentioned the condition i lt 9 was just for testing. i was having some trouble with the correct condition which has since been resolved but as part of the troubleshooting i wanted to simplify my condition to check the operation of the loop. this is what led me to the above question - i wasn't sure why a printf statement would cause the loop to fail and actually it seems cause the child process to crash as the --ending execute line after the loop would not print whenever trying to print path i for values of i above 6. i understand that in this case maybe there is no path 7 or greater but i wouldn't think trying to print that string would have broken the loop. i thought at worst it may just print random data. when i gets to 5 and 6 i still prints something for printf d element in path is s n i path i lt span class redactor-invisible-space gt lt /span gt specifically 5 element in path is null 6 element in path is null even though path 5 and path 6 are null. i am not sure what is different about values of i above this which would actually cause the loop to break. i understand it may not print anything meaningful but i was surprised the loop if not the entire process broke as my understanding was the index i was a number of bytes past the start of the array.i also would have thought if it did try and access memory it wasn't allowed to it would have output an error of some sort to stdout but there has never been one. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"permission denied hi i'm working on cse machine. but i get permission denied when used execve. so what should i do to avoid this thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"it's possible that your parameters to execve are not right ... despite the message about executing /bin/ls . you might want to print the values of the arguments that you're actually passing to execve or use gdb to help you check them.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i wonder why command cd does not work in my-shell is it due to cd is not in the directory /bin and if so is it possible to achieve this goal thanks","answers":[{"text":"good question ... and to be resolved in assignment 2. cd is a special command built-into the shell. it needs to be built in because it changes the state of the shell. programs that you execute via execve run as separate processes and do not affect the shell's internal state. you can achieve this via chdir . read the manual entry.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"got it. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the answers for q11 include sigquit which isn't mentioned in the question.","answers":[{"text":"thanks ... fixed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the answer for q4 is incorrect as well. it shows that the output is the same for both cases.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in the example jas showed for the atexit function printing bye i'm confused about where the function call to atexit actually happened in the main. does this block imply calling the atexit function or is it just checking if atexit returns a valid value thanks","answers":[{"text":"atexit registers a function to be called at termination. in this example there is a function bye that is being registered. the if statement is executed if atexit fails. that is if bye can't be registered. so the call to atexit happens when you see it. the call to bye happens when main returns.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i understand. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"could i be hinted on where the fault in my code may lie looking at the differences in calculation of paddr all the memframes and pte are correctly outputted. any help appreciated thanks","answers":[{"text":"given that pa is always zero i'd be looking at where its value is calculated/assigned.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"am i correct in thinking that the nwrites counter mentioned is actually supposed to be the nsaves counter i have tried incrementing in only the suggested spot as well as combinations including when an already loaded file is modified. none of these seem to produce the expected output. when exactly should nsaves be incremented","answers":[{"text":"hi eleni yes the nwrites counter is nsaves in the program. the value is there to keep track of how many saves to disk so you should increment it whenever a modified page is booted from the frame table or memframes to indicate that the changes would have been saved to disk.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks that makes sense and it's now passing the tests","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can a page be modified without being loaded first","answers":[{"text":"hi farhan yes and no... modifying a page will require loading it into physical memory. however it could happen in one step in your vm simulation. so if a page is currently not loaded and your operation on that page is a write you will need to 'load' it in to the frame table and set it to modified. this operation would still also count as a load because the page is being both loaded and written to.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i asked for some feedback on assignment 1. the general consensus was that it wasn't difficult just laborious. most students agreed that there wasn't much thinking required as the c code was given and felt like they were simply machine-transcribing. a common complaint was that debugging was difficult and many students said they would've liked to have been taught how to use qtspim more thoroughly. another suggestion was for the assignment to be less all-or-nothing i.e. having milestones so that students who didn't get the program completely working could still receive marks for their effort.","answers":[{"text":"the assignment is not all-or-nothing . the auto-marking when i get a chance to do it is a first-cut. if it works then they get full marks for that part and then you assess the style. if it doesn't work then you need to look at how close they got and award a partial performance mark based on that.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i found last semester that the fork lab was completed fairly quickly but most students didn't seem to understand it unless we walked them through what was happening. i think an exercise with forking is a good idea though eg. fork to a particular depth and then stop or create n children and print pids/info about them without making a fork-bomb. or maybe extending the alternating process one so they are writing the majority of the code for it themselves perhaps they'll understand it a bit better having been through the process. i thought the assignment seemed fairly straightforward the main thing students are asking me for help with is memory exceptions and not being sure how to debug them. perhaps they're having more issues because there's more movement of data and calculating the addresses is a bit more in-depth.","answers":[{"text":"i agree with ellen on the fork lab. on the assignment most students i spoke to 'completed' their code but couldn't debug it - perhaps less of a chance to test the assignment while writing it was an issue.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the last step in the question 8 solution should have the title after read page0 t 10","answers":[{"text":"thanks ... fixed","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the assignment i tried so hard on it but my code still doesn t work and now the deadline is over. can i still get some marks for the code that i submitted if it doesn t work","answers":[{"text":"yes. you'll get some marks. you could also keep working on it maybe get it working and submit late. it might end up being worth more than submitting something that doesn't work. but this all depends on how much time you have available.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was wondering what this error message meant.","answers":[{"text":"it's not an error message. your file executed everything and nothing is wrong.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh thankyou","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm really confused is this what the print clear is meant to look like","answers":[{"text":"qtspim doesn't understand the control sequence we use for clear. that looks right.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"clear is like writing clear in the terminal","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'v been trying to run my code on qtspim several times but it keeps getting caught at the point where it returns string 'main_1' where its detecting my string characters to not be upper or lower case or even a ' '. i'v entered an all-lowercase string as a parameter which should pass the islower function which was given in the partly complete .s file. what should i be looking at in this case","answers":[{"text":"if you're running qtspim on a mac there's a known problem discussed in lectures and on this forum that the instruction that gets the address of the start of the string i.e. argv 1 needs to be lw $t2 8 $a1 rather than lw $t2 4 $a1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm using windows on dell but i changed it to lw $t2 8 $a1 and it worked. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"did i understand correctly that $s2 contains numbers of all the entered characters as a single string and we were supposed to split them into individual hexadecimal values and also that calculation of biglength was incorrect and also needed to be rewritten i'm just still trying to find where i made a mistake","answers":[{"text":"did i understand correctly that $s2 contains numbers of all the entered characters as a single string and we were supposed to split them into individual hexadecimal values no. either you did not understand correctly or your explanation is mighty unclear. also that calculation of biglength was incorrect and also needed to be rewritten no. as far as i know its calculation is not incorrect.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i run the scroll.s and use qtspim it looks like this i don't know what is my problem","answers":[{"text":"when i run the scroll.s and use qtspim it looks like this i don't know what is my problem read the message in the xterm. it's telling you that you didn't supply a string. in qtspim you do this via the run parameters option under simulator in the menu. if you're using qtspim on a mac you need to read a whole bunch of other forum posts that describe what to do.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is a valid style to have all the c in comments next to their corresponding mips statement but tabbed further along at approximately column 65 so that all of them are completely clear of the mips i personally think this makes it the easiest to read but don't want to be penalised for going over the 80 char limit if that is still applicable in mips .","answers":[{"text":"this approach sounds perfectly reasonable","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in regards to the marking criiteria what does it mean by lining up the opcodes and the args consistently","answers":[{"text":"making it look like the supplied code. lt tab gt opcode lt tab gt args where args are separated from each other by a comma and a space.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am very confused about the data structure of 'bigstring' in the assignment specification it's define as a double array of bigstring 9 1000 with 9 rows and 1000 columns each row that is 9 1000 9000 bytes in total. but in the real code provided it seems more like bigstring 9 9000 from bigstring nrows nscols and make the bigstring 9 9000 81000 bytes which confused me a lot. is there an extra 9 multiplited in here","answers":[{"text":"this is a known error but it doesn't effect program execution.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"whenever i try to run scroll.s i get this memory error. i've tried going through my program through qtspim and it kept hanging around this line. and the console looks like this when it stops. any tips on how to solve this i'm absolutely lost right now.","answers":[{"text":"the line you're looking at is the exit function to finish the program. form the registers etc. it looks like the program is trying to terminate normally after printing an error message. the program thinks that you didn't give it a string to print. did you if not and within qtspim you need to feed the string in via the run parameters option under simulator in the main menu. if you're using a mac check out the numerous other times it has been asked on the forum about the main function not finding the string in argv 1 even if you do input it as described above.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"has anyone encountered their program outputting just these hash symbols instead of a string the input was hello","answers":[{"text":"it almost looks like you've messed up the offset calculations and you're printing a column as a row. but that's just a wild guess.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there an autotest for this assignment if not any suggestion on how to check the output of mips program identical to the c program","answers":[{"text":"$ make $ ./scroll hello gt out1 $ 1521 spim -file exe.s hello sed -e 1d gt out2 $ diff out1 out2 this should work on the cse machines which is where you should test your programs anyway before submitting them where the loaded /home/cs1521/lib/spim/exceptions.s is the only junk that spim writes before the real output. one other machines it might write more junk.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what is the 802 810d801","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it tells you that there's a difference between the two outputs. lines 802-810 in out1 have been replaced by a single line in out2 your output is 99 the same as the expected output. without seeing the code and don't send it because i don't have time to trawl through it it's hard to tell. it might be simpler to interpret the output if you didn't print the clear string in either program.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i used the command you provided and the output is 802 810d801 lt lt lt lt lt lt lt lt lt","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"bad address in data/stack read error on this line here i'm not sure what's going on but it loops successfully twice before hitting this. somehow $t2 becomes 51 instead of an address note this is a part of the given code ie i didn't write this part of the code","answers":[{"text":"the code just below what you sent has calls to isupper and islower one of which you wrote. the code also jumps back to main_ptrs_cond. perhaps your function messed things up. try single-stepping through the isupper function in qtspim and seeing if it changes $t2 inappropriately somewhere.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"just to check could it be that $t2 is being overwritten when jumping to isupper and islower","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it won't be overwritten during the instruction that makes the jump i.e. what i interpret you to mean by when jumping however there's nothing to stop it being overwritten during execution of the function.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no it doesn't i may have done the easy way of copy pasting islower and changing all the tags from lower to upper . just to clarify that it's not a return address issue the code is supposed to loop thru my code main_thelength_ge_1 in main and then go back to main_ptrs_cond right","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"in that case try single-stepping around that region of the program and seeing which instruction messes up the value of $t2 .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ah it would seem that the jr $ra in my setupdisplay function is taking me back to main_ch_lower shouldn't it be taking me back to where i called j setupdisplay","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if you used jal setupdisplay it might work better","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the 3d array all_chars which row col i don't know what is the base address of all_chars and i don't know the col_size is ndcols or nscols","answers":[{"text":"the label all_chars in an instruction gives you the base address of all_chars . all_chars is effectively a large array of 9-byte rows. each big char occupies 9 rows. you can find the start byte of each big char by finding its offset from 'a' and then multiplying that by 81 9 9 . from that start byte you have 9 rows of 9 chars each.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are we allowed to change the registers in the delay function cause i want to use $s instead of $t in delay since i already used a bunch of $t in main and i don't want delay to change the values in main's $t registers.","answers":[{"text":"we told you that $t registers are temporary and by convention can be changed by any function any time it likes. the caller of a function should make no assumptions that $t registers will hold the same value after the function finishes as they did before the function was called. we also told you that $s registers by convention should be preserved across a function call. what you're proposing is the opposite of this convention. nobody will use your functions if you implement them this way","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i personally would change the values in main that you don't want to be changed in a function to be $s registers as that is the point of those registers .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i want to know the two if in the photo is the two if means if isupper ch 1 which ch - 'a' and if islower ch 1 which ch - 'a' 26","answers":[{"text":"that's a decent interpretation of what the code says. note that at most one of those if 's can be true.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i must have an error in calculation of position of element of bigstring row col i chrsize 1 do i understand correctly the formula is nscols row col i chrsize 1 or is nscols a wrong multiplier thank you again","answers":[{"text":"nscols is the wrong multiplier bigstring rows contain 100 chrsize 1 bytes multiply by the row index to get the offset of the start of the row then add the col index to get the byte position within the row add that to amp bigstring and you've got the absolute address","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i look at the output from my exe.s using vim i see a lot of null characters after each line once there's space between the end of the string and the rightmost of the display matrix. is this supposed to happen / will this affect the autotests","answers":[{"text":"no. it's not supposed to happen. yes. it will affect the auto-testing.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi so for the function setupdisplay i'm accessing the argument 'int starting' from $a0. however from qtspim it seems this value is really large and the loop for out_col 0 out_col lt starting out_col doesn't seem to end. i tried accessing it with move $s0 $a0. i also tried accessing it as a address but that also didn't work. thank you","answers":[{"text":"the actual value in $a0 looks like an address in the data region. since the starting argument is supposed to be a count in the range -80...80 it should not have a value in the data region. i'd be looking at the code that set the value of $a0 before calling setupdisplay","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"alright thanks for the tip","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"look into the delay function","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"well anyone know how to have a auto-testing which shown in the assessment before submitting what command","answers":[{"text":"what command spim -file exe.s some string try a few variations on some string . that's all the testing you need.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks and i have a perfect result but only about the delay. is it alright to change some number in the delay func by myself if there will be any affection for auto-testing","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"this is the last time i am going to answer this question ... the delay function is completely irrelevant to our testing.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i set the delay parameter in mips the same to c it goes really really slow. is that normal will that affect the auto test","answers":[{"text":"read the notices.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so the scrolling speed does not affect test right","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no. the speed has no effect on the tests.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"well i changed the $t4 and $t5 in delay part in mips as 1000 and 100 it goes better at least not so slow. however i don't know if it would affect the auto-test. by the way do you know how to have a auto-test what command","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i don't think we have auto test.. it seems that our assignment will be test by auto test after due.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"bad address in data/stack read error. anyone have an idea of what the problem could be spent nearly a whole day trying to figure out what the issue is ' it's printing a bunch of errors according to qtspim it's failing on the line i've highlighted in the code. i've done some testing and for some reason if i try to print the byte at display row out_col 's address it's fine but it screws up if i try to print the byte at bigstring row in_col 's address... any ideas appreciated","answers":[{"text":"why are you trying to print the bigstring byte bigstring is only for inout. in any case the output you've sent is giving plenty of clues. it's telling you which instruction. it's telling you the address being used. you know that this instruction is using the address contained in $t4 . now find out which instruction set the value of $t4 incorrectly. then work out why. a loop that hasn't terminated an invalid offset calculation","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm trying to print out bigstring to see what characters are being stored there. anyhow thank you for the advice i'll test them out and see if i can pinpoint where the issue lies.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"and exception occurred at pc 0x004003f0 i am getting these errors when attempting to run the code i was just wondering if it is a problem with a loop or with wrong calculation of address and so how do i tell if address is out of bounds thank you","answers":[{"text":"the bad address es it's complaining about are all roughly in the data region how do you know this if it's complaining about out of bounds then maybe you've gone beyond the end of your defined data structures. if you want to find where the bounds are look at the data tab in qtspim. qtspim tells you the value of all registers. if you're using some register as an offset/index then check that its value hasn't gotten too large","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello some trouble here. when i run my exe.s in putty with an input hello there it only showing a rolling hello here while i dedug in qtspim it only showing a roling there . why my one exe.s would have 2 different result in putty and qtspim the pictures shown below is the result in putty and qtspim","answers":[{"text":"spim and qtspim are slightly different environments.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"by the way can i have a change in delay func. because it is too slow so i change the $t4 as 1000 and $t5 as 100. but i don't know if i changed the delay func is it alright to pass the auto-test and how to have a auto-test by myself","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the auto-tests couldn't care less about the delay function. change the values so that they suit the speed of your terminal. how to have a auto-test by myself it's not hard. by now you should be able to think up suitable tests by yourself. run your program with a number of different strings. make sure they include upper-case lower-case and spaces.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi my program keeps on printing every character ... it might be a v stupid mistake but i've been staring at this program for 4 days straight and just can't find the problem","answers":[{"text":"one very easy thing to see from this output is that $10 has a value that can't possibly be an address but you're using it as one in lb ... 0 $10 is the value in $10 an offset rather than an address if so try adding the base address of the array before dereferencing it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the help it seems like i loaded the label instead of the byte into $a0 for syscall.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"anyone know what is wrong with my code when i enter an argument such as hi or abc or anything it just skips all the code in the main and jumps straight to the main_post and i even used qtspim.","answers":[{"text":"how do you know that it skips all the code in the main","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i used qtspim and went through it step by step. i saw it just skipping to the epilogue. but all good i think i just didn't insert the parameters properly","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"presuming you haven t edited the code given to us in main. run the string argument with the run parameters option in qtspim and set your string there","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeaa that really helped me debug the code thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i was wondering if my style is good or not this is just some random code i made up . https //pastebin.com/ckrwnher 1. when i comment something what do i comment the c code part or what the actual mips code is doing 2. for example bge is the equivalent of i lt j. so do i comment i lt j or i gt j 3. also is there any autotests for this assignment","answers":[{"text":"comments that just restate what the instruction is doing are not helpful. you're better to put a single line of c code as a comment over the few mips instructions that implement that c code. if you want to put i lt j somewhere put it in a block comment before the loop. if you want to put i gt j then put a comment like if i gt j break there are few distinct cases that we can test so you don't really need auto-tests. as long as it works with one word e.g. hello and works for mixed case strings e.g. hello and two words e.g. hello world and three words e.g. hello there john then it'll work for all of our tests.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the reply. just 2 follow up questions. 1. what is a comment block a multiple line description 2. i have concerns about how i do the spacing for instructions sets which are 2 3 and 4 character instruction sets. https //pastebin.com/ckrwnher in the above link the instruction li and add have the registers line up nicely. however in the instruction move the registers are not lined up. what would i do","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what is a comment block a multiple line description a bunch of comments not appended to instructions and occurring just before the sequence of mips instructions that they're describing. spacing for instructions sets which are 2 3 and 4 character instruction sets. i think you mean register rather than character ... but to be consistent with the supplied code each instruction should be formatted like lt tab gt opcode lt tab gt args where the args are separated from each other by a comma and a space.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if i follow the same format supplied in the initial code i will be fine not lose any marks for style","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi sorry if this isn't very assignment specific but i've been stuck with a can't expand stack by lt big number gt bytes to lt bigger number gt error for a while and was told it could be the way i'm setting up my prologue/epilogue. assuming i'm using s0 through s5 would this be the correct way to set up and tear down the stack frame","answers":[{"text":"use qtspim to find what instruction it crashed on and the values of the registers at that point. and then work backwards through the execution in your head qtspim can't execute backwards to see where the offending registers were set.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"looks fine to me. make sure all your stacks are correct to then and see if it works.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am getting the error memory address out of bounds i have no idea what is causing this issue in the code.","answers":[{"text":"use qtspim. at least it highlights the instruction where the error occurred and shows you registers that were recently changed. the register to look at is the one you're using as an index at the point the crash occurs. then work out why it has that value. etc. etc. i.e. work backwards from the instruction where it crashed to the place where the incorrect values were set.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"comment stuff and see what is causing it or not. typically i had this issue when i called functions setupdisplay and showdisplay - which ended up being because my array offsets were incorrect which may be your issue","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how far are we permitted to stray from the provided c code there are sections of main e.g. the multiple nested for loops inside a single 3rd for loop that would make more sense to me if i wrote them differently. provided that our eventual output is the same is this allowed","answers":[{"text":"mapping c to mips is just a way of making it easier to write mips code. in reality you might implement things differently to make them more efficient less instructions faster loops etc. . as long as it actually works you don't have to slavishly follow the c code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i think they wrote it in c like that since it is the most easiest way to translate the code across from c to mips. otherwise make sure you got your program working first before you think about this stuff. writing it as a direct representation of c code in mips works fine and is the nature of the task.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the writing of the code isn't the part i'm concerned about. to translate the given section into mips as-is would require 6 for loops and 4 if-statements for approximately 16 labels. however it could easily be done in half that number which would at least in my opinion significantly improve the readability of the code which is itself worth marks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"can also be marked on your ability to translate code given to you in c and into mips since you're understanding the process of how a set amount of c code may be represented in assembly code and your ability to manage all those assmembly processes.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was just wondering if the value under bad address in data/stack read is the value it is trying to store the byte of the line associated with the error is an lb call and if that would mean i haven't correctly gotten the value to store in the array into the register i'm using. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"the stack starts at address 0x7ffffe00 and grows downwards so 0xf7e497d6 is clearly not an address on the stack. check the bits of your code that modify $sp and you'll probably find the instruction that's messing it up. if you single step through the program in qtspim it's easy to spot when the value changes to something bad since qtspim highlights the registers that were changed by the last instruction. if this is happening well into the program single stepping will take too long so use a breakpoint to get to roughly the relevant part of the code. left mouse-click while hovering over the instruction where you want to set the breakpoint","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"could be more something like you're accessing a part that is beyond the size of the array. also you're having stack issues it seems so check your epilogue/prologue","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi again. my program won't stop syscall-ing and i was wondering whether there is any way i can stop it from doing so. a thousand thank you's.","answers":[{"text":"an infinite loop around the syscall possibly caused by using the wrong value in $ra when doing jr $ra or could be some other incorrect branch. impossible to tell without more info.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi my program only print the first column and it does not scroll at all which part could be wrong thanks","answers":[{"text":"are you changing the starting column as richard liu said look at what the c code is doing and render that in mips.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"look into c code where it scrolls the printing part and look where you did that in mips. could be there. otherwise it is printing your array and your array could have the wrong stored values. delay might be making it run slow so comment it out and check the behaviour again.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the printed characters from my mips program doesn't scroll all the way to the left and stays inside the command prompt. i am wondering if this is acceptable for this assignment or is it require to scroll all the way to the left and then disappear from the command prompt","answers":[{"text":"you need to scroll the text all the way off the display. think negative starting column.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"probably required to scroll across the screen since the assignment itself is named scroll. presuming you are printing out the correct big character versions could be something to do with delay or your loop to scroll","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i think my qtspim is reading one argument before because when i shift up the $a0 by 4 bytes it reads my word perfectly on qtspim but tells me i need to enter a string on spim. any clue what i may have done wrong.","answers":[{"text":"i mentioned this in the lecture. the 4 $a1 works ok on qtspim on the cse servers. however on macs the argv array is a different size and you need to use 8 $a1 .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the line of code provided with 4 $a1 is correct. any other problems your are having will be causes elsewere.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do i access all_chars which row col i've loaded the index/offset calculation into $t4 and done the below to try and load all_chars which row col into $t4 as well lb $t4 all_chars $t4 however im getting an bad address in data/stack read error. can someone help","answers":[{"text":"because you are using $t4 to store in character into all_chars and using $t4 as your offset. maybe try lb $t0 all_chars $t4 where $t0 is an used register","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi my scroll.s now prints out only the bottom line of the word and then enters into exception 7s. what does this mean this was for hello also the symbols in the right are just spaces- i changed the character to make sure they were printing","answers":[{"text":"thankyou","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"formulas for your arrays could be wrong or loops issues or register issues concerning not printing what you want. otherwise the errors are because you are accessing an array beyond the size of the array or a counter is wrong","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"does anyone know what does this mean","answers":[{"text":"okayy fixed it now thank you to everyone that helped","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"0x20 sounds like the space character ... check the load/store at 384.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i saw that kind of thing when i was writing past the end of an array. i expect that output appears very quickly but i would try and see what was on the screen if any thing directly before that output starting appearing i.e where your program got up to. then with that information try and debug from that point in your code within qtspim.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in showdisplay i don't know what is printf clear","answers":[{"text":"clear is just a string that was defined in the header . you're just printing the string.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you i know how to do that","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"clear is a label in the .data section.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i'm been debugging my program for almost the entire day now. i can t figure out what is causing my program to print the big chars like this. i am printing the letter b https //gyazo.com/017cd099d8d64718c7c03d0e2b2b35fb what could be the cause of this i've checked my formula's at least 7 times now. you can see in the middle it brings b correctly. it prints the top half then the entire b then the bottom half","answers":[{"text":"what happens if you print more characters","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it looks like a mess. in this case i am writing comp but you can only see bits and pieces of the o i think its an o or a p . https //gyazo.com/32032b9193e3c6ec4d86f0df38da80f7 tried another typing jku https //gyazo.com/97198adfe49cf7bab9721ce7bc9bf202","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"then the or ' ' are not being copied properly from array to array. so it could be formulas on arrays loops or register issues","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"well all my array copying formula's for the 2d array is just i know some of them have other things in there like bigstring row col i chrsize 1 but i take that into account too. bigstring offset chrsize row chrsize 1 i col array row col offset row chrsize col then for 3d arrays array which row col offset chrsize chrsize which chrsize row col","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"bigstring nrows nscols display nrows ndcols think about this...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"that makes no sense to me. if i use ndcol's the offset is way off and nscol's formula is basically given in the c code when you have to calculate bigstring row col i chrsize 1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"from c to mips you traverse an array from 1 column to the end then you 'move onto the next row'. hence why we do row x maximum columns. so what are the maximum columns in those arrays","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"max column in all the 2d arrays is 9 in bigstring we have 9 rows and 9 columns 9x9 block for 1 letter. edit reading some other questions. i see bigstring as 9 1 columns. one column at the end i'm assuming is the gap we leave between each letter we print but doesn't the formula i gave above already take that into account chrsize 1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"format array row column ndcols 90 nscols 9000 display 9 90 bigstring 9 9000 the big string is meant to be that large since it holds the maximum amount that someone could input via the terminal 100 characters . display holds the maximum amount that will be displayed in the terminal at 1 given point of time. so the maximum columns for display is 90 and the maximum columns for bigstrings is 9000. make sure you're not mixing up your terminals. edit to your edit yes gap for space between characters in a single word. i am getting mixed up now haha. but everything they've given us is correct and is there for a reason to be used.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"could you explain why the column is 90 and not 9 i thought all 2d arrays only have a column of 9 since the width of a letter is 9 . would this mean the offset for bigstring is actually bigstring offset nscols row chrsize 1 i col","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes to formula. i mean ndcols/nscols are just a predetermined sizes to hold all the and all the empty spaces ' '. so its not just holding the important character and the 9x9 size of that character since you're transferring everything over from one array to another.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so when i calculate this part for bigstring bigstring row col ' ' that would also mean i need to do bigstring offset nscols row col","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yes","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it looks like a mess to you but leaks information to me. as below check the block building bigstring.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"presuming it isn't the formulas check your loops that they are working as expected","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"well i've also checked those already too. i've been over my code many times already. the first time i went over my code i found issues with my formula which i fixed but after that i checked my entire code again about 4 times but still haven't found the issue. i've been looking for mistakes ever since.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'd be suspicious of your first loop copying characters into bigstring and the loop in setupdisplay. i don't have enough data to suggest anywhere else to look.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i've checked this. it looks perfect to me. i guess the only thing i am unsure about in the entire setupdisplay is this part in c. i wrote it down on paper and went through some of the cases i feel like this part is correct too. if out_col gt ndcols break mips lw $t0 ndcols load ndcols into $t0 blt $s1 $t0 sud_start_rel_loop if out_col lt ndcols go to next part j sud_end break and jump to the end of the entire function.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"looks ok but hard to tell only looking at a piece of code instead of the whole function from label to label loop to end_loop","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i believe the loops are fine. i also checked the loops/the entire setupdisplay function10 minutes ago.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"looks like your counters or branch conditions/values might be wrong. the skewing of the text make me think your 'one off' somewhere in your code so each time a loop iterates it is one off where it should be hence the increasing misalignment you see.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"that was my first instinct too but my loops are correct. i think my formulas might be wrong. bigstring offset chrsize row chrsize 1 i col display row col display offset row chrsize col then for 3d arrays all_chars which row col all_chars chrsize chrsize which chrsize row col","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"3d array 90 x letter number 0-51 10 x row number 0-8 column number 0-9 assuming you have a blank space at the end of each 9 bytes for a space","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so are these formula's correct ndcols 90 nscols 9000 chrsize 9 c display i j ' ' display offset ndcols i j c bigstring row col i chrsize 1 ' ' bigstring offset nscols row chrsize 1 i col c all_chars which row col all_chars offset chrsize chrsize which chrsize row col confused here why the letter number is 90 because 9 width and 9 height so we take into account the 1 column gap . c bigstring row col ' ' bigstring offset nscols i j","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"its just which 9 9. no 9 1. bigstring is fine but you didn't take that concept for the display array...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i edited the post above. like that","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"what is max columns for display","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"9 columns for the letter 1 for the gap. 10 total columns for the offset","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"reread what i said above regarding these arrays and the display array. you seem to have missed the point.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm just having trouble understanding by the column is 90 for display and 9000 for bigstring rather than 9. i went to one of the help sessions and i was told that the column size would be 9 because the width for each character is 9 characters long.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"each character is of size 9x9. as represented in chars.s display array is sized to fit that amount of characters in the terminal big string array is sized to fit the entire string in big characters 9x9 of what the user inputted. so naturally the display array must use the max columns it has in it and not just 9x9 since its not just fitting in a 9x9 character it also may contain other 9x9 characters and spaces etc. i guess specifically the terminal can display 9 characters at 1 given time - but not certain on that.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i think i just got it. so when the user inputs a letter. thats automatically 10 columns taken up 9 for the letter and 1 for the gap . if the user enters 2 letters that's 10 columns for the first letter and 10 for the second letter. hence 20 columns total so the max column for display is 90 or 100","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ndcols is defined for us. use it. but yes that's the way to think about it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"so these are correct now ndcols 90 nscols 9000 chrsize 9 c display i j ' ' display offset ndcols i j c bigstring row col i chrsize 1 ' ' bigstring offset nscols row chrsize 1 i col c all_chars which row col all_chars offset chrsize chrsize which chrsize row col confused here why the letter number is 90 because 9 width and 9 height so we take into account the 1 column gap . c bigstring row col ' ' bigstring offset nscols i j","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"should be yeah.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"last thing ndcols is defined as 80. this means i have to make ndcols equal to 90","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi. sorry for asking for help so much but i've got an error and im not sure why my program still wont go through qtspim properly. this might be a related question - how would i be able to enter the code here i inserted the exact same format and it wouldn't read my input into the program i was alrd told to 'load some code' which i did through '1521 qtspim -file exe.s '. what could i possibly be doing wrong","answers":[{"text":"file gt reinitialise and load file is your friend. and don't forget to set arguments in simulator gt run parameters","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i was using mars myself as an emulator at home but then when i ran the code on qtspim i saw something similar. from memory it was something like a white space or layout issue qtspim was complaining about. making sure everything was aligned in the file fixed it it didn't seem to be a syntax or coding error.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the error itself means that when spim attempted to do symbol resolution for any dangling labels before executing it couldn't find the label main -- this is left dangling by the default runtime in exceptions.s . qtspim is likely forgetting to tell you that it couldn't load the file. i've not used mars but i gather it's got a quite different interpreter to spim.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is there a way i can retrieve my code from previous submissions","answers":[{"text":"i know you could in other comp subjects i have taken but i am not sure you can yourself in this subject. i am pretty sure one of the tutors would be able to retreive a previous revision for you though.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeah i thought that too so i didnt bother making backups changed quite a bit of code broke a few things but ended up fixing it","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was just wondering how you would found the offset for the 3d array all_chars","answers":[{"text":"well the offset for 2d arrays are row_index col_size col_index sizeof data_type base_address. i think if you kind of substitute the 3rd dimension you'll find it. and it's pretty close to the above formula.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"think about it like this. the which array has a character for each index. going into that index you access the matrix representation of that character. so then how might you access 'a' or 'b'.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"i asked this question before and we are allowed to yes. spec also says already complete delay function but you can tweak the numbers if you want to speed up or slow down the animation.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i try to run the parameter hello or hello into qtspim it always just goes through the main__0 path and then clears the stack like how it would act if there was no command line argument. i'm using the latest revision 1.5 and my code prints stuff out when i run it with spim so how can i get it to run through my code properly on qtspim i've submitted my latest code with give if that helps.","answers":[{"text":"... if it works fine using spim on cse that's all you need. qtspim is in my experience filled with bugs that cause breakage.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i wanted to use qtspim for debugging though since my code isn't printing out the right things right now - it keeps printing out all hashes in the display. i wanted to see where things might be going wrong. should i go about debugging another way then","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i can't think of any particularly nice approach using qtspim. i'd suggest xspim 1521 xspim as a more reliable option but it seems to be badly behaved in vlab. my preferred debugging approach is a combination of spim -dump -file hang j hang and a bunch of print syscalls. it's spartan but it gets the job done.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm really not sure where my code is going wrong as i am getting no exceptions or error yet it is just printing this any idea what this might be","answers":[{"text":"i've experienced this difficulty before finally getting it to work. it may/may not be what happened in your case but in my case i forgot that $t registers unlike $s registers aren't preserved after a function call and my output is pretty much what you have there.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"check your arrays are holding correct character value or that the array formulas are correct byte offsets","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i want to print a single character in a string e.g. display i j which syscall should i use is syscall 11 correct","answers":[{"text":"yup","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"memory address out of bounds hi i wrote a code snippet like this. and it behaves like this it seems that the code could run normally until bne $t8 $t7 ..... . it could print out value of $t7 which is the first element of thestring array h . but it cannot print out $t8 which supposed to be a blank. i guess the problem happens at the bne . is there any suggestion about this kind of issue thanks in advance","answers":[{"text":"memory address out of bounds suggests you've got a syscall 4 with a character value in $a0. i suspect you're looking in the wrong spot.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"are you sure the issue is not occurring in ch_not_eq_blank like it might be doing something in that function which does something wrong - otherwise check where specifically the issue is in qtspim and see what values are in your registers","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i keep getting the above error message. from qtspim i know which part of the code is the issue and i've tried to change the code numerous times but nothing seems to be working. if someone could give some advice that'll be great thank you","answers":[{"text":"what's the address that's producing the fault","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi so i got this output using spim.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you've wandered off the end of an array in the .data segment. i agree with richard check your range conditions and offsets. in particular you have one useful piece of information where the fault is 1fc check around there.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"check your registers are behaving as expected or potentially a formula for byte offset is wrong presuming this is in the area of the first c loop you are meant to implement","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for your help jashank and richard seems i just made a very careless mistake '","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hey i've been running my program in qtspim but it seems to be exiting on the early part printing 'only letters and spaces are allowed in the string '. running it again i've noticed that it detected 5 command line arguments when it starts running. i also haven't changed anything in the main program. is this meant to happen submitted code if its any help.","answers":[{"text":"does it work when you're not using qtspim","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it ends up not printing anything like this.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm pretty sure the 5 command line arguments are 1521 spim -file exe.s hello . if you can run 1521 spim -file exe.s hello and nothing happens check you have either implemented your setupdisplay amp showdisplay functions properly. since it would have printed something else if something was wrong. you are using set parameters properly with command line being a or whatever right","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no spim counts arguments after -file filename such that the program behaves roughly like a normal application and so you could concievably make it an executable script.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we run the auto-test ourselves on the assignment to check if they pass","answers":[{"text":"the submission test does spim -assemble -file exe.s which should be enough to catch syntax errors. as for more testing... you've got a known to be working program and a program that may work why not write your own tests have a look at the tests used in the labs to get some ideas of how to do that.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks jashank not a bad idea and time permitting i would probably give that ago but time is something that may not permit.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i only just submitted the assignment for the first time. does the output below indicate the submission tests passed continuing with the submission... submission assign1 ------------------------------ files found scroll.s ------------------------------ assign1 dryrun checking syntax of 'scroll.s'... cat chars.s scroll.s gt exe.s submission datestamp sat sep 1 20 07 38 2018 assignment deadline sun sep 2 23 59 59 2018 this submission is 1 day and 3 hours early submission accepted. awesome","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it just verifies scroll.s can be concatenated into an exe.s file","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"not just. it asks spim to check it can assemble all the opcodes which should give you a good idea if your syntax is wrong or you've goofed a symbol. that command isn't visible or rather the output from make isn't suppressed.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"you haven't loaded any code","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how are you today i have a question in regards to assignment 1. i'm just wondering if we arewe allowed to change the stack frame for the main function thank you. raymond.","answers":[{"text":"absolutely","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi mr. jashank thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there i have another question in regards to assignment 1. how do i store the ' ' into array in mips thank you. raymond.","answers":[{"text":"you'd have to load the value immediate you wanted to store then store that into the array at the appropriate location.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if we have the address of display i j sorted in the $t3 and ' ' stored in $t4 do we use sw $t4 $t3 but that would be store ' ' in $t3 instead of in display i j","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"stores work in the opposite direction to loads. sw register location writes the value in register to the memory address location ... so your store is the right way around.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi mr. jashank thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"read from unused memory-mapped io address 0xfffffff0 i'm not sure about what this mean i saw another guy have similar issue but mine got read and different value. could anyone give an explanation thank you very much","answers":[{"text":"it's the same sort of issue you're offsetting -16 from a value that's gone to zero. on a hunch you're not using $s8 somewhere","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i got it i didn't correctly write epilogue of the function. thanks for hints","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no what i used most of the $s registers in function stack are $s1 $s2 $s4 $s5 $s6","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am a bit confused by 'clobbers'. for example in a function if i use $s6 as i in a loop and after this loop i use $s6 for other purposes does this mean $s6 is a clobber thanks.","answers":[{"text":"clobbers mark up registers that will lose their value across a function call. save registers shouldn't.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you for your reply. does it mean that if there is no function call inside a function then there are no clobbers in this function","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if a function can be observed to change the value of a register that register is clobbered. if a function can be observed to change values in s-registers that function is broken.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if i'm not mistaken that's correct for example in the delay function you can see that all the clobbers are t registers.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do i do command line arguments in qtspim","answers":[{"text":"simulator - gt run parameters then in the 2nd text box you insert your command line args there.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"scroll window height if i expand my terminal window to higher than 9 rows i can see the previous output as shown below. do we just assume the terminal window is only ever going to be 9 rows high so the previous output won't be seen or are we meant to somehow clear the terminal screen prior to printing so we will only ever see the single row of scrolling characters regardless of the window height thanks","answers":[{"text":"you are given a special string in the clear label to print after each iteration. printing the clear label as a string will clear the screen and is required to be used to pass the auto tests.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks i see that now.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"error write to unused memory-mapped io address 0xfffffffc i've tried my own research and debugging but i can't seem to find out how to fix this error does anyone know/can help","answers":[{"text":"0xfffffffc is two's complement -4. some variable you're dereferencing with offset -4 is zero. this was a known issue with some versions of the sample code make sure you've got up-to-date starter code and check your epilogues.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi getting syntax error with global variables when trying to run the code. any ideas on how to fix or why this error is occuring syntax error bge $t2 nrows nrows_end_loop1 however it compiles does not have the error if i run bge $t2 $t0 nrows_end_loop1 thanks","answers":[{"text":"you need to load the values from those memory locations.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there i have done the program and try to debug. but the spim command not found . i tried many times but got the same result. could someone help me","answers":[{"text":"have you tried 1521 spim -file exe.s test input","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"an error is occuring when i access the all_chars array. is it ok to do 'lb $t0 all_chars offset to store the content into $t0 or is it because my calculation for the offset is incorrect thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"as long as offset is a single register's value i see no obvious problem. spim can be temperamental about this though so you could also add the label and offset together and that would be fine too if the first style doesn't work.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"that should be fine. calculation or something else is incorrect.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi. is there any possible way for me to test my main function without my other functions being completed yet from what i've tried it doesn't seem to work and simply outputs exception occurred at pc 0x004003cc unaligned address in inst/data fetch 0x10010232 exception 4 address error in inst/data fetch occurred and ignored many many times. i'm not sure whether this has to do with the fact that the other functions aren't done or because my main function is fault. thanks.","answers":[{"text":"is there any possible way for me to test my main function without my other functions being completed yet it's possible but you're not going to get sensible behaviour from main . at the very least all of your functions would need a prologue and an epilogue and set a dummy return value in $v0 . then your main could call the functions and have them return. in the case of isupper and islower the only plausible dummy return value would be 1 otherwise your program will stop with an error straight away. event then if your string does not contain only upper and lower case letters you'll get problems further on ... you're better off testing your lower level functions first which would require writing a simple dummy main and then putting them together with the main function.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the reply. i finished all the required functions but i still get the same error. how do i identify such an error thanks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"the error is an unaligned access suggesting you've got a load-word of a value that can't be loaded as a word.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"do we need to follow the format of the given code in order to get the styling mark for example for our loops do we need to set labels for init cond step as in the main_ptrs_init main_ptrs_cond main_ptrs_step or is it fine to leave it like this init_loop_ i if...then j to endi init_loop_ j if.... j to end j j j init_loop_ j endj i .. j init_loop_i endi thank you.","answers":[{"text":"pick a style and be consistent. so long as that style is not totally illegible you're pretty likely to get the style mark. the style i've used is intended to make it easy to see c's control flow points in your assembly program. many of those labels won't be a branch target but serve to provide you information.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi. my program has numerous errors that i have no idea as to why they exist. i haven't a clue as to why this occurs. this prevents my program from actually running anything at all.","answers":[{"text":"i'm not sure how to put my actual mips file here for only the 'course staff' to see.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i looked at qtspim and it seems like you're running qtspim without first loading the exe.s file into qtspim so either do 1521 qtspim -file exe.s or open qtspim then load file or reinitialise and load file","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi all i'm getting some errors when i run spim -file exe.s abc screenshot below . however when i run it using qtspim everything seems all good. any help on how to fix this would be much appreciated thanks","answers":[{"text":"the version of spim you are using is different from that on the cse labs in the labs a char can be loaded by li. but in your version li only works with ints. either change the line to 'li $a0 10' or use the cse version.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi when i try to run exe.s with hello or with any non-empty string lt 100 char it always returns only letters and spaces are allowed in the string . i haven't changed anything in main before the first ..todo.. section besides adding things to the stack and i also haven't changed the inlower function so shouldn't the command line checking for lower case words at least be working . i've tried to print out some things to try to see what was happening and in one test when i printed out the return value v0 of islower after the function call there was one more return value than there was letters e.g. hello --printed-out-- gt 111110. in another test i forced v0 to take 1 after islower was called and got a string mush sic be lt 100 chars error. i've also tried using qtspim and running parameters like hello but it only prints the main__0 message before restoring the stack so that hasn't helped. i've been using the latest revision of the code from assign1 $revision 1.5 $ so what could the problem be i've submitted my current code with give if that would help.","answers":[{"text":"line numbers are from scroll.s without the code fragment includded. if you add this li $a0 68 li $v0 11 syscall to line 291. you will see something strange execution gets to your code and then at some point in the future jumps back to the arg checking. the only way this is possible is by jumping to the wrong place you don't jump to the wrong label anywhere so only an indirect jump will do this. the main way to indirectly jump is by a ja $ra and therein lies the problem when a function is called it's return address is saved to $ra. but only if the address is saved there to begin with. you call j isupper 372 instead if jal isupper in your code this causes $ra not to be set and when isupper returns your jump back to the last properly called function islower 165 in the arg checking section thus the error gets printed","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you for the explanation that seems to have fixed the problem.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"allowed to alter delay function numbers i checked the other posts regarding delay and it was not quite clear so i just wanted to verify. are we allowed to alter the delay function specifically the $t4 amp $t5 values so it prints nicely out on the terminal thanks.","answers":[{"text":"the is a post on the front page tweak the loop bounds in delay until you get decent scrolling speed .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there. may i ask can i build a extra function myself for finding the address of the element of the array . also i wonder how could i add an argument into qtspim like hello there","answers":[{"text":"hi there you are allowed write extra functions to add arguments into qtspim go to the menu bar simulator - gt run parameters and you'll be able to enter in your arguments. word of warning though you won't be able to test strings that have a space bar - due to the way that qtspim handles the arguments.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you thanks a lot","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"green flashes hi there. when i run my mips code i get flashing green cursor rectangles. you can see an example in the image below. strangely this only occurs at certain speeds. at lower speeds there is no flashing green. i'm not sure if this is a problem with uninitialised array indexes in my code or if my code is ok. i know some others are having the same problem. would anyone be able to point us in the direction of the bug any help would be greatly appreciated. thanks","answers":[{"text":"the short answer we're interested in the characters your code outputs not how it's painted by a heap of very slow software emulating an even slower terminal. the slightly longer and less cryptic answer the approach we're using in painting the marquee to the terminal is extremely naive for every frame we clear everything and then paint everything. in an ideal world the terminal could work out how to turn this into partial updates of the screen. in practice what you're seeing is that not happening. the way terminals work hasn't really changed much since 1978 with the introduction of the dec vt-100 terminal the terminals we use today or more accurately terminal emulators pretend to be vt-100 relatives of various denominations. these were powered by intel 8080 processors running at a blistering two megahertz and with very nearly no memory and words like optimised display update algorithm weren't the domain of hardware. the sequences of characters in the clear label -- if i recall correctly something like 033 h 033 2j -- is magic to clear all characters on the screen. the terminal emulator meditates upon its idea of what the screen looks like and updates it character by character or sequence by sequence so each step occurs effectively separately. at low speed the terminal emulator and the rest of the graphics pipeline can keep up but at high speed the terminal has to be painting nearly continuously which can cause the frame that's pushed into the raster buffer to be incorrect. what you're likely seeing then is a weird combination of multiple frames one fully painted with the cursor placed after the last newline and one that's being painted with a cursor being placed before characters are. exactly what is causing that would be a fun well fun weekend exercise in following data through the baklava-like layers of thin flaky delicious abstractions. an interesting challenge and one not worth marks but worth many many kudos and/or mars bars devise a faster screen painting algorithm for this assignment or for say a visual text editor like vi or emacs . there's a few interesting approaches that come to mind ... you may also like a list of all the control sequences you could use to help you out.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks jashank much appreciated. i will begin research into baklava","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i got some questions there. 1.though we have a .space 81000 there but the bytes we actually use is 9 10 1000 which is 9000 so just leave other places nothing or a space 2. for display at t 0 should we have a column of the character stored in bigstring or should all the column be the column of thank you in advance","answers":[{"text":"hi feng you questions seem a little bit ambiguous. so for your first question why are you saying that the actual bytes we use is 9000 are you saying nscols is at size 9000 but that is not the total bytes we will use that s just the number of bytes the bigstring colum will use hence the actual byte bigstring uses is multipled by nrows and that is the maximum number of bytes it will take. and if you are saying what will happen if the input is shorter than the maximum then i would recommend you to read through the setupdisplay function variable thelength is passed to setupdisply function to tell setupdisplay to stop setting up as long as it hits the end of your input so it won t keep printing until reach the end of the bigstring. and for your question 2 are you saying after the first iteration the program will show the first column of bigstring and yes it will since the starting_col is set to ndcols-1 and i don t think we need to make it show nothing in the first iteration as the assignment specification just asked us to translate the c program but if you want u can simply set starting_col to ndcols it will fix the problem . and i also think you have some misunderstandings with respect to bigstring and display because if you want to change the starting column that will show after the first iteration you should alter the arrary display rather than big string as bigstring constantly stores the big version of our input and will not be altered once it is created and display is the actual picture of every frame we see from the command line.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"after a communication to her her first confusion was actually about the calculation of nscols which is in deed a problem of the code it was accidentally multiplied by an extra nrows. original post https //webcms3.cse.unsw.edu.au/comp1521/18s2/forums/2702663","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"thestring hgffhgfg la $t7 thestring li $t5 4 mul $t6 $t3 $t5 $t3 is i counter which is 0 $t6 0 as expected addu $t7 $t7 $t6 $t7 no change as expected lw $s2 $t7 $s2 66666768 unexpected should be ascii for 'h' not sure what to do is the string not being read in properly or am i somehow accessing the wrong address im not sure what is wrong lt /span gt note - i get different errors based on the starting letter of the string argument z5165118 vx3 /scrolls$ 1521 spim -file exe.s asd loaded /home/cs1521/lib/spim/exceptions.s exception occurred at pc 0x004002c0 unaligned address in inst/data fetch 0x00647361 exception 4 address error in inst/data fetch occurred and ignored only letters and spaces are allowed in the string . . . z5165118 vx3 /scrolls$ 1521 spim -file exe.s dsa loaded /home/cs1521/lib/spim/exceptions.s exception occurred at pc 0x004002c0 bad address in data/stack read 0x00617364 exception 7 bad data address occurred and ignored only letters and spaces are allowed in the string really lost right now","answers":[{"text":"because you're dealing with a string array of char each element is one byte long. when you multiply the index by 4 in mul $t6 $t3 $t5 you're skipping over 3 elements. when iterating through an array of chars you do not need to multiply the index to get the correct byte offset.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"from an ascii table h 68 and if we have a look whats in $s2 we see 666667 68 so lets convert the rest 66 f 66 f 67 g 68 h its your string backwards. because a char is 1 byte and lw loads a words 4 bytes your loading four bytes chars at a time try lb load byte to get a single char at a time.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you're loading a word from the address $t7 which is address 0","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"$t7 is not 0 its the address loaded from thestring when i check in qtspim","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"doesn't lw just take the value of the whole string whereas if you used lb you get 'h' try that","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"load word loads the next 4 bytes which is not a full string im pretty sure nvm lb worked ty still quite confused as other examples of accessing arrays all included lw and traversing word by word","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"lw is for arrays of ints lb is for arrays of chars","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there. i ran into an infinite loop. for some reason the value store in register $t0 cannot exceed 8. i would be grateful if someone can help me out. here is my code lw $s4 nrows li $t0 0 initialise_display_row_loop finish loop when $t0 gt $s4 bge $t0 $s4 finished_initialse_display nop for debugging for some reason this keeps printing out from 1 to 8 in an infinite loop move $a0 $t0 li $v0 1 syscall then some code here addi $t0 $t0 1 i j initialise_display_row_loop nop finished_initialse_display thanks again for looking at my code. any kind of help/suggestion would be appreciated","answers":[{"text":"your code iterates for $t0 0 to $t0 lt nrows ... given that nrows 9 it's not surprising that it doesn't exceed 8","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for replying. but the problem is for some reason $t0 keeps resetting to 0 and thus never satisfies the branch condition to jump out of the loop...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"... have you got a function call in there somewhere are you assuming a t-register is retaining its value across a function call","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for the reply. i don't have any function in between neither do i use the register for any calculation...","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"cool send me your code i'd love to have a look.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi in the islower function provided in scroll.s is there a particular reason a fallthrough label is used thanks","answers":[{"text":"i consider anywhere that control flow moves from one edge to another to be a fallthrough and the comment there notes what's happening. the label is a bit more subtle though if you've read my guide to writing assembly you'll have spotted a reference to phi labels which are where both branches of a conditional come back together this name is borrowed from ssa form. so all together in the false arms of islower control flow falls through into the phi as opposed to the true arms where it explicitly jumps.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks jashank one more quick question when we are printing out a single newline character do we have to declare it in .data or can we just load immediate into $a0 and syscall","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"qtspim issues when used on cse vlab machine. in attempts to debug my code i seemed to have done something to my qtspim application as i cannot use it at all. whenever i attempt to load file or reinitalize and load file in mips my terminal outputs setnativelocks failed resource temporarily unavailable . then when i attempt to run or step through my program using qtspim i get the error exception occurred at pc 0x00040000 followed by bad address in text read 0x00040000 which then continues to output the same error message with the hexidecimal value just incrementing by 4 exception occurred at pc 0x00040004 . in the qtspim window it always seems to run starting from line 80000180 or the first line in the kernel text segment and never reaches the user text segment i did attempt logging off and on again disconnecting and reconnecting to the vpn and loading other assembly files although nothing seemed to work. hence irrespective of if the assembly code was incorrect qtspim did not work. any help would be greatly appreciated as it makes using qtspim in vlab impossible.","answers":[{"text":"i'm not sure what the lock problem is. maybe there are too many people trying to run qtspim on the vlab servers. is it still happening","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it appears everywhere on cse... i suspect a bug in qtspim.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i don't ... but why not tell them about xspim","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"pc 0x00040000 is where it normally starts running. if there's not a valid instruction at that location then you would definitely observe the behaviour you describe where it jumps off to the kernel to handle the error. what appears in the code window before you step through the program","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i tried again just now it seems i still am having the same issues. i've added screenshots of the issues i detailed above. but basically i open qtspim load a file then press single step and it starts at pc 0x80000180 /the line i display above every time. i have tried using previous exercises which i know work fine although they did not work and this program exe.s or in this case exe_final.s works fine on home computer's qtspim. although i seem to be unable to use run parameters on my mac since it crashes hence i tried to use qtspim on the vlab to no avail.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"have a careful look at your text segment addresses. the address 0x00040000 is incorrect it should be 0x00400000.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks jas and jashank for the help. it is working now. it seems the run parameters had the address stuck at 0x00400000.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi what is the best way to debug my program printing out a chunk of space and no characters i can't step through in mips because there's so many loops that i'll never reach the end so are there any common reasons for this happening that i can look into thanks.","answers":[{"text":"qtspim has breakpoints that can be set by right clicking and has a list of each register.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm not sure how to figure out using breakpoints whether certain arrays have been filled with a blank rather than a character how would i go about it thanks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"set a break point before you set your display array to stop executing at the trouble spot. then step through from there to see what value you are saving into the array to make sure its correct.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi in the provided scroll.s v1.5 the error message has a typo string mus h be lt . the scroll.c file fixes the typo. i know this is a trivial issue but i am not sure how the auto tests will be run. are our outputs compared to outputs produced from a model .s file or the model .c file should i fix the typo thanks","answers":[{"text":"both the misspelled and correct message will be marked as correct. fix at your own discretion.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi there in my program the whole message can't be scrolled off the left hand end. it always stoped when the the first letter of message touch the left hand side screen. it is so weird and i can't find anything wrong in qtspim. what parts could be wrong thanks.","answers":[{"text":"i suspect you've got one of the conditions in main' wrong and your program is giving up too soon. i'd have to see the code to have a less speculative answer.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi jashank thank you for your reply i have send my code to your email. thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm entering an infinite loop when i run scroll.s and i can't find out why. can someone please help","answers":[{"text":"i'd suggest trying some of the following - run in qtspim to find the location of the infinite loop - check all loops to make sure you have a jump instruction when you need it a branch instruction when you need it and that you are incrementing any counters. - check any registers you are using as counters in loops to make sure that they aren't being used for something else and being overwritten. - check your stack frame setup and tear down - gt errors in return address can sometimes lead to this behaviour","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am having trouble trying to debug my code. when i run it via the console i get the following error message but when i try to run it in qtspim with the argument 'hello' in the argument box i get the output only letters and spaces are allowed in the string even though the program has identified there was an argument as it didn't just print out the usage error usage ./scroll string . i have tried to use the command line version of spim and step through execution line by line but am not sure how to go about 'injecting' a string into the program as if it was an argument in the original execution of the program. any help would be greatly appreciated","answers":[{"text":"i'm getting the same error did you anyone manage to fix it not sure what's wrong","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"are you using the most recent version of the code om the assign1.zip if so look to the frame set up and tear down in your isupper subprocess.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep i'm using version 1.5. i'll have a look at the isupper subprocess - but i copied the same prologue and epilogue from islower so i don't see why that would be an issue","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i'm getting a very similar error and i still don't know why","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i've managed to use jas' suggested debugging fix to temporary disable the need for command line argument and can run it inside qtspim now","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am getting the error write to unused memory-mapped io address 0xfffffffc everytime i try and run the scroll.s file. can someone give me an idea of what this sort of error refers to i have already tried using qtspim and can see the save registers which i am storing important results in are not changing but i am not sure what is causing this.","answers":[{"text":"email me your code and i'll have a look. hard to work out without more context.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you. i have sent my code","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hey adam i'm getting the same error what was the problem with yours hopefully i get ideas to fix mine","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"double check the prologue and epilogue of isupper make sure there is no old code floating around in your file that was what caused my error","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the scroll.c file there is one line where it says int which ch a ch is type char to achieve this in mips what should the method be should be translate both ch and a into ascii numbers and do the subtraction or we can just do subtraction between characters thanks a lot","answers":[{"text":"you can just simply do subtraction since actually ch and a are all treated as integers or u can say immediate numbers and that s also why when u try to assign a to a register you use li load immediates rather than other instructions.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"small possible mistake in scroll.s sorry if i'm wrong. islower is loading 1 to $v0 if true and 0 if false but in main_ptrs_cond after calling the islower function it is considering $v0 0 as being true i.e. in line 154 beqz $v0 main_ch_islower","answers":[{"text":"this has been fixed in the new .zip that is now live.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"also in line 174 the loop is being broken when $s0 lt $t0 i.e. current_length lt max_chars instead of current_length gt max_chars. sorry if i'm wrong once again","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"already been sent to jas. should be updated shortly. in the mean time changing blt to bge will fix the problem.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"cheers","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"now fixed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"just wondering the purpose of multiply by nrows here. i changed the c code so that nscols maxchars chrsize 1 and it was fine with handling an argument of 99 chars.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"see jas' answer.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yeah i'm also confused about this. shouldn't the number of columns in the bigstring matrix only need to be 1000 why are we multiplying it by nrows","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i am not sure why but this line is causing the error write to unused memory-mapped io address 0xfffffffc . i don't see the problem in this piece of code it is part of the starter code we were given.","answers":[{"text":"0xfffffffc is -4 ... so $sp is zero. check your prologues and epilogues contain correct loads and stores.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was just wondering why nscols is the product of nrows maxchars charsize 1 as opposed to just maxchars charsize 1 this currently give us an array bigstring 9 9000 as opposed to bigstring 9 1000 .","answers":[{"text":"yes ... you're right ... ignore the problem unless it's causing you to run out of memory. at least we gave you more space than you need in the matrix rather than less. and it doesn't affect the way you deal with the matrix. it's effectively just a large array of bytes which you treat as 9 x 1000-byte segments glued together one after the other.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"what is the final values of the delay numbers for the scroll.s file when submitting","answers":[{"text":"anything you want that produces a nice looking output as long as it is still relatively fast so it doesn't time out.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will only the latest submission be marked","answers":[{"text":"yes. you can use give as many times as you want before the due date and only the most recent will be marked.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"will we get marked down for not using nop even though mips works without it","answers":[{"text":"no you waon't get marked down ... as long as you put a statement at the top of your program saying that you know that the program may fail on real mips hardware.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"does it matter what the numbers in the delay function are set to when we submit","answers":[{"text":"only the output of the program is checked as long as the delay is not long enough to time out the auto tests delay does not matter at all.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"putchar to mips is putchar in mips simply print string syscall from a register which has a word stored in it or am i missing something huge","answers":[{"text":"the syscall number for print char is 11 with a byte stored in $a0.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i get an infinite loop with this error when i try running my program with spim. any idea about what it means/how to fix it","answers":[{"text":"the address is bad 0x00000020 looks like null plus 32 bytes which won't resolve. the other address looks like a data address has been multiplied by something plausibly 2 or 32. ask spim for the disassembly and work out what's at instruction 0x4003b0 and how you got there. qtspim gives you the disassembly in a window xspim lets you step through it. it may help you to step through with some idea of what the original code was doing to see if you've mistranslated something obvious.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm having trouble de bugging my code. i have gone step by step with multiple command line arguments such as hello hello etc but i have never even reached the point in the main function that i have written. a common error is if the first letter is lower case the program will come up with the write to unused memory mapped io address during the first step of the islower prologue. other times qtspim will just close without telling me anything usually around a store byte command.","answers":[{"text":"did you download your code before the revisions were made at 2 30pm on sun 19 august if so you will need to replace the provided part of the main subprocess with the new code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks yeah i was on the 1.4 code not the 1.5 code. i have now moved my code into the new file with not much success in debugging i am still getting errors before it even reached my code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"not entirely true you are responsible for the isupper subprocess have a look at that part of the code especially the stack frame setup and tear down.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks dylan. there was an issue in my uppercase epilogue. my debugging is moving forward now quick question would you have any idea why my qtspim on my mac despite giving it lots of different command line arguments it always seems to just give a space 0x32 i can see it in the register. however when i run the program on the cse system it receives the appropriate ascii codes.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"unfortunately i have no experience running qtspim on a mac so i am no help there.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do you use qtspim i have gone cat chars.s scroll.s gt exe.s 1521 qtspim -file exe.s and then specified hello as the run parameter but it still executes the code to do what it should do when no command line argument has been run where it prints usage blah blah blah . when i run with spim i have the write to unused memory-mapped io address but i don't know how to solve it without qtspim. cheers.","answers":[{"text":"did you download your code before the revisions were made at 2 30pm on sun 19 august if so you will need to replace the provided part of the main subprocess with the new code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no i didn't","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"please send your code and i'll have a look.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i just sent it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"good q. i am having similar problems","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"just wondering what the purpose of completing isupper when it is just the opposite of islower could we leave it out","answers":[{"text":"it's not the opposite . the two functions are measuring different things. maybe in this context it's not needed but it would definitely be useful and distinct from islower in other contexts. but it was mainly there to be an easy mark tog et started ... because it is so similar to islower.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i know how to implement something like display i j ' ' in mips after watching this week's lab video https //www.soln.io/s/hk1b3yuuq series_id rj-ufzvu... but i am not sure how to implement bigstring row col i chrsize 1 ' '. can someone explain how to do this","answers":[{"text":"jashank did a nice explanation of this he was getting a value rather than setting a value but there's only on line different in tuesday's lecture towards the of the first hour. the videos are on echo360 now and will be on youtube later today hopefully","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok ... jashank's explanation wasn't quite the same ... but principle of computing an offset by arithmetic on indices is the same","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm a bit confused by nscols being 9000. shouldn't the number of columns in the bigstring matrix only need to be 1000 why are we multiplying it by nrows","answers":[{"text":"maybe nscols is a crappy name. nselems might have been better. it's easiest to allocate the entire matrix in one statement .space 9000 which includes 9 rows of 1000 bytes each giving 9000 bytes. the alternative would be to have nine .space 1000 declarations one for each row.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"hi i noticed this as well but i am still confused by this since afterwards the label bigstring is declared to be .space 81000 nrows nscols which is nrows nrows maxchars chrsize 1 . does this make sense","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i've managed to get a working solution except i have a few issues with mine 1. using the given delay values in the c file makes my text not scroll and reducing it to 2000 100 for t4 and t5 makes it scroll very slowly. is this an issue with mips or my code 2. when i print a scrolling word i get my text blinker not sure what the right word to describe it is flying all over the place as opposed to running the c file solution which keeps it in the bottom left hand corner. doing a diff between the outputs between the c file and mips one has no differences except the mips has an extra line saying where my spim was loaded from . once again is this an issue with my code or mips or could it potentially be my home computer i am using the windows bash on ubuntu lol","answers":[{"text":"delay spim is several times maybe 1000x slower than the same code running natively. you almost certainly want to turn down the delay numbers. i gather microsoft don't know how to implement a standard terminal. try a real ansi-compatible terminal emulator like putty or hop onto a system running a real os and try there. otherwise good job","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"isn't that tearing because of the lag","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how can u use all_chars array when its not in the scroll.s code it keeps saying its undefined","answers":[{"text":"did you create exe.s by combining the code and data files. if you're trying to run scroll.s by itself it will not have the all_chars array.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you but how do i install spim if it doesn't let me through vlab","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you can find it here .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how to run the.s file with a command line argument","answers":[{"text":"e.g. spim -file scroll.s hello there where hello there is a single command-line argument","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"but when i run qtspim -file exe.s ./scroll hello it said no such file hello","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you didn't say that you were using qtspim . i haven't been able to work out how to enter command-line arguments in qtspim . if someone else has maybe they can enlighten us. in the meantime the simplest solution would be to modify the main program to set thestring manually to whatever command-line argument string you want. comment out all of the argc/argv processing leading up to this.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"you can set command line arguments from qtspim in simulator - gt run parameters.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"any idea how to get the command line argument to work when you use the 'step by step' mode setting the command line argument in 'run parameters' only seems to work when you run the whole program.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"just set a breakpoint somewhere early in the mips code. then you can run the whole program and it will stop at the breakpoint. once it reaches the breakpoint you can step through the code.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"when i compare the output of my .s file with the .c file there's a difference ' lt loaded /home/cs1521/lib/spim/exceptions.s ' which i think is an extra line when running spim how could i remove that line of output to see whether there's a real difference between outputs","answers":[{"text":"spim -file scroll.s message sed -e 1d gt observed.output","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"scroll speed too slow","answers":[{"text":"i just posted a notice on this. the solution is to tweak the loop bounds in the delay function until you get acceptable scrolling speed.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"do you know how to run the program with a command line argument i could only manually change a0 and a1","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"make 1521 spim -file exe.s string isnt it this","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks i think by changing the value of the delay number could help","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"typo in scroll.s gt string mush be lt instead of gt string must be lt","answers":[{"text":"your message didn't come though quite right but i'm guessing you thought it should be lt rather than lt . the buffer is 100 bytes long which allows for at most 99 visible chars plus the ' 0' to terminate the strings.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh oz no i meant scroll.s has 'mush' instead of 'must'","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's too late to fix it in assign1.zip. everyone will have already downloaded it won't they with the incorrect message. maybe some people will decide to fix it ... so we'll have to allow either spelling in the test cases.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"oh yeah i noticed that too","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i was wondering when the mips code for the assignment would be released","answers":[{"text":"the mips code has already been released read the assessment 1 spec for the download link.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i am a little confused about the part for handling the oversize error why there a 2 comparison. why we can not jump to main_thelength_ge_maxchars directly and print the error message but need to first jump to main_ptrs_f and then jump to main_thelength_ge_maxchars . thank you very muchhhhhhhhhh","answers":[{"text":"because that's not what the c does - remember the assignment is to take a blob of c and translate it to spim-flavoured mips assembly. you could deviate from a literal interpretation of the c but you must explain why you've done what you've done.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i believe there is another error in almost all the epilogue sections of all the functions except delay where the stack pointer is assigned using load word. thus when the function returned the stack pointer was 0 when stepped through with qtspim. for me this meant that any time i tried to run the starter code it would simply crash qtspim on both cse through vlab and my machine most likely due to its use in the prologue of the next function. it was quite frustrating trying to locate this issue. after changing all 5 occurrences to load address as shown below it appears to be working correctly and no longer crashing qtspim.","answers":[{"text":"additionally the given starter code also does not store thestring correctly in memory. here $t1 has not been used yet and is 0. instead $s2 should be used as it is currently storing the relevant ch.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"both these issues are now fixed in the provided code. thanks for the heads-up","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello on line 73 i.e. the frame bit of the main function's text in scroll.s is there any particular reason why $s0 and $s1 are not included when it looks like they are included as per lines 113 and 114 unless we're supposed to be putting that in there ourselves. or am i misunderstanding what's going on thanks","answers":[{"text":"the line ends with a ... as in and everything else the comment isn't too important but you can update it if you wish.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do we print the escape sequence to clear the screen can i still use the regular string printing syscall even though the string isn't null-terminated","answers":[{"text":"the .asciiz directive is allows you to write a sequence of nul-terminated ascii bytes by definition it is a nul-terminated string. in other words these two declarations are equivalent clear1 .asciiz 033 h 033 2j clear2 .byte 0x1b 0x5b 0x48 0x1b 0x5b 0x32 0x4a 0x00 if you look in the data section up around address 0x10011088 you'll see exactly this is the case -- 0x10011080 0x00000064 0x00002328 0x1b485b1b 0x004a325b note that the bytes written into the section there are reversed within the word. that is we wrote out bytes 0x1b 0x5b 0x48 0x1b but the word at 0x10011088 is 0x1b485b1b . the terminating nul is in the word at 0x1001108c .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"another quick question how do you print individual chars since it doesn't seem to be any of the listed syscall functions edit nevermind i figured out its syscall 11 which i don't think is in the lecture notes.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's worthwhile having a look at the syscalls table in the spim instruction set document.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ahh thanks. that makes sense.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"one more question about the assignment - one of my students has used some $t registers where they should be $s registers and then in function calls had pushed both s and t registers onto the stack to preserve values. they were wondering if they would be marked down for that and therefore whether they should spend the time going through and refactoring or not.","answers":[{"text":"harmless ... no need to change the code","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"one of my students has finished their assignment and notices that while their text is scrolling the cursor jumps around to random points in the text and there's a lot of flickering. there is no difference in the output from the mips file or c file i'm guessing its just the terminal's behaviour. they seem quite worried about it so i just want to check that's fine","answers":[{"text":"that's fine. how fast have they got the scrolling going if i make it fast enough on my mac in a local terminal window i get exactly the same problem. we're actually going to comment out the call to delay when we test their programs. why sit there waiting minutes for the tests to run when you could run them in sub seconds.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"awesome thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"really odd error i've got - rowloop beq $s0 $a1 endrowloop lt some code here gt endrowloop and qtspim is giving the error instruction references undefined symbol at 0x004001cc 0x004001cc 0x12050000 beq $16 $5 0 endrowloop-0x004001cc 158 beq $s0 $a1 endrowloop basically it thinks my endrowloop doesn't exist update this line of code only breaks in qtspim","answers":[{"text":"hi john it's had to debug from a comment send your code to me and i'll have a look.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ah i've figured it out. one of my labels was indented for readability and qtspim really hated it for some reason","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello i received this error message when i was trying to merge isi.s and the data file . can you help me fix it","answers":[{"text":"datafile.s is placeholder which signifies that you should use whatever .s file you would like to merge with isi.s to test your code. for example you might try first with matrix.s. or maybe one of the mx.s files in the test folder","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how are you today i have a question in regards to lab 5 exercise 2. why are the stack frames different than previous labs thank you. raymond.","answers":[{"text":"there are many different way to setup a stack frame all doing the same thing. the course and labs are setup to show you many different ways.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi how are you today i hope you are well i have a question in regards to week 5 lab exercise 2. why am i not able to run the isi.c program it keeps saying that a fatal error has occured as matrix.h is not found. are you able to explain why i'm getting this error thanks raymond.","answers":[{"text":"you need to have isi.c and matrix.h in the same folder and run make then run ./isi","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do i submit the 2 files which are both under different subdirectories","answers":[{"text":"try copy 2 files into the same directory then submit","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"the test command for part 2 of the lab might be $ 1521 check matrix.s","answers":[{"text":"and now it is ... looks like someone beat me to fixing it.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"having trouble getting the home computing working also if you want to work at home you'll need to download the mips emulator. executables for qtspim are available for most operating systems from http //spimsimulator.sourceforge.net/ . if you want to use the spim command-line interface on your own machine you'll need to download the source code from sourceforge and compile it yourself after modifying the makefile in the spim/ subdirectory of the source code to tell make where to install the executable and the exception handling code. after doing that installation is as simple as running lt nobr gt make make install lt /nobr gt . this is true on macos with gcc installed and linux. i haven't tried to install spim on windows. this didnt make a lot of sense to me unfortunately. how do i compile the soure code where do i find it i downloaded the zip not sure what im looking for maybe the spim.cpp file how do i modify the makefile as below after modifying the makefile in the spim/ subdirectory of the source code to tell make where to install the executable and the exception handling code. got lost here. im using a mac but i don't think i have installed gcc. is any of this necessary if i'm using tigervnc thanks.","answers":[{"text":"it sounds easier for you to use vla","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i'm a bit confused as to what it means when it says simplified c does have jump-and-remember-where-you-came-from . do you mean like a jump-and-link in mips also what is the c syntax for this thanks","answers":[{"text":"i was referring to function calls. but as i hope you're starting to see c functions calls do a lot more than just this. feel free to argue that my analogy is crappy","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks for your quick reply i'm still a little bit confused about how to perform function calls in simplified c. should we call regularly using goto or some other method thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it would be very difficult to implement function calls in c just using goto . just make a regular function call knowing that it maps to jal function followed by some stack setup. and return maps to set $v0 clean up the stack frame then jr $ra .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi i currently have a non-working draft of scroll.s . when submitting my assignment draft via give i'm given the following error message submission assign1 ------------------------------ files found scroll.s ------------------------------ assign1 dryrun checking syntax of 'scroll.s'... cat /web/cs1521/18s2/assignments/assign1/code/chars.s permission denied submission test failed. continue with submission y/n y ls -l /web/cs1521/18s2/assignments/assign1 ... drwxr-x--- 2 cs1521 cs1521 4096 aug 19 14 29 code/ .. i'm not sure if this is an issue or not. i don't expect my submission to pass the test anyway in its current state but i thought i should raise it just in case. best joe","answers":[{"text":"whoops i'll fix that now. the dryrun test just passes your code through spim to make sure your syntax and labels are correct. it's not a substitute for real testing we'll have real tests up within the next few days.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i asked both of my classes about lecture attendance as well. the general consensus is that most are quite satisfied with the quality and promptness of lecture recordings. a frequent comment was that playing the lectures at 2x speed makes it appear as if jas is speaking at a normal speed. other benefits mentioned include not needing to travel to uni being able to rewatch certain parts of the lecture and skip parts as well. the latter isn't so much about lecture content but rather a student apparently introduces himself as raymond and frequently asks long questions that derail the lecture. perhaps it might be more economical to make all lecture streams web streams in the future. i also have a number of students who have previously completed comp2121 and comp1521 has not been excluded for them for some reason. i even have a student who is currently enrolled in comp6447 and i can tell he really does not belong in comp1521. i think the entire prereq/exclusion business is a bit of a mess at the moment. also regarding the quiz about lecture pace i understood this to mean the rate at which content was introduced. however a number of students seem to have interpreted this as how fast jas talks . without clarification the quiz results might not be entirely accurate.","answers":[{"text":"i second the exclusion comment. some of my friends and others i have heard of have taken comp1917/1927/2121/others and were told by the student office to do comp1521 anyway because that's what the degree says after changing degrees etc. a lot of them find the subject a bit of a breeze as a result... but i feel like in time the possibility for this to happen will be ruled out eventually","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"jas i asked a lot of students individually this week about lectures and a lot of them 50 said they usually prefer to watch lectures later at home because they can watch it at 2x speed and do it in their own time/pace. about 25 of them said they still go to lectures the other 25 said they just weren t keeping up and planned to catch up. i think it s worth noting that there s a portion of second years that didn t take this subject last year for whatever reason and are able to cruise through the labs/content without attending lectures or doing much revision as they feel a lot more comfortable with programming at this stage. they seem quite switched on in the tutes and labs and are usually first to finish too. most people said they were quite comfortable with the lab this week a fair few of them finished early the tut content seemed to be pretty easy to follow for almost all of them","answers":[{"text":"the point about 2nd years is interesting. if that were a general issue then we could change the pre-reqs to require an extra programming course and then talk about the implementation of linked data structures . however we are constrained by the fact that other schools e.g. eet have comp1911- gt comp1521 as their only required comp courses and they're not going to be willing to add another course. it might be worth drilling down to find out how students who have just done either comp1511 or comp1911 are finding the course. is comp1911 sufficient preparation. as for why cse students might do the course in 2nd year ... some of the programs e.g. binf and seng have it scheduled in 2nd year in the program description. for those students it's a dip into how computer systems work under the hood and that's about all they need. these degrees have other constraints about courses to take in year 1. also i was trying to balance the size of classes in the two semesters rather than enrolments one semester being twice as large as in the other semester .","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i taught comp1911 last semester as well as the bridging course those that did both seem like they're coping just fine in comp1911 whenever i see them and ask although that might be just because the bridging course takes students in a first in and best dressed manner. i would say comp1911 has enough preparation to cope with comp1521 in general though we didn't cover structs in overly great detail nor did we make them to use them as much as compared to comp1511 pointers were only used for passing things by reference/value and we tended not to go into detail about the layout of things in memory beyond bits bytes and size... but i would say students who got over 60 in comp1911 seemingly quite a few are well equipped to tackle comp1521","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"honestly i m not sure why comp1911 exist for eet students. imo eet students should be doing comp1511. i m curious to know why eet students are told to do comp1911 and not forced in comp1511.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"videos hi guys as part of a fun side-project hugh chan and i are developing a tool that lets you easily create and share educational videos all in-browser khan-academy-esque digital whiteboard videos . we've been making some pre-lab content for 1521 which you may have seen this/last week and we'll likely make more in the coming weeks hopefully of improving quality . hugh and i aren't tutoring 1521 i tutor 2521 hugh tutors 2511 and we don't want the vids to feel like they're coming from outsiders. we'd love for you to be involved if anyone is keen to make content with us please find me on facebook or email me jakehenryfitz gmail.com alternatively we made a slack channel for people that want to make videos https //join.slack.com/t/soln-creators/shared_invi ... any feedback is also appreciated we've found making content really fun and rewarding so far we had 700 students watch last week and 100 hours of playback .","answers":[{"text":"that's very cool jake and hugh i saw a lot of students using the videos last week in the lab.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"awesome to hear let us know if you want to make a video in the coming weeks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in the lab the students seems to only need to implement two versions of factorial but need to submit three .s files. i assume this is a mistake and they only need to submit two .s files. the recursive version of factorial is missing do the students not need to do this anymore imo i though the recursive function was a good way to explain the need for a stack.","answers":[{"text":"i thought i'd fixed all the places it was expecting them to submit fac3.s ... is there anywhere left where it asks for fac3.s apart from the bottom of the lab spec which i just fixed i didn't get far enough in lectures to justify getting them to implement the stack frame themselves. doing that is an important aspect of the recursive version. i'll do something with recursion for next week's lab.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i only saw a mention of fac3 in the bottom of the lab spec. i wasn't sure if i had to explain the stack in the tutorial this week since i saw a large explanation in the lab. i guess i'll try to cover it if i can.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i've had a lot of students asking me if/when solutions of labs will be released - what should i say will they be released soon just before finals or should they not expect them at all","answers":[{"text":"not in the next few weeks. i'll upload them once i get up-to-date with everything else. probably during the mid-term break .","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i seem to be getting a difference in answers b/w my float values after the decimal. what could be the problem expected output my output any help appreciated thanks","answers":[{"text":"i had the same issue before because i put the frac exp and sign the wrong way round when defining the bit fields so that may be the problem look back at q1 of the lab","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"it's hard to tell what's actually the problem without seeing your code but put the result you're getting is very likely to have the last 8 bits in the fraction part unset. i was able to generate the same float using 0 10000111 11111111111111100000000 using a working calculator. perhaps look through your code and try to work out why it might be doing that but printing the 'bits' value out correctly.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"in the sum.c exercise in this lecture there is the following prototype at the top of the file int sumof int int this doesn't actually make any mention of the variable names given as input to the function. is this legal in prototypes in c","answers":[{"text":"yes prototypes exist only to give the compiler an idea of the existence of a function and the types it takes in and returns. of course you need to provide variable names when implementing a function.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i noticed this a bit last week but especially this week my monday class seems very confused ... students haven't seen enough about data representation or bitwise operations for some of the lab questions because that's not covered until tomorrow's lecture. i'm not sure how to fix this other than to cover that content in tutorials which cuts into interesting tutorial discussion or in labs which cuts into lab time i don't like those solutions.","answers":[{"text":"i noticed this today as well a lot of students needed walking through the warmup exercise and didn't understand 2s complement and that you can do binary operations on 'int' values in c. once they understood that i saw some clever solutions to the warmup. i can't find any labs under the webcms3 marking page is the marking set up for labs","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i too noticed that a lot of the students didn't understand the concept of negative numbers 2's complement etc. another thing that students didn't understand was casting might be worth explaining casting in the lecture if it hasn't already.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hello where can we find the tutorial solusion","answers":[{"text":"the tutorial questions are replaced by new version with solutions early in the week after the questions are looked at in the tute. go back to tutorials gt week 01 and you should find the questions plus answers.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i have just completed first weeks labs but i am not able to access the quiz. sorry for the inconvienience.","answers":[{"text":"i can't see any reason why you shouldn't be able to access it. there's a link to quiz 2 in the right-hand sidebar on the course homepage. this link only becomes visible when you log in.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"is it possible to get a due date extension arrived in sydney late last night just need a day or two to catch up on all the lectures quiz and lab exercises. understandable if not","answers":[{"text":"do them asap. and let me know when done.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i have just completed first weeks labs but i am not able to access the quiz. sorry for the inconvienience.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"also could you provide some instructions for home computing what are mips and spim should i be worrying about this now or will it pop up in future lectures or will week 1 lectures cover this all thanks.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"home computing varies a little depending on your operating system. there's some instructions here https //taggi.cse.unsw.edu.au/faq/accessing_your_files/ mips is assembly programming. we'll start it in a few weeks you don't need to worry too much about it yet and you will learn how to do it in lectures and labs.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"i think you can find some info about spim under the documentation tab.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"are bonus marks arbitrary for each tutor or only assignable in the case of challenge exercises ie is it possible to get bonus marks for this weeks lab","answers":[{"text":"marks are never arbitrary . it's possible to get an a for the week 01 lab. the wording says must complete any challenges if there are no challenges you have to do something well beyond what the lab was asking and discover something interesting. e.g. for this week's lab investigate and explain with empirical results the differences between the various approaches.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"how do we show to you that we have done something interesting is it through our blogs","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"amaze your tutor when you demo your program in the lab as you are required to do. or at least you're require to demo ... not necessarily amaze.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i think that the command cs1521/bin/check cat4 is missing from the lab spec. was this a mistake or was it intentional without it we can't autotest cat4.c","answers":[{"text":"why can't you autotest it doesn't the command cs1521/bin/check cat4 work","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"no i meant that it's not mentioned in the lab spec above. we aren't instructed to use it to test our solution which is why i got confused. we are told to use cs1521/bin/check cat1 cs1521/bin/check cat2 and cs1521/bin/check cat3 for questions cat1 cat2 and cat3 respectively but nothing for cat4. the command cs1521/bin/check cat4 once executed works completely fine","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"use your initiative. you should always test your work. there's a tool to test your work. qed i.e. i was assuming that i wouldn't need to tell you do it.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"alright sir i understand. thank you.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i don't understand how the test scripts are working with these exercises. when i run the test i get the following z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ cs1521/bin/check cat2 running tests on cat2 ... failed test 1 check differences using diff tests/1.exp tests/1.out failed test 2 check differences using diff tests/2.exp tests/2.out failed test 3 check differences using diff tests/3.exp tests/3.out failed test 4 check differences using diff tests/4.exp tests/4.out failed test 5 check differences using diff tests/5.exp tests/5.out failed test 6 check differences using diff tests/6.exp tests/6.out z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ diff tests/2.exp tests/2.out 1 2c1 lt a simple file lt with two lines --- gt cannot open source file. exiting z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ however if i run my programs specifying input and output files from within the tests folder it seems to run fine z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ cat tests/2.exp a simple file with two lines z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ cat tests/2.out cat tests/2.out no such file or directory z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ ./cat2 tests/2.exp tests/2.out z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$ cat tests/2.out a simple file with two lines z5200681 vx2 /tmp_amd/glass/export/glass/4/z5200681/comp1521/week01/lab$","answers":[{"text":"i see the issue now. even though the comments in the cat template files imply we are opening files i needed to just use stdin and stdout for cat1 2 and 3","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"hi dr. shepherd i have a question in regards to week 1 lab part 3. so we have to write a code that reads the file content to a string with fgets and write into an output with fputs thank you. raymond.","answers":[{"text":"yes.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"correct. but it doesn't read the entire file content into the string if that's what you meant. it reads line-by-line.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"can we give multiple submissions or is it a one time only","answers":[{"text":"multiple submissions","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"for the tutorial my tutor said i could get the bonus marks by for example writing more tests and a file to run those tests. but how do i submit this additional file for marking","answers":[{"text":"if you're doing this as a bonus exercise showing your tutor in next week's lab should be fine.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ok thanks","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm having trouble submitting this lab. with the give command gs_extract no amp assignmap in spec files login z5115499 class cs1531 classrun error detected while scanning spec files for assignment lab01 last system error no such file or directory using webcms classrun directory /import/ravel/3/cs1521/18s2.work/lab01/thu18-tabla/ does not exist login z5115499 stuid 5115499 class cs1521 last system error no such file or directory in both cases no submission has been made. i'm not so sure if this is an error on my part or if the submitted files goes to the thu18-tabla directory and it doesn't exist yet.","answers":[{"text":"hmmm ... where did that lab come from yes you're right that thu18-tabla wasn't mentioned in any of the give/sms files. i've attempted to hack it for lab01. could you let me know if it now works i'll need to ask ask the give/sms maintainers what the correct fix is.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"yep your hack works thanks","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"if i understand the error correctly it looks like you were trying to give to cs1531 instead of cs1521.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"ooh nice catch yeah when i using the give command i was giving it to the wrong class but then it should have worked for the webcms.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"how do i check and confirm that my lab exercises have been submitted i remembered that i did submit my labs as soon as i've finished them during the lab time but under the check submission tab it says classrun no record of any submission for this assignment lab01 i also tried checking the collect submission tab and it says classrun your submission for lab01 not yet marked. so i'm assuming the above sentence means that i did submit but i remembered from 1511 that you can check your lab submission using the grades button between your name and the blog button so i checked there and it was empty. i am really confused can someone clarify thanks so much.","answers":[{"text":"the submissions for the monday 1pm lab ended up in the wrong place. someone had forgotten to set the semester to 18s2 so they all ended up in the 18s1 submission directories i'll move them to the correct place this morning and then hopefully you'll be able to see them.","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"cheers","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"im having trouble downloading the warandpeace.txt the cmd said permission denied .","answers":[{"text":"when i was working from home i had permission denied for trying to store the result in /tmp/wp.out. so basically the command below was not working for me. ./cat1 lt /home/cs1521/web/18s2/labs/week01/warandpeace.txt gt /tmp/wp.out but the next command time ./cat1 lt /home/cs1521/web/18s2/labs/week01/warandpeace.txt gt /dev/null worked for me. also doing a quick search online i found this link https //www.archive.org/stream/warandpeace030164mbp/warandpeace030164mbp_djvu.txt","theta":1,"count":0},{"text":"thank you very much your command is correct","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"i'm having trouble getting dcc on my laptop as my package manager cannot find dcc. is it okay if i use gcc","answers":[{"text":"dcc is a python script that andrew taylor wrote so it won't be in any package manager. since it's a wrapper around gcc clang you might be able to get it to work on your laptop by grabbing the python script and whatever else it needs and tweaking it yourself. using gcc is fine. if you can use gdb as well then you won't miss dcc too much. an alternative is to use vlab on your laptop and then you get the full cse environment.","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"http //www.cse.unsw.edu.au/ cs1521/ redirects to the 18s1 webcms","answers":[{"text":"fixed now","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"deleted","answers":[{"text":"no ... it requires me to make the course visible to students. which i've now done. does it work","theta":1,"count":0}]},{"question":"minor correction for q 4b p.x is interpreted as p.x post-fix operators have higher precedence than pre-fix","answers":[{"text":"ok ... i'll take your word for it ... fixed in the solutions.","theta":1,"count":0}]}]}